[INTRIGUING MUSIC]
[引人入胜的音乐]
DAVID MALAN: All right, so this is CS50.
大卫·马兰：好的，这是CS50。
And this is week 1, zero index, so to speak.
这是第一周，从零开始，可以这么说。
And it's not every day that you can say that you've learned a new language,
你并不每天都能说你学会了一门新语言，
but today is that day.
但今天就是那一天。
Today, we explore a more traditional and older language called C.
今天，我们将探索一门更传统和更古老的语言，叫做C。
And rest assured that even if what you're about to see-- no pun intended--
请放心，即使你即将看到的东西，没有双关语的意思，
looks very cryptic, very unusual, particularly if you're
看起来非常神秘，非常不寻常，特别是如果你
among those less comfortable, cling to the ideas from last week,
是那些不太舒服的人，坚持上周的想法，
week zero, wherein we talked about some of those fundamentals of functions
第零周，我们谈了一些关于函数的基本知识
and loops and conditionals, all of which are coming back today.
循环和条件语句，今天都会回来。
Indeed, whereas last week, and with problem set 0,
事实上，上周，还有问题集0，
we focused on learning how to program with Scratch,
我们专注于学习如何用Scratch编程，
which, again, you might have played with as a younger student days back.
同样，你可能在小时候就玩过它。
Today, we focus on C instead.
今天，我们将专注于C语言。
But along the way, we're going to focus, as always, frankly,
但在此过程中，我们将像往常一样，坦率地说，
on learning how to solve problems.
专注于学习如何解决问题。
But among the goals for today and really on an entire class like this
但今天以及像这样的一整门课的目标之一
is just to give you week after week all the more tools for your toolkit,
就是每周给你更多工具，
so to speak, via which to do exactly that.
可以这么说，通过这些工具，就可以做到这一点。
So for instance today, we'll learn how to solve problems all the more
所以比如今天，我们将学习如何更好地解决问题
so with functions, as per last week.
用函数，就像上周一样。
We'll do the same with variables.
我们也会用变量做同样的事情。
We'll do the same with conditionals, with loops, and with more.
我们也会用条件语句、循环以及更多内容做同样的事情。
But we'll also learn at the end of today's class
但我们也会在今天的课程结束时学习
really how not to solve problems.
如何解决不了问题。
It turns out as powerful as Macs, PCs, cell phones are nowadays,
事实证明，如今的Mac、PC、手机再强大，
there's actually certain things that they can't do very well
它们也有一些事情做得不好
and information they can't represent very well.
也有一些信息它们无法很好地表示。
And that actually leads to a lot of real-world problems, both past
这实际上会导致很多现实世界的问题，无论是过去
and surely future.
还是未来。
So more on what we're not going to be able to do with programming before
所以我们将在编程方面无法做到的事情，
long.
过不了多久就会了解。
But beyond that, let's come back to this picture here.
但除此之外，让我们回到这张图片。
So this was the very first program that I wrote,
这是我写的第一个程序，
that you wrote presumably in some form.
你可能也写过类似的程序。
And all it does is say "Hello, world."
它所做的就是说“你好，世界”。
But as promised, today, this puzzle piece, or these puzzle pieces together,
但正如承诺的那样，今天，这块拼图，或者这些拼图加起来，
are going to very quickly start to look more like this.
会很快开始变得更像这样。
And I've deliberately color coded it in a way so that the text on the screen
我故意用颜色编码，让屏幕上的文本
now kind of resembles the puzzle piece.
看起来有点像拼图。
So if I go back, notice that we had this, when green flag clicked puzzle
所以如果我后退，你会注意到，我们有这个，当绿色旗帜被点击时，这个拼图
piece, mostly in yellow with the green flag, that sort of kicks off
大部分是黄色的，上面有绿色的旗帜，它启动了
the whole process once you actually click
整个过程，当你实际上点击
the button at top right of Scratch's user interface.
Scratch用户界面右上角的按钮。
And then there's the purple block which actually is the verb, the action,
然后是紫色的块，它实际上是动词，动作，
the function that does something.
执行某些操作的函数。
So if I bring us back over to what we're about to see today,
所以如果我们回到我们今天将要看到的，
there's going to be some boilerplate, so to speak, some orange text here
将会有一些模板，可以这么说，屏幕上有一些橙色的文本
on the screen that for now you just type and take for granted,
屏幕上，你现在只需输入并默认接受，
like you need to write your code like that.
就像你需要那样写代码。
But more interesting is going to be the purple.
但更有趣的是紫色。
And we're going to see today that the function previously
而我们今天将会看到，之前
called "say" in Scratch is now called "printf" in this language called C.
在Scratch中被称为“say”的函数现在在这门叫做C的语言中被称为“printf”。
But in white here, you'll see similar text to our white oval
但这里用白色，你会看到与上周的白椭圆相似的文本，
last week, whereby that's where user input, like your input
那里是用户输入，就像你的输入
as the programmer, can actually go.
作为程序员，实际上可以去的地方。
So there's a lot of distraction.
所以有很多干扰。
And honestly, it's these kinds of things that
说实话，正是这些事情
tend to distract and get frustrating early on when
在学习编程初期容易让人分心和沮丧。
learning to code for the first time.
第一次学习编程。
But the ideas, most importantly, are going to be the same.
但最重要的想法会是一样的。
So how are we going to go about using this.
那么我们该如何使用它呢？
Well, it turns out, like last week, you're
事实证明，就像上周一样，你
going to start writing something called source code.
将开始编写一些叫做源代码的东西。
So code as we know it, quote, unquote, is more technically called
所以我们所知道的代码，可以这么说，更技术地称为
"source code."
“源代码”。
That's what you and I as humans actually write.
那是我们人类实际编写的。
And indeed it might look a little something like we just saw.
它确实可能看起来有点像我们刚刚看到的。
But unfortunately, computers only speak this, binary--
但不幸的是，计算机只能识别这种语言，二进制，
zeros and ones-- more properly known as machine code, in other words,
零和一，更确切地说，是机器码，换句话说，
those same patterns of zeros and ones last week, someone guessed,
上周，有人猜到，这些相同的零和一的模式，
print out "hello, world" on the screen because one of those patterns
在屏幕上打印出“hello, world”，因为其中一个模式
is an H. Another pattern is an E, an L, and L, and an O, and so forth.
是一个H。另一个模式是E，L，L，O，等等。
And then other patterns of those zeros and ones are commands or instructions
然后，那些零和一的其他模式是命令或指令
to the computer that literally say, show H-E-L-L-O comma "world" on the screen.
对计算机来说，它们实际上就是说，在屏幕上显示H-E-L-L-O逗号“world”。
But machine code would not be nearly as much fun
但机器码写起来远没有那么有趣
to write if it were indeed in zeros and ones.
如果它确实是用零和一写的。
Entirely for us, ideally, you and I are going
完全是为了我们，理想情况下，你和我都将
to write source code, which conceptually is sort of up here, high level.
编写源代码，从概念上讲，它在更高层次。
But we're going to need a program to convert it to the lower-level machine
但我们需要一个程序把它转换成更低级的机器
code so that we don't spend our lives actually having to read and write
代码，这样我们就不必花费一生去读写
zeros and ones, which back in the day, kind of in yesteryear,
零和一，在过去，在往昔，
you kind of did with things called punch cards
你用一种叫做打孔卡的东西来做
and holes on physical sheets of paper.
以及物理纸张上的孔。
We're beyond that because after years and years of innovation,
我们已经超越了这一点，因为经过多年的创新，
folks have given us higher-level languages instead.
人们给了我们更高级的语言。
So here's what we're going to need to do today.
所以今天我们需要做的是：
If at the end of the day you and I are writing source code
如果我们最终编写源代码
but we want machine code as output, we need something
但我们想要机器码作为输出，我们需要一些东西
in the middle that's going to convert that source code to machine code.
在中间，它将把源代码转换为机器代码。
You and I are not going to have to learn or talk
你我都不需要再学习或谈论
about really any more zeros and ones.
任何关于 0 和 1 的东西了。
And the type of program we're going to start using today and introduce you to
我们今天将开始使用并向大家介绍的一种程序类型
is called a compiler.
叫做编译器。
So a compiler is a program that translates one language to another.
所以编译器是一个将一种语言翻译成另一种语言的程序。
And it can be any two languages.
这两种语言可以是任何两种语言。
But today, and often, we'll talk about it in the context of source code
但今天，通常我们会从源代码的角度来谈论它
to machine code.
到机器代码。
So this is Apple or Google or Microsoft or folks from other companies
所以这是苹果、谷歌、微软或其他公司的员工
or even volunteers who have written software that do this conversion.
甚至还有志愿者编写了进行这种转换的软件。
You and I are essentially going to download a free compiler
你我基本上要下载一个免费的编译器
and use it to actually get our computer to understand the source
并用它来让我们的计算机真正理解源
code that you and I write in these higher-level languages.
你我用这些高级语言编写的代码。
So where are we going to do that?
那我们要在哪里做呢？
Well, we could actually give you instructions
嗯，我们可以给你一些指令
and you could download the appropriate free open-source software
你可以下载相应的免费开源软件
onto your own Mac or PC.
到你的 Mac 或 PC 上。
The reality is that creates so many technical support headaches because we
现实情况是，这会造成很多技术支持上的麻烦，因为我们
all have slightly different computers.
每个人都有略微不同的电脑。
We all have slightly different versions of Windows or macOS or Linux
我们每个人都有略微不同的 Windows、macOS 或 Linux 版本
or other operating systems.
或其他操作系统。
And that, too, tends to be a distraction at the beginning of any course
而且这也会成为任何课程开始时的干扰
like this or learning programming.
比如这个课程或学习编程。
So we're going to use the cloud instead.
所以我们打算使用云。
We're going to use a URL of the form https://cs50.dev.
我们将使用 https://cs50.dev 形式的网址。
And what this will do for you is put inside of your browser window
它会为你做的事情是在你的浏览器窗口内
absolutely everything you need for the course, but it's going to use software,
放置你上这门课所需的一切，但它会使用软件，
software called Visual Studio code, otherwise known as VS Code,
名为 Visual Studio Code 的软件，也称为 VS Code，
that's actually free itself.
本身也是免费的。
It's very popular in industry.
它在业界非常流行。
It's what "real" programmers use every day.
这是“真正的”程序员每天使用的工具。
But it's a cloud-based version thereof.
但它是一个基于云的版本。
And so everything will just work for you out of the box.
所以一切都会为你开箱即用。
But toward the end of CS50, the goal is going
但在 CS50 结束时，目标是
to be to get you off of CS50's infrastructure,
让你离开 CS50 的基础设施，
to get you to download this freely available software onto your own Mac
让你下载这个免费提供的软件到你的 Mac 上
or PC if you so choose so that those training wheels, so to speak,
或者如果你选择的话，也可以下载到你的 PC 上，这样那些所谓的辅助轮
can come off.
就可以取下来了。
And then even if you never take another class again,
然后即使你再也不上其他课了，
you don't need any class's infrastructure moving forward.
你也不需要任何课程的基础设施来继续前进。
You'll have everything you want and need on your own Mac or PC.
你将在自己的 Mac 或 PC 上拥有你想要和需要的一切。
But for now, it'll save us a bit of time.
但现在，这会为我们节省一些时间。
So in just a bit, I'm going to go to that URL myself on my computer.
所以过一会儿，我将在自己的电脑上访问这个网址。
And I and you will see a user interface that
我和你将会看到一个用户界面，
looks a little something like this.
看起来有点像这样。
The colors might be different based on your settings.
颜色可能会根据你的设置有所不同。
Fonts might be different, and so forth.
字体也可能不同，等等。
But in general, it consists of a few different regions.
但总的来说，它由几个不同的区域组成。
So over here at the top is where we are going to start writing code today.
所以这里上面是我们今天将开始编写代码的地方。
So it's a tabbed interface like any number of programs nowadays.
所以它是一个带标签的界面，就像如今许多程序一样。
And this is that same C code we saw a moment ago.
而这是我们刚才看到的相同的 C 代码。
So this is where, in a moment, I'm going to start to type it.
所以这里就是我过一会儿将开始输入的地方。
Over here at the bottom is what we're going to call
这里底部是我们即将要称作
a terminal window, or a console.
终端窗口或控制台。
And the terminal window is where we're going to type commands
而终端窗口就是我们用来输入命令的地方
for compiling our code, for running our code.
用来编译我们的代码，用来运行我们的代码。
And we'll see today a contrast between a graphical-user interface,
今天我们将看到图形用户界面
or GUI, which has menus and icons and things
即 GUI 之间的一个对比，GUI 有菜单、图标和一些东西
you click and are very familiar with, versus a command-line interface,
你可以点击它们，你对此非常熟悉，与命令行界面
or CLI.
即 CLI 之间的对比。
And so we're using both of these together.
所以我们一起使用这两个东西。
And command-line interface just means, down here, you only use your keyboard.
命令行界面只是意味着，在这里，你只能使用键盘。
You can click, click, click if you want with your mouse.
你可以用鼠标点击、点击、点击，如果你愿意的话。
It's not going to generally do much because a command-line interface takes
它通常不会做太多，因为命令行界面会接收
commands at the keyboard.
键盘输入的命令。
So in a weird sense, it's going to feel like taking
所以从某种奇怪的角度来说，这会让人感觉像是
a step backwards from the Macs, the PCs, the iPhones, and Android phones we all
从我们每个人使用的 Mac、PC、iPhone 和安卓手机后退了一步，这些手机都是非常图形化的。
have, which are very graphical.
这些手机都是非常图形化的。
But it turns out, once you become a "computer" person or a programmer,
但事实证明，一旦你成为一个“电脑”人或程序员，
you can be a lot more productive, a lot more efficient, I dare say,
你可能会变得更有生产力，更高效，我敢说，
by learning to harness the command-line interface
通过学习驾驭命令行界面
and using both types of interfaces for what each is good at.
并根据每种界面的优点来使用它们。
So more on that in just a bit.
所以我们过一会儿会更多地谈论这个。
Over here at left, you're going to see soon a folder interface like Mac OS
这里左边，你会很快看到一个类似 Mac OS 的文件夹界面
or Windows where any of the files or folders we create in CS50
或 Windows，我们在 CS50 中创建的任何文件或文件夹
are going to end up, as well.
也都会出现在这里。
So it gives you the best of both worlds.
所以它提供了两全其美的选择。
You can point and click on the left, or you can type commands at the bottom,
你可以点击左边，或者在底部输入命令，
as we'll soon see.
正如我们很快就会看到的那样。
And then along here is the so-called activity bar,
然后这里就是所谓的活动栏，
where there's just VS Code-specific features but also CS50-specific
那里有一些 VS Code 特定的功能，但也有 CS50 特定的
features.
功能。
And if you're in your own version of CS50.dev,
如果你在自己的 CS50.dev 版本中，
you click through in the dot dot dot menu
你可以在点、点、点菜单中点击
or zoom out so you can see everything.
或者缩小，以便你能看到所有东西。
You'll see CS50's own rubber duck, virtually speaking,
你会看到 CS50 自己的橡皮鸭，虚拟地说，
that will be there throughout the course to answer
它将在整个课程中陪伴你，来回答
any and all of your questions, as well.
你所有的问题。
So more on that soon, too.
所以我们很快也会更多地谈论这个。
So here's the code that I propose that we write first,
所以这里就是我建议我们首先编写的代码，
just like we wrote our very first Scratch program to say "hello, world."
就像我们编写了第一个 Scratch 程序来输出“hello, world.”一样。
So let's go ahead and do exactly this.
所以让我们继续做 exactly this。
I'm going to switch over to this screen here,
我将切换到这里的这个屏幕，
where I've already logged into CS50.dev on my computer.
我已经在电脑上登录了 CS50.dev。
And just to keep the focus on the code, I've hidden the activity bar.
为了让大家专注于代码，我已经隐藏了活动栏。
I've hidden the File Explorer, so to speak.
也就是说，我已经隐藏了文件资源管理器。
So you're seeing here the area where all of my tabs are about to go
所以你们现在看到的是，所有标签即将出现的地方，
and the terminal window, where all of my commands are going to go.
还有终端窗口，所有命令都将在这里执行。
But I've just simplified the UI to keep our focus
不过我仅仅简化了界面，以便让大家专注于
on the interesting parts for now.
目前有趣的部分。
So how do I go about actually writing and compiling and running some code?
那么，我该如何实际编写、编译和运行一些代码呢？
Well, the teaser is going to be these three steps.
好吧，这三个步骤将会是预告。
One of these is a command called, aptly, Code.
其中一个命令恰当地叫做“Code”。
And Code is just going to let me to open or create a new file,
而“Code”命令可以让我打开或创建新文件，
like a file called "hello.c."
例如，名为“hello.c”的文件。
Make is going to be, for now, my compiler that
“Make”命令目前将是我的编译器，它
allows me to make the program, that is convert source code into machine
允许我创建程序，也就是将源代码转换为机器
code, so from C to zeros and ones.
代码，也就是将 C 代码转换为 0 和 1。
And then weirdly, but we'll soon see why,
然后奇怪的是，不过我们很快就会知道原因，
./hello is going to be the command to run my actual code,
"./hello”命令将用于运行我的实际代码，
so the textual equivalent of like double-clicking on a Mac or a PC icon
这相当于在 Mac 或 PC 上双击图标，
or tapping an icon on your phone.
或者在手机上点击图标。
So that's it.
就是这样。
These three commands are going to allow me to write, to compile, and to run
这三个命令可以让我编写、编译和运行
code ultimately.
代码。
So let's go ahead and do that.
所以让我们开始动手吧。
I'm back in my VS Code interface.
我回到了 VS Code 界面。
I'm going to go ahead and run "code hello.c."
我将运行“code hello.c”命令。
And notice a couple of details here.
请注意这里的一些细节。
So one, there's this weird dollar sign, which has nothing to do with currency,
首先，这个奇怪的美元符号与货币无关，
but it's just a common convention in the programming world
它只是编程领域中的一个常见约定，
to represent your prompt.
用来代表你的提示符。
So if a TF, if I ever say, go to your prompt,
所以如果助教，如果我曾经说过，去你的提示符那里，
we really mean, go to your terminal window.
我们的意思实际上是，去你的终端窗口。
Go to the dollar sign.
去美元符号那里。
And the dollar sign is where you type the command.
美元符号是你在那里输入命令的地方。
Sometimes it's a different symbol, but a dollar sign is conventional.
有时它会是不同的符号，但美元符号是传统的。
Now that I've typed "code" space "hello.c,"
现在我已经输入了“code”空格“hello.c”，
I'm going to go ahead and hit Enter.
我将按下 Enter 键。
And maybe not surprisingly, this gives me
也许并不意外，这给了我
a brand new tab, a new file if you will, called "hello.c."
一个全新的标签，如果你愿意的话，一个名为“hello.c”的新文件。
And just like Word documents have their own file extension, like DOC, DOCX,
就像 Word 文档有自己的文件扩展名，比如 DOC、DOCX，
and Excel files have .XLSX and PDFs have .PDF and GIFs have .GIF and so forth,
而 Excel 文件有 .XLSX，PDF 文件有 .PDF，GIF 文件有 .GIF 等等，
so do C files have a file extension by convention that is .C.
C 文件也按照惯例有一个文件扩展名，即 .C。
Now, a couple of minor points.
现在，几点小细节。
Notice that, by convention, I'm almost always
请注意，按照惯例，我几乎总是
going to name my files in lowercase.
使用小写字母命名我的文件。
By convention, I'm never going to use spaces in my file names.
按照惯例，我永远不会在文件名中使用空格。
And my file extension, too, is going to be lowercase.
我的文件扩展名也是小写的。
Long story short, accidentally hitting the spacebar
长话短说，不小心按了空格键
or using file names with spaces just tends
或者使用带有空格的文件名，这往往会
to make life harder when you're in a command-line environment.
在命令行环境中使生活更加困难。
So just beware silly, stupid things like that.
所以要小心这种愚蠢的事情。
So all lowercase, no spaces for now.
所以现在都是小写，没有空格。
So my cursor is literally blinking because the program
所以我的光标不停地闪烁，因为程序
wants me to write some code.
希望我写一些代码。
I'm going to do this from memory.
我要凭记忆来写。
It'll take you presumably some time to acquire the same instincts.
你可能需要一些时间才能获得同样的直觉。
But I'm going to go ahead and type this first line here,
但我将继续输入这第一行，
pronounced "include standard io.h"--
读作“包含标准输入输出头文件”——
more on that soon--
稍后会详细介绍——
int main(void), with some parentheses thrown in.
int main(void)，包含一些括号。
Notice what's about to happen here is a little interesting.
请注意，这里即将发生的事情有点意思。
In the code I want to type, I want what we'll
在我想输入的代码中，我希望有我们所说的
call curly braces, the sort of squiggles that you
花括号，你并不常在英语中使用的那种波浪线，但它就在
don't use often in English, at least, but are there
你的键盘上某个地方。
on your keyboard somewhere.
它就在你的键盘上某个地方。
But notice what VS Code does, and a lot of programming environments,
但请注意 VS Code 的行为，还有许多编程环境的行为，
is it finishes part of my thought.
它们会完成我的一部分想法。
So I'm only going to type a left curly brace,
所以我只输入一个左花括号，
but notice I actually get two of them.
但请注意，我实际上得到了两个。
And if I hit Enter, notice that not only does it scooch one down a bit,
如果我按下 Enter 键，请注意，它不仅向下移动了一点，
it also indents my cursor because, just like with pseudocode last week,
它还缩进了我的光标，因为，就像上周的伪代码一样，
whenever you're doing something logically that should only
当你逻辑上做一些只有在上面一行执行后才能执行的操作时，类似地，
happen if the thing above it happens, similarly
缩进将成为我们实际编写代码时的重要元素。
is indentation going to be a thing when we actually write code.
所以 VS Code 和类似的程序只是试图为我们节省
So VS Code and programs like it just try to save us
按键次数，这样我就不必浪费时间去按空格键
keystrokes so I don't have to waste time hitting the spacebar
或 Tab 键，或者浪费我的时间。
or hitting Tab or wasting my human time like that.
好的，说了这么多，我将继续
All right, so with that said, I'm going to go ahead
输入最后一行，"printf"，
and type the last of these lines, "printf,"
其中 F 代表“格式化”，后面跟着一个括号。
where the F is going to mean "formatted," and then a parentheses.
请注意，它给了我两个。
And notice it gave me two.
它免费给了我第二个。
It gave me the second one for free.
有时它会弄混。
Sometimes it will get confused.
当然，你可以覆盖它，删除它，然后重新开始。
And you can certainly override this, delete it, and start over.
现在，与 Scratch 不同，在 C 语言中，事实证明
And now, unlike Scratch, in C, It turns out
我需要在任何时候都使用双引号
I'm going to need to use double quotes anytime
使用英语单词或短语，或任何人类语言。
I'm using an English word or phrase or any human language for that matter.
“Hello”逗号“world”。
"Hello" comma "world."
然后，在我的行末，就像英语使用句号一样，
And then at the very end of my line, much like English uses periods,
我在 C 语言中使用分号。
I'm going to use a semicolon in C.
说了这么多，但代码并不多。
So that's a lot of talking, but it's not much coding.
它实际上是六行代码。
It's technically six lines of code.
但说实话，从智力角度来看，唯一有趣的是第五行，
But honestly, the only interesting one intellectually, as we'll soon see,
因为，正如我们很快就会看到的，它相当于那个块。
is really line 5.
现在我要祈祷，希望
Like, that is the equivalent of that, say, block.
Now here's where I'll cross my fingers, hoping
everything will work.
一切都能正常运行。
that I didn't make any typographical errors.
我确保没有打错字。
It's going to automatically save for me.
它会自动帮我保存。
And I'm going to go back to my terminal window where now I'm
我要回到我的终端窗口，我现在要
going to do that second command, "make" space "hello."
执行第二个命令，“make” 空格 “hello”。
Common mistake-- you do not say "make hello.c," because you
常见的错误是 - 你不能说“make hello.c”，因为你
already made that file.
已经创建了那个文件。
You say "make hello," which is the name of the program that in this case I do
你说“make hello”，这是程序的名字，在本例中，我想
want to create.
创建它。
And Make is smart.
Make 很智能。
It's going to look in my folder.
它会查看我的文件夹。
And if it sees a file called "hello.c," it's
如果它看到一个名为“hello.c”的文件，它会
going to convert that source code to machine code
将源代码转换为机器代码
and save the results in a simpler shorter-named file just called
并将结果保存在一个更简单、更短的文件中，名为
"hello," like an icon on your desktop.
“hello”，就像你桌面上的一个图标。
Now, hopefully nothing will happen.
现在，希望不会发生任何事情。
And that is a good thing, quite paradoxically.
这其实是一件好事，虽然听起来很矛盾。
If you do anything wrong when programming, odds are you're
如果你在编程时做错了什么，很有可能你会
going to see one or many more lines of error sort of yelling
看到一两行或更多行的错误信息，像是在向你
at you that you made a mistake.
大声喊叫你犯了一个错误。
Seeing nothing happen is actually a good sign.
什么都没有发生实际上是一个好兆头。
So the last command, to run my code, recall our three steps here.
所以最后一个命令，运行我的代码，回顾一下我们这里的三个步骤。
We've written code to create the file, Make to compile the file from source
我们编写了代码来创建文件，Make 用于将文件从源代码
code to machine code.
转换为机器代码。
So lastly is "./hello."
所以最后是“./hello”。
So this now is the equivalent of my double-clicking on a Mac or PC
所以现在这相当于我在 Mac 或 PC 上双击
or single tapping on a phone.
或在手机上单击。
Enter.
回车。
[SIGHS] So close!
[叹气] 真是太近了！
All right, it's pretty good.
好吧，还不错。
I got the H-E-L-L-O comma space "world."
我得到了 H-E-L-L-O 逗号空格“world”。
But there's something a little stupid about my output.
但是我的输出有一点愚蠢。
What might rub some of you aesthetically the wrong way?
什么可能会让你们中的一些人从美学上感到反感？
Yeah?
是的？
STUDENT: The dollar sign.
学生：美元符号。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so the dollar sign looks like I was like, "hello,
David Malan：是的，所以美元符号看起来像是“hello，
world" dollar sign in my output.
world” 美元符号，在我的输出中。
But no, that's just kind of a remnant of my prompt starting with a dollar sign.
但是，这只是我的提示以美元符号开头的一个残余。
And this is a little nitpicky, but this just doesn't feel right,
这有点吹毛求疵，但这确实感觉不对，
doesn't look right.
看起来也不对。
It's not quite correct.
并不完全正确。
So how can I go about fixing this?
那么我该如何解决这个问题呢？
Well, here's where, at least initially, it's
好吧，至少一开始，
going to take some introduction to just new syntax in C to fix this.
需要一些关于 C 语言新语法介绍才能解决这个问题。
The simplest instinct might be to do this.
最简单的本能可能是这样做。
Well, let me just hit Enter like that.
好吧，让我像那样按回车键。
But this should soon, if not already, rub you
但这很快就会让你感到反感，如果不是已经的话，因为一般来说，我们
the wrong way because in general, we're going
会发现，在 C 语言和 Python 语言中
to see that programming in C and in Python
以及其他语言的编程往往是基于行的。
and other languages tends to be line-based.
就像你应该在一行上开始和结束你的想法。
Like, you should really start and finish your thought on one line.
所以如果你习惯于像这样按下回车键
So if you're in the habit of hitting Enter like this
并在下一行结束你的想法，
and finishing your thought on the next line,
通常编程语言不喜欢那样。
generally programming languages don't like that.
所以这实际上不会按预期进行。
So this is, in fact, not going to do what we expect.
为了向你展示，我将执行此操作。
And just to show you as much, I'm going to do this.
让我回到我的终端窗口。
Let me go back to my terminal window here.
我要在做出更改后重新运行“make hello”。
I'm going to rerun "make hello" after making that change.
回车。
Enter.
我们得到了第一个错误输出。
And there we have it, like the first of our erroneous outputs.
它在向我大喊大叫。
And it's yelling at me.
它缺少一个终止字符。
It's missing a terminating character.
这里有一些红色和绿色，吸引着我的注意力。
And there's some red in here, some green, drawing my attention to it.
有时这些错误消息会很直接。
Sometimes these error messages will be straightforward.
有时你需要花点时间才能理解它们。
Sometimes you're going to rack your brain a bit to figure them out.
但现在我已经剧透了。
But for now I've kind of spoiled it.
显然，回车不是正确的解决方案。
Obviously Enter is not the right solution.
让我清理一下我的终端窗口，隐藏那个错误。
So let me clear my terminal window just to hide that error.
让我删除它。
Let me delete this.
让我现在提议在这里添加这个咒语。
And let me propose now that I add this incantation here.
事实证明，反斜杠 n 将是
So backslash n, it turns out, is going to be
确保你的输出结尾处真正有新行的神奇方法。
the sort of magical way of ensuring that you actually get
所以现在我将继续重新运行“make hello”，因为我改变了代码。
a new line at the end of your output.
我需要现在重新转换、重新编译源代码到新的机器。
So let me go ahead now and rerun "make hello," because I've changed my code.
“./hello”。
I need to now reconvert, recompile the source code to new machine.
现在，出现了我本来想要写的规范的“hello, world”程序。
"./hello."
所以现在，不要担心 include。
And now, there is the canonical "hello, world" program
不要担心 standard io。
that I hoped to write in the first place.
不要担心 int 或 main 或 void 或花括号。
So for now, don't worry about the include.
主要关注这里的第 5 行。
Don't worry about the standard io.
在今天和下周，
Don't worry about int or main or void or the curly braces.
我们将开始拆解其他字符
Focus primarily on line 5 here.
这些字符目前你应该直接接受。
And over the course of today and next week,
不过，关于我们刚刚完成的任何步骤，你们有什么问题吗？
we'll start to tease apart the other characters
是的？
that, for now, you should take at face value.
学生：为什么反斜杠 n 在单引号里？
Questions, though, on any of the steps we've just done?
David Malan：当然，为什么反斜杠 n 在引号里面呢？
Yeah?
简而言之，它必须在那里，因为引号里面的内容是你想让 printf
STUDENT: Why is the backslash n inside the apostrophes?
输出到屏幕上的内容。
DAVID MALAN: Sure, why is the backslash n inside of the quotation marks,
所以，如果你想要 printf，这个函数，输出一个新行，
if you will?
它必须包含在你要给它的引号文本中。
So short answer is that's just where it needs
学生：[听不清]
to be because inside of the quotes is the input that you want printf
David Malan：没错。
to output to the screen.
反斜杠 n 是一个特殊的模式，它代表着“printf no”，意思是，好的，我应该
So if you want printf, this function, to output a new line,
将光标移动到下一行。
it must be included in the quoted text that you give it.
好问题。
STUDENT: So the backslash n [INAUDIBLE].
关于这些步骤，还有其他问题吗？
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Backslash n is a special pattern that "printf no" means, OK, I should
move the cursor to the next line.
Good question.
Other questions on any of these steps?
Yeah?
嗯？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: A good question.
好问题。
So what if you actually want to print backslash n?
那么，如果你真的想打印反斜杠 n 呢？
Things get a little tricky there.
事情就有点棘手了。
Let me go ahead and propose that we do this.
让我来提议我们这样做。
So it turns out-- and this is often the case in programming--
结果证明，这在编程中经常发生，
when you want a literal character to appear,
当你想要一个字面字符出现时，
you actually put another backslash in front of it.
你实际上要在它前面放另一个反斜杠。
But this is not going to be something we do often.
但这不是我们经常会做的事情。
But there is in fact a solution to that.
但确实有一个解决方案。
But let me propose that beyond that now we compare it
但让我提议，除此之外，现在我们把它
against what we've actually done.
与我们实际做过的进行比较。
So here is the first Scratch program we wrote with the green flag there.
所以，这是我们用绿色旗帜编写的第一个 Scratch 程序。
Here, recall, is the mental model that I proposed
这里，回想一下，是我提出的思维模型
we have for almost everything we do whereby functions are just
我们对几乎所有事情都持有这个思维模型，函数仅仅是
an implementation, say, in code of algorithms, step-by-step instructions
一个实现，比方说，在代码中实现算法，一步一步的指令
for solving problems.
用于解决问题。
The inputs to functions, recall from last week,
函数的输入，从上周回顾一下，
are called arguments, or in some contexts parameters.
被称为参数，或者在某些情况下被称为参数。
And sometimes functions can have side effects.
有时函数会产生副作用。
Like last time with Scratch, there was the speech bubble
就像上次用 Scratch 一样，有一个气泡
that magically appeared next to the cat's mouth
神奇地出现在猫嘴旁边
as a sort of side effect of using the Say block.
作为使用 Say 模块的一种副作用。
So just like this then, we had the white oval as input.
所以就像这样，我们有一个白色的椭圆作为输入。
The Say block was the function last week.
Say 模块是上周的函数。
And then we had this here, side effect.
然后我们有了这个，副作用。
Well, how do we compare these things left to right?
那么，我们如何从左到右比较这些东西呢？
Well, here's the Say block at left.
好吧，左边是 Say 模块。
Let's compare now to the C code at right.
现在让我们把 C 代码与右边进行比较。
Notice a couple of things to adapt from Scratch to C. Print
注意从 Scratch 到 C 的一些适应之处。Print
is almost the name of the function.
几乎是函数的名称。
It is technically "printf," for reasons we'll eventually see.
技术上来说是 "printf"，原因我们最终会看到。
Notice the parentheses in C are kind of evocative of the oval in Scratch.
注意 C 中的括号让人想起 Scratch 中的椭圆。
And that's probably why MIT chose an oval, because a lot of languages
这可能是 MIT 选择椭圆的原因，因为许多语言
use parentheses in this way.
用这种方式使用括号。
You still write "hello, world" just as we did last week in Scratch.
你仍然像上周在 Scratch 中那样写 "hello, world"。
But per our demo thus far, you do need the double quotes--
但是根据我们迄今为止的演示，你确实需要双引号——
and double quotes, not single quotes-- double quotes on the left and right.
双引号，而不是单引号——左右两边都用双引号。
And in order to get that new line, you need the backslash n.
为了得到那个换行符，你需要反斜杠 n。
And one more thing is missing.
还有一件事是缺失的。
Yeah?
嗯？
STUDENT: Semicolon.
学生：分号。
DAVID MALAN: The semicolon to finish your thought.
分号来结束你的想法。
So all of these sort of stupid things now
所以现在所有这些愚蠢的事情
that honestly you will forget initially if you've never programmed before,
老实说，如果你以前从未编程过，你一开始会忘记这些，
but you'll soon-- within days, within weeks--
但你很快就会——在几天内，在几周内——
develop the muscle memory where all of that stuff just jumps off,
形成肌肉记忆，所有这些东西都会跳出来，
jumps off the page right at you.
直接从页面上跳到你面前。
All right, so this backslash n is generally known,
好的，所以这个反斜杠 n 通常被称为，
just so you know, as an escape sequence.
你知道，作为转义序列。
And so backslash n allows us to specify a character that
所以反斜杠 n 允许我们指定一个字符，
might otherwise be hard to type.
否则可能很难输入。
But let's tease apart some of the other things atop that function already.
但让我们拆解一下该函数顶部的其他一些东西。
So include stdio.h.
所以包含 stdio.h。
It turns out that in C, a lot of the functionality that
事实证明，在 C 中，许多语言自带的功能
comes with the language is tucked away in separate files.
被隐藏在单独的文件中。
So if you want to use certain functions, you have to tell the compiler,
所以如果你想使用某些函数，你必须告诉编译器，
hey, I want to do some standard input and output.
嘿，我想做一些标准输入和输出。
Like, I want to print some things on the screen.
比如，我想在屏幕上打印一些东西。
And that's because, for now, you can think of printf
而那是因为，现在，你可以把 printf 想象成
as living in this file, stdio.h.
住在这个文件里，stdio.h。
That's a bit of a white lie for now.
现在这有点像善意的谎言。
But in stdio.h is essentially a declaration for printf
但在 stdio.h 中，本质上是对 printf 的声明
that will teach the compiler how to print things to the screen.
它将教会编译器如何将东西打印到屏幕上。
So "hash include" here simply tells the compiler
所以这里的 "hash include" 只是告诉编译器
before it does anything else essentially go ahead and find
在它做其他任何事情之前，本质上是去找到
on the local hard drive a file called stdio.h
在本地硬盘上名为 stdio.h 的文件
and copy/paste it there so I know now about printf.
然后将它复制粘贴到那里，这样我就知道 printf 了。
So this thing, this .h file, is what we'll technically call a header file.
所以这个东西，这个 .h 文件，我们从技术上来说把它称为头文件。
And if you've ever heard this word, especially
如果你曾经听到过这个词，尤其是
if you have programmed before, it represents essentially what
如果你以前编程过，它基本上代表着
we'll start calling a library.
我们将开始称之为库。
So a library in the world of programming is just code
所以，在编程世界中，库只是代码
that someone else wrote that you can use.
由其他人编写，你可以使用。
It's usually free and open source, which means
它通常是免费的开源软件，这意味着
you can literally see the code that someone else wrote,
你可以直观地看到其他人编写的代码，
or sometimes you pay for it.
或者有时你需要付费。
Sometimes it's closed source, which maybe Microsoft wrote it.
有时它是闭源软件，比如微软可能编写了它。
They won't show you the code, but they will let you use the zeros and ones.
他们不会向你展示代码，但他们会让你使用这些零和一。
So libraries are super useful because honestly
所以库非常有用，因为老实说
even I don't really know how printf works.
即使我也不知道 printf 是如何工作的。
I've taken for granted for 25 years that if I use printf,
我已经 25 年来理所当然地认为，如果我使用 printf，
stuff prints on the screen.
东西就会打印在屏幕上。
But someone smarter than me had to actually write
但比我更聪明的人必须真正编写
the code in C that figures out how to get the H, the E, the L-L-O, and so
用 C 编写的代码，它弄清楚了如何将 H、E、L-L-O 等等
forth onto the Mac screen, the PC screen, the phone screen, or somewhere
放到 Mac 屏幕、PC 屏幕、手机屏幕或其他地方
else.
其他地方。
So libraries allow us to stand on each other's shoulders
所以库让我们能够站在彼此的肩膀上
and so that someone else can do the hard work,
这样其他人就可以完成艰苦的工作，
and we can now solve problems that are more interesting to us,
而我们现在可以解决对我们来说更有趣的问题，
not the basic commodity stuff that everyone might want in their code.
而不是每个人都可能在他们的代码中需要的基本商品。
So again, library is code that someone else wrote.
所以，库是由其他人编写的代码。
A header file in C is just a file ending in ".h"
C 中的头文件只是一个以 ".h" 结尾的文件
that gives you access to the same.
它让你能够访问相同的东西。
And so for instance, if you to learn more about these,
there are, what are called in the world of programming, manual pages.
And these are textual files, like a documentation of sorts,
via which you can just learn how a function works
or how you can use its inputs or arguments.
The reality is they're written for folks who aren't in CS50.
They're written for folks who aren't just learning how to program.
They're written for and by folks who have been programming for years.
And so frankly, they're a little hard to understand.
And so CS50 has its own version thereof at this URL, manual.cs50.io,
where you'll see not only the official documentation for C, the language,
but also staff-written simplifications in layperson's terms
what all of the various popular functions are, what their inputs,
and what their outputs are.
So for instance, under stdio.h, you can actually go to that website.
You can go to a URL like this, where stdio.h is in there.
And you can actually see the documentation therefore.
So let me go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go ahead in my browser here,
I'm going to go to manual.cs50.io.
And let me go ahead here and select those functions
that are frequently used in CS50.
And under stdio.h, you'll see a bunch of functions,
only one of which we've even discussed called printf.
I'm going to click on printf there.
And you'll see an interface that at first glance
might be a little overwhelming, but it's going
to start to look more and more familiar.
So first of all, you'll see that if you want to use printf under Synopsis,
you need to include this header file.
Like, you literally copy and paste that line into your own code.
You'll also see this, which for now is a bit arcane,
but this is kind of a hint as to what the function is going to look like.
But more on that soon.
But more importantly, you can read a description about it.
And because these descriptions, when you're in less comfortable mode,
are written by me and the course's teaching fellows, teaching assistants,
and course assistants, you'll find them to be much more in layperson's terms.
And so long story short, rely on this site
once you want to learn how to use some function
and also what other functions exist.
In fact, if I go back to the main page here,
you'll see that there are all of these functions like are frequently
used in CS50.
And there's hundreds more that come with C.
But learning a programming language is not about learning all of those
but rather just getting a sense of where you find answers to questions when
you do want to try something new.
But what is important to know for CS50 today
is that we have our own header file called cs50.h which has functions
that we have written just to make life easier
in the first few weeks of the class.
These are training wheels that we'll eventually take off.
But it turns out in C, especially if you've
programmed before, it's actually really hard and annoying just
to get input from users, to get them to type a word or a number or something
else.
Like, C does not make this easy, in part because it's one of the earliest
languages that wasn't zeros and ones.
So you have to do a lot of the heavy lifting yourself.
But we'll put on these training wheels today and for a few weeks
so that we can focus really on the intellectually interesting ideas of C
and programming without getting bogged down in certain weeds
that we will come back to before long.
So for instance, CS50's own documentation is there at that URL.
But within the library are these functions,
a function called get_string to get a string of text.
"String" is a synonym for just text in a programming language.
So get_string will prompt the human for a string of text.
Get_int is shorthand for "get integer," if you
want to get a number from the user.
Get_float is a little more arcane-- get a floating point number,
like a real number with a decimal point in it.
And dot, dot, dot, there are others, as well.
So this is to say within CS50, we've got some user-friendly functions via which
we can actually get some input.
And let's go ahead and use one of these, for instance get_string
because recall that last week our second program in Scratch
was this one here, where we didn't just say "hello, world."
We said "hello, David," or "hello, Carter,"
"hello, Julia," whoever it was typing their name in.
But to do that, we needed this Ask block in Scratch.
And then we used the Say block.
And then we used the Join block to make all of this work.
So let's translate this program now into C
because it's a little more interesting and representative of the kind of code
we'll start to write.
But we need a slightly different mental model.
Still have a function here, which is the implementation in code of an algorithm.
We still have some inputs called arguments.
But previously, I said that the Say block and, in turn,
printf have side effects, which is just something visually, typically,
printf 函数有副作用，这仅仅是在视觉上，通常情况下，
that happens on the screen.
发生在屏幕上。
Other functions actually have, what we called last week, return values.
而其他函数实际上有上周我们提到的返回值。
And this is kind of analogous to a function maybe doing something for you,
这有点类似于一个函数可能为你做一些事情，
writing down the answer on a slip of paper, and then handing you,
将答案写在纸条上，然后递给你，
the programmer, the slip of paper to do whatever
程序员，那张纸条，让你用它去做任何事
you want with it without just broadcasting it
你想要做的事情，而不是只是广播它
to the world with, like, a speech bubble on the screen.
给世界，就像屏幕上的一个对话框。
So a return value is germane for a program like this
所以，对于像这样的程序，返回值是相关的
because recall when we used the Ask block and I typed in my name,
因为回想一下，当我们使用 Ask 块，我输入了我的名字，
where did my name end up initially?
我的名字最初在哪里？
It didn't go on the screen yet.
它还没有出现在屏幕上。
Where did it end up?
它最终在哪里？
STUDENT: In an answer.
学生：在答案里。
DAVID MALAN: In an "answer" puzzle piece.
David Malan: 在一个叫做“答案”的拼图块里。
And that special oval puzzle piece I claimed at the time
我当时说过的那个特殊的椭圆形拼图块
represents a return value, so the metaphorical piece of paper
代表返回值，所以，这个比喻性的纸张
that the answer is written down on so that I can then use it later.
答案被写在了上面，这样我就可以在以后使用它。
So that's what we want to get to now in C,
所以，这就是我们现在在 C 中想要达到的目标，
a return value that I can then do anything I want,
一个返回值，这样我就可以做任何我想做的事情，
whether it's print it to the screen, change it in some way,
无论是把它打印到屏幕上，以某种方式改变它，
save it in a database, or anything else.
把它保存在数据库中，或任何其他事情。
So here, for instance, is what we did with Scratch,
所以，例如，这就是我们用 Scratch 做的事情，
the input to the Say block-- or the Ask block was "what's your name," quote,
对 Say 块的输入——或者 Ask 块是 "what's your name"，引号，
unquote.
引号。
The function, of course, is the Ask function.
当然，这个函数是 Ask 函数。
And the return value was "answer."
返回值是 "answer"。
If we now consider how we might translate this to C,
如果我们现在考虑如何将它翻译成 C 语言，
it's going to look a little weird at first.
它一开始看起来会有点奇怪。
But it's going to follow a pattern today, next week, the week
但是，它将遵循今天，下周，下下周的模式
after any time we do code like this.
我们每次写这种代码时都会遵循这种模式。
So get_string, I claim, is going to be the most analogous function in C
所以，我认为，get_string 将是 C 语言中最类似于 Ask 块的函数
to the Ask block.
Ask 块。
And to be clear, this is a CS50-specific thing, training wheels of sorts.
需要明确的是，这是 CS50 特有的东西，算是辅助工具。
But we'll show you in a few weeks what this function is doing and how you
但是，我们会在几周内向你展示这个函数在做什么，以及如何在你
cannot use it moving forward once you're comfortable with the language itself.
习惯了语言本身之后，不能再使用它。
Notice I've put parentheses, left and right,
注意，我已经放了括号，左括号和右括号，
as sort of a placeholder for user input.
作为用户输入的占位符。
And that user input is going to be "what's your name?"
用户输入将是 "what's your name?"
But I can't just put "what's your name" in parentheses.
但是，我不能仅仅在括号里写 "what's your name"。
What do I minimally need to add in there, too?
我还需要在里面添加什么？
STUDENT: Quotes.
学生：引号。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so the double quotes, left and right.
David Malan: 是的，所以要加上双引号，左边的和右边的。
So let me go ahead and add those in.
所以，我加上了。
I left a space here, not for a new line.
我在这里留了一个空格，不是为了换行。
I could move the cursor to the next line.
我可以将光标移动到下一行。
But I minimally at least want to move the cursor at least one space over
但是，我至少想要将光标向右移动至少一个空格
just so it looks pretty, so that when I'm prompted for my name,
这样看起来更漂亮，这样当我被提示输入名字的时候，
there's a space between the question and my answer.
在问题和我的答案之间有一个空格。
But it could also be backslash n.
但也可以是反斜杠 n。
That's just an aesthetic choice on my part.
这仅仅是我的审美选择。
But what do I do with the answer that comes back from get_string?
但是，我该如何处理从 get_string 返回的答案？
This is where the text is going to look different today.
这就是今天文本看起来不同的原因。
In C, you start to use an equals sign from left to right respectively.
在 C 语言中，你开始使用等号，从左到右分别使用。
And on the left, you put the name of the variable in which you
在左边，你放置你要存储返回值的变量名。
want to store that return value.
你想存储那个返回值。
So a return value is kind of a conceptual thing.
所以，返回值是一种概念性的东西。
You can do with it what you want.
你可以随心所欲地使用它。
And if I want to store it longer term in a variable,
如果我想把它长期存储在一个变量中，
like x or y or z in math class, I can just give it a name here-- x
就像数学课上的 x 或 y 或 z 一样，我只需要在这里给它一个名字——x
or y or z or, more reasonably, "answer," or any other English word.
或 y 或 z 或，更合理地，"answer"，或任何其他英文单词。
No spaces, generally lowercase, same heuristics as before, but this means
没有空格，通常是小写字母，与之前相同的启发式方法，但这意味着
now, ask the user, what's their name?
现在，问用户，他们的名字是什么？
Whatever they type in, go ahead and store it from right
无论他们输入什么，请将它从右
to left in this variable called "answer."
到左存储在这个名为 "answer" 的变量中。
But C's not done with us yet.
但 C 还没完。
If you've learned Python or certain other languages,
如果你学过 Python 或其他一些语言，
you'd kind of be done writing code at this point.
你会在此时完成代码的编写。
In C, though, you additionally have to tell the compiler what type of variable
但是，在 C 语言中，你还需要告诉编译器你想要使用哪种类型的变量
you want to use.
你想使用。
So if it's a string of text, you say "string."
所以，如果它是一串文本，你说 "string"。
If it's an integer, a number, you say "int," as we might have seen before.
如果它是一个整数，一个数字，你说 "int"，就像我们之前可能看到的那样。
So it's a little more pedantic.
所以它有点更学究气。
It's more annoying, frankly, the more onus on you and me, the programmers.
坦率地说，它更烦人，更多地依赖于你和我的责任，作为程序员。
But this just helps the compiler know how
但这仅仅是帮助编译器知道如何
to store it in the computer's memory.
把它存储在计算机的内存中。
And I'm so close to being done with this line of code, but what's missing?
我离完成这行代码只有一步之遥了，但是，还缺少什么？
STUDENT: Semicolon.
学生：分号。
DAVID MALAN: So semicolon.
David Malan: 所以是分号。
And mark my words, if you've never programmed before, sometime this week,
记住我的话，如果你以前从未编程过，这周的某个时候，
this semester, you will forget a semicolon.
这学期，你就会忘记分号。
You will raise your hand.
你会举手。
You'll get frustrated because you can't understand why your code's not working.
你会感到沮丧，因为你无法理解为什么你的代码无法工作。
You will run into stupid issues like that.
你会遇到这种愚蠢的问题。
But do take faith that they are stupid issues.
但请相信，它们确实是愚蠢的问题。
It doesn't mean it's not clicking for you or you're not a programmer.
这并不意味着你没有理解，或者你不是程序员。
It just takes time to see these things if it's a new language to you.
如果你对它是一种新的语言，那么需要时间才能看到这些东西。
So there now is my semicolon.
所以，现在是我的分号。
All right, let's go ahead then and do something
好的，我们继续做点什么
with that return value using the second of the big puzzle pieces in Scratch.
用 Scratch 中的第二个大拼图块来处理返回值。
So when I wanted to say, "hello, David," or whatever the human's name is,
所以，当我想说 "hello, David"，或者任何人的名字，
I kind of stacked my puzzle pieces like this.
我将拼图块堆叠起来，像这样。
This is actually similar to Python and maybe some other languages some of you
这实际上与 Python 类似，也许还有一些其他语言，你们中的一些人
have learned.
我们已经学习了。
But C is a little bit different.
但是C语言有点不同。
And the closest analog to this Scratch solution is going to look like this.
而与Scratch解决方案最接近的模拟将看起来像这样。
I still use printf because printf is the equivalent of Say.
我仍然使用printf，因为printf等同于Say。
Inside of my parentheses, I'm going to go ahead and say, weirdly, "hello, %s."
在我的括号内，我将继续说，奇怪的是，“hello，％s”。
So there's no real analog in C of Join.
所以C语言中没有Join的真正模拟。
Instead, there's a way to specially format text using printf, hence the F
相反，有一种方法可以使用printf专门格式化文本，因此F
in "printf."
在“printf”中。
And what you do in printf is you type whatever English word
在printf中，您键入任何英文单词
or human words that you want.
或您想要的单词。
You then use %s a placeholder.
然后使用％s作为占位符。
If you want a string of text to be added to your own text,
如果你想将一串文本添加到你自己的文本中，
you literally write "%s."
你直接写“％s”。
And let me anticipate a question from the crowd-- how do you print out %s?
让我预测一下观众的一个问题——你如何打印出％s？
There's a solution to that, too, if you literally ever want to print out %s.
如果你真的想打印出％s，也有一个解决方案。
But it's deliberately a weird choice of characters
但它故意选择了奇怪的字符
so that the probability that we ever need to type this ourselves
这样我们自己需要输入它的概率
is just low that no one really worries too much about it.
很低，没有人真的太担心它。
All right, but that's not quite enough.
好吧，但这还不够。
In addition to saying "hello", comma, space, placeholder %s--
除了说“hello”，逗号，空格，占位符％s之外——
and just for vocabulary sake, that's a format code.
出于词汇的缘故，这是一个格式代码。
Again, "format" being the F in printf.
再说一遍，“format”是printf中的F。
I still need my double quotes around the whole thing.
我仍然需要在整个东西周围使用双引号。
In this case, to match my previous program,
在这种情况下，为了匹配我之前的程序，
I am going to go ahead and add the backslash n
我将继续添加反斜杠n
to move the cursor to the next line.
将光标移到下一行。
And now I've left a crazy amount of room here, but that's deliberate.
现在我在这里留下了很多空间，但这是故意的。
Does anyone have an instinct for what I'm probably
有没有人直觉地知道我可能
going to want to add after the quotes but still inside of the parentheses?
想要在引号之后但在括号内添加什么？
STUDENT: The answer.
学生：答案。
DAVID MALAN: So answer itself.
大卫·马兰：所以答案本身。
I need to somehow tell printf with a second input,
我需要以某种方式告诉printf用第二个输入，
otherwise known as an argument, what I want to substitute for that %s.
也称为参数，我想用什么来替换那个％s。
And so I put a comma and then the name of the variable
所以我添加了一个逗号，然后是变量的名称
that I want printf to figure out how to plug in here.
我想让printf弄清楚如何在这里插入。
So honestly it's a little annoying, and this is kind of a dated approach.
所以说真的，这有点令人讨厌，这是一种过时的做法。
Newer, more modern languages, like we'll see later
更新、更现代的语言，比如我们稍后会看到的
in the course, Python and JavaScript, actually
在本课程中，Python和JavaScript，实际上
have much more user-friendly ways of doing it.
有更人性化的方法来实现。
But once you wrap your mind around the heuristics, the rules here,
但是一旦你掌握了启发式算法，这里的规则，
it's just formatting a string by plugging in whatever you want
它只是通过插入你想要的任何东西来格式化字符串
into this format string, so to speak.
到这个格式字符串中，可以这么说。
And again, the comma here is important.
再说一遍，这里的逗号很重要。
This signifies that it takes one input at left and a second input at right.
这表示它在左边接受一个输入，在右边接受第二个输入。
But notice this comma.
但是注意这个逗号。
There's technically two commas.
技术上讲有两个逗号。
But I'm not claiming that this function takes three inputs.
但我不是说这个函数接受三个输入。
Why?
为什么？
This comma I'm pointing out doesn't mean the same.
我指出的这个逗号没有相同的含义。
STUDENT: It's because that comma's part of the quotation marks
学生：因为那个逗号是引号的一部分
and it's been part of the string.
并且它是字符串的一部分。
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
大卫·马兰：没错。
This comma that I'm pointing to is part of the quotation marks and therefore
我指的这个逗号是引号的一部分，因此
part of my string of English text.
是我英文文本的一部分。
So this is just English grammar.
所以这只是英语语法。
This is sort of C syntax.
这是C语言的语法。
And again, these are the sort of annoying little details
再说一遍，这些都是令人讨厌的小细节
that we're using the same symbol for different things, but context matters.
我们用相同的符号来表示不同的东西，但上下文很重要。
So just stare at your code, look carefully left to right,
所以仔细看你的代码，从左到右仔细看，
and generally the answer will pop out, no pun intended.
通常答案会跳出来，没有双关语。
OK, questions now on this syntax before we actually write it and run it?
好的，现在在我们实际编写和运行它之前，关于这个语法的问题？
Yeah?
是的？
STUDENT: Why is the backslash n not after the answer?
学生：为什么反斜杠n不在答案之后？
DAVID MALAN: Why is the backslash n not after the answer?
大卫·马兰：为什么反斜杠n不在答案之后？
So the way functions work, including printf,
所以函数的工作方式，包括printf，
is that you pass to them one argument inside of the parentheses.
就是你把一个参数传递给它们，放在括号里面。
And then if you have a second argument, you put it after this comma here.
然后，如果你有一个第二个参数，你把它放在这个逗号之后。
But the way printf works is that its first argument is always a string
但是printf的工作方式是它的第一个参数总是一个字符串
that you want to be formatted for you.
你想要被格式化的。
So anything you want printed on the screen has to go in those quotes.
所以你想在屏幕上打印的任何东西都必须放在这些引号中。
And you can perhaps extrapolate from this.
你可以从这里推断出来。
If I actually wanted to say multiple things in this sentence, so "hello,"
如果我实际上想在这句话中说很多东西，比如“hello”，
maybe first name, last name, I could actually do "hello" comma, %s, space,
可能是名字，姓氏，我实际上可以写“hello”逗号，％s，空格，
%s, if I had two variables, one called First Name, one called Last Name.
％s，如果我有两个变量，一个叫名字，一个叫姓氏。
But then I would need another comma for a third input to the function.
但是，我需要另一个逗号作为函数的第三个输入。
And so it's very general purpose in that sense.
因此，从这个意义上来说，它非常通用。
Questions?
问题？
Yeah?
是的？
STUDENT: Can you abstract this further by [INAUDIBLE] the "hello" [INAUDIBLE]??
学生：你可以通过[听不清]“hello”[听不清]进一步抽象吗？
DAVID MALAN: OK, so can you abstract away the format string itself, "hello,"
大卫·马兰：好的，所以你可以抽象掉格式字符串本身，“hello”，
comma answer?
逗号答案？
Short answer, yes, but not nearly as easily in C
简短的回答是，是的，但在C语言中并不像其他语言那样容易
as you can in other languages.
就像你在其他语言中可以做到的那样。
So that's why we're keeping it simple for now.
所以我们现在把它保持简单。
But you're going to love something like Python or JavaScript,
但你会喜欢像Python或JavaScript这样的东西，
where a lot of this complexity goes away.
在那里，很多复杂性都消失了。
But you'll see also in Python and JavaScript and other languages,
但你也会在Python、JavaScript和其他语言中看到，
they still are inspired by syntax like this.
它们仍然受到像这样的语法的启发。
So just understanding it now will be useful for multiple languages
所以现在理解它将对多种语言有用
down the line.
在未来。
All right, so let's actually do something with this code
好吧，所以我们实际上用这段代码做点什么
rather than just talk about what it might be doing for us.
而不是仅仅讨论它可能为我们做了什么。
Let me go over to, for instance, VS Code again.
让我再次回到VS Code。
And I'm going to go ahead now and remove this middle line of printf.
现在我将继续删除这行中间的printf。
I'm still in my same file called "hello.c."
我仍然在我的同一个名为“hello.c”的文件中。
I'm going to clear my terminal window just to eliminate distraction.
我将清除我的终端窗口，以消除干扰。
And to do that, I can literally type "clear."
要做到这一点，我实际上可以键入“clear”。
But this is just for aesthetic's sake.
但这仅仅是为了美观。
That's not functionally that useful.
从功能上来说，这并不是那么有用。
Or you can hit Control L to achieve the same on your keyboard.
或者，你可以在键盘上按住Ctrl+L来实现相同的效果。
But I'm going to go back to line 5 here, where I previously just
但我要回到这里第5行，我之前只是
said "hello, world."
说了“hello, world”。
And I'm going to do this instead.
我打算这样做。
I'm going to give myself a variable called string.
我要给自己一个叫做string的变量。
Sorry, I'm going to give myself a variable called
对不起，我打算给自己一个叫做
answer, the type of which is string.
answer 的变量，它的类型是string。
I'm going to set it equal to whatever the return
我将把它设置为get_string函数的返回值，并询问一个英文问题“你叫什么名字？”
value is of get_string, asking an English question, "what's your name?"
在问题的末尾，只留一个空格，以便将光标移到下一个位置，
with just a single space just to move the cursor over,
然后加一个分号。
followed by a semicolon.
接着，我将继续输入printf，双引号，
Then I'm going to go ahead and say printf, quote,
双引号，“hello，占位符，反斜杠n，”
unquote, "hello, placeholder, backslash n,"
逗号，然后这里又应该放什么呢？
comma, and then what goes here again?
学生：Answer
STUDENT: Answer.
大卫·马兰：答案应该放在这里。
DAVID MALAN: This is where answer goes.
然后，我只需要在右侧加上一个分号。
And then I just need a semicolon on the right of that.
但我认为现在我已经完成了。
But I think now that I'm done.
但是，让我指出一些细节。
But let me point out a couple of details.
它变得非常丰富多彩，非常漂亮。
This got very colorful, very pretty quickly.
而且它不像我之前在屏幕上看到的黑白代码。
And it's not like the black and white code I had on the screen a moment ago.
这是因为像VS Code这样的程序为我们做的事情是“美化”打印，
This is because what programs like VS Code do for us is it "pretty" prints,
或者更确切地说，它为我们对代码进行语法高亮显示。
or rather it syntax highlights our code for us.
语法高亮显示意味着只需在代码中添加一些颜色，
So syntax highlighting means just add some colors to the code
这样不同的想法就会脱颖而出。
so that different ideas pop out.
你会注意到，例如，这里的printf，这里的get_string
So you'll notice, for instance, that printf here, get_string here
都是紫色的，因为它们代表函数，就像Say块一样。
are in purple because they represent functions, just like the Say block.
这里，“你叫什么名字？”，引号，引号，在VS Code中
Here, "what's your name?", quote, unquote, in VS Code
是浅蓝色而不是白色。
is a light blue instead of white.
但如果我在其他地方使用文本字符串，它仍然会保持一致。
But it's still going to be consistent if I use strings of text elsewhere,
同样。
as well.
我并没有输入任何特殊的内容。
So I didn't type anything special.
这不像Microsoft Word或Google Docs。
This isn't like Microsoft Word or Google Docs,
我不会在那里高亮显示并更改事物的颜色。
where I'm highlighting and changing colors of things.
这一切都是自动发生的。
This is all happening automatically.
但它只是Unicode文本。
But it's just unicode text.
它只是被自动解释，
It's just being interpreted automatically
并应用这些颜色，以便事物在视觉上更加突出。
and having these colors applied so that things pop out more usefully visually.
现在，我不小心犯了一个错误。
Now, I've unfortunately made a mistake.
但我将故意诱发这个错误，因为你也会犯同样的错误。
But I'm going to deliberately induce this one because you, too,
我将继续运行“make hello”。
will probably make this mistake.
因为我已经更改了代码。
I'm going to go ahead and run "make hello"
所以我必须从新源代码生成机器代码。
again, because I've changed my code.
但不幸的是，当我按下Enter键时，我的天哪，
So I have to regenerate the machine code from the new source code.
错误甚至无法显示在屏幕上。
But unfortunately, when I hit Enter now, my God,
所以我把这个放大一点。
the errors don't even fit on the screen.
我将点击这里的小插入符符号，
So let me make this bigger.
只是为了让我的终端窗口短暂地变大一些。
I'm going to click the little caret symbol here just
你会看到，错误行比我实际编写的代码行还要多。
to make my terminal bigger for just a moment.
而且这些错误常常以一种相当晦涩难懂的方式写出来，又是针对那些编写代码已经10、20年的程序员。
And you'll see that there's more lines of errors
但有一些细节映入眼帘。
than there are of code that I actually wrote,
所以请注意，问题绝对出在hello.c。
often which is written pretty arcanely, again, for programmers who've
太好了，是我的错误。这里的语法意味着第5行是问题所在。
been writing code for 10, 20 years.
接下来的5表示第5个字符。
But there are some details that pop out.
所以你可以通过定位第5行，
So notice the problem is definitely with hello.c.
然后向右移动5个字符，来确定你的错误所在，它就在这个区域。
So great, it is my fault. This syntax here means that line 5 is the problem.
具体来说，“该区域是使用未声明的标识符字符串”。
And this next 5 means character 5.
你是想说标准输入吗？
So you can literally triangulate your bug, your mistake by going to line 5
我不认为我想说的是这个。
and then over five, and it's somewhere in that area.
就像，我确实想要string，然后这里还有一些其他的复杂情况。
Specifically, "the area is use of undeclared identifier string.
但这里重要的是，并非这个错误的具体内容，而是它真的
Did you mean standard in?"
无法识别“string”或“get_string”这两个词。
I don't think I did.
那么，这可能是为什么呢？
Like, I do want string, and then there's some other complexity here.
是的？
But what's important here is not the specifics of this error but really
学生：你说为了[听不清]
the implication that it doesn't recognize the word
大卫·马兰：没错。
"string" or "get_string."
因为我们正在使用get_string，我声称
Now, why might this be?
它是CS50中我们会用几周的东西，
Yeah?
C语言本身并不支持它。
STUDENT: You said that in order to [INAUDIBLE]
我必须告诉编译器get_string的存在，
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
就像我通过包含适当的头文件告诉编译器printf的存在一样。
Because we are using get_string, which I claimed
在这种情况下，很简单，它被称为includeCS50.h。
is a CS50 thing that we'll use for a few weeks,
现在，它告诉编译器，哦，其他人
C does not know about it out of the box, so to speak.
已经写了这个函数，get_string，以及这个叫做string的变量类型。
I have to teach the compiler that get_string exists,
所以现在如果我回到我的终端窗口，
just like I taught the compiler that printf exists by including
并重新运行完全相同的命令“make hello”——也许祈祷一下——
the appropriate header file.
现在事实上没有任何问题，因为编译器
And in this case, quite simply, it's called includeCS50.h.
已经了解了它需要的所有功能。
That now teaches the compiler, oh, someone else
现在如果我执行./hello，回车，它出现了，你叫什么名字？
wrote this function already, get_string, and with it this type of variable
请注意，光标向前移动了一个空格，
called "string."
因为我认为这样比将光标放在问号旁边更美观。
So now if I go back to my terminal window
我输入D-A-V-I-D，然后回车。
and rerun the exact same command, "make hello"-- maybe crossing my fingers--
然后，“hello，David”。
now nothing in fact goes wrong because the compiler
到目前为止，关于这段代码你有什么问题吗？
has been brought up to speed with all of the functionality it needs.
有问题吗？
And now if I do ./hello, Enter, there it is, what's my name?
任何代码都可以。
And notice the cursor is one space over just
没有？
because I thought that looked prettier than having the cursor right
next to the question mark.
D-A-V-I-D as my input, and Enter.
And "hello, David."
Questions on any of this code thus far?
Questions?
Any of the code.
No?
All right, so let's introduce some other functionality into the mix.
好的，让我们在其中加入一些其他功能。
It turns out that there are other types of data,
事实证明，世界上还有其他类型的数据，
other types of variables in the world, not just strings
其他类型的变量，不仅仅是字符串，
but indeed, per before, we have things called
但实际上，正如之前所说，我们有一些东西被称为
integers, "int" for short, floating point values, "float" for short,
整数，简称为 "int"，浮点数，简称为 "float"，
and a few others as well.
还有其他一些。
So rather than only focus on string, let's
所以，与其只关注字符串，让我们
get a little more interesting with numbers
用数字变得更有趣一些
here and see what we can do with something like integers, again
这里，看看我们可以用整数做些什么，再一次
"int" for short, by taking a look at not get_string, as before, but now
简称为 "int"，不再像之前那样看 get_string，而是现在
how about get_int.
试试 get_int 如何。
And for this, I'm going to give us a few other tools in our toolkit,
为此，我将在我们的工具箱中提供一些其他工具，
those format codes to which I alluded earlier, like %s,
我之前提到的那些格式代码，比如 %s，
fortunately are pretty straightforward.
幸运的是，它们非常简单直观。
And here is a list of most of the popular format codes
这里列出了您在使用 printf 时可能需要用到的大多数常用格式代码
that you might ever care about with printf.
您可能在使用 printf 时需要用到的大多数常用格式代码。
In particular, we saw %s for string.
特别是，我们看到了用于字符串的 %s。
And you can perhaps guess which one we're going to use for integers.
也许您能猜到我们会用哪一个来表示整数。
STUDENT: %i.
学生：%i。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so %i is what we're going to use for integers.
大卫·马兰：没错，所以我们将使用 %i 来表示整数。
And this is the kind of thing that you can
而这类信息，您可以
consult in the manual pages or a slide like this.
查阅手册页或类似这样的幻灯片。
There's only a few of them that you might frequently use.
您可能经常使用到的只有几个。
But let's go ahead and use integers in a more interesting context, not
但是，让我们在更有趣的环境中使用整数，而不仅仅是
just using functions.
仅仅使用函数。
But let's revisit this idea of conditionals.
但是，让我们重新审视一下条件语句的概念。
And conditionals in Scratch were like these proverbial forks in the road.
在 Scratch 中，条件语句就像这些众所周知的岔路口。
Like, do you want to do this thing or this thing or this other thing?
就像，您想做这件事还是那件事，或者做其他事情？
It's a way of making decisions in a program, which
这是一种在程序中进行决策的方式，这
is going to be super useful and pretty much omnipresent in any problems
将非常有用，并且在我们要解决的任何问题中几乎无处不在。
that we try to solve.
我们尝试解决的任何问题中。
So let me give you a few more building blocks
所以，让我向您展示更多 C 语言中的构建块
in C by doing the side-by-side comparison again.
通过再次进行并排比较来展示。
So here in Scratch is how we might say if two variables, x and y,
所以，在 Scratch 中，如果我们想说两个变量，x 和 y，
one is less than the other, then go ahead and say, quote, unquote,
其中一个比另一个小，那么就可以说，引号，引号，
"x is less than y."
"x 小于 y"。
So kind of a stupid program.
所以，这是一个有点愚蠢的程序。
But just to show you the basic syntax for Scratch,
但仅仅是为了向您展示 Scratch 的基本语法，
this is how you would ask the question, if x is less than y, then say this.
这就是您提出问题的方式，如果 x 小于 y，那么就说这句话。
So Say is the function.
所以 Say 是函数。
"If" is the conditional.
"If" 是条件语句。
And the green thing here we called, what?
而这里这个绿色的东西我们称之为，什么？
What did we call it?
我们叫它什么？
Yeah?
是的？
STUDENT: A Boolean.
学生：布尔值。
DAVID MALAN: A Boolean or a Boolean expression,
大卫·马兰：布尔值或布尔表达式，
which is just a fancy way of saying a question whose
这只是一个花哨的说法，表示一个问题的答案是
answer is true or false, yes or no, 1 or 0, however you want to think about it.
真或假，是或否，1 或 0，无论您想怎么思考。
In C, the code is going to look like this.
在 C 语言中，代码将如下所示。
So it'll take a little bit of habit, a little bit of muscle memory to develop.
所以，这需要一些习惯，需要发展一些肌肉记忆。
But you're going to say "if," then in parentheses,
但您将说 "if"，然后在括号中，
you're going to say "x less than y," assuming x and y are variables.
您将说 "x 小于 y"，假设 x 和 y 是变量。
You're then going to use these curly braces.
然后，您将使用这些花括号。
And then if you want to say, quote, unquote, "x is less than y"
然后，如果您想说，引号，引号，"x 小于 y"
in C, what function should we use here presumably?
在 C 语言中，我们应该在这里使用什么函数？
So printf.
所以 printf。
So printf, quote, unquote, "x is less than y."
所以 printf，引号，引号，"x 小于 y"。
So it's a bit of a mouthful, but again notice the pattern.
所以，这有点拗口，但请再次注意这种模式。
Name of the function is printf.
函数名称是 printf。
In the parentheses, left and right, is the argument to printf,
在括号中，左和右，是 printf 的参数，
which is, quote, unquote, "x is less than y."
即，引号，引号，"x 小于 y"。
And again, just for aesthetics, to move the cursor to the next line,
再次，为了美观，将光标移到下一行，
which you don't have to worry about in Scratch because everything's
在 Scratch 中，您不必担心，因为所有内容都是
in speech bubbles, we're adding a backslash n, as well.
在气泡中，我们也添加了一个反斜杠 n。
So notice that these curly braces, as they're
所以，请注意，这些花括号，正如它们
called, much like the orange puzzle piece here,
被称为的那样，就像这里这个橙色的拼图块一样，
are kind of hugging the code like this.
就像这样拥抱代码。
And I'll note that technically speaking in C,
我注意到，从技术上讲，在 C 语言中，
If you only have one line of code inside of your conditional,
如果您在条件语句中只有一行代码，
you can actually omit the curly braces altogether.
您可以完全省略花括号。
And the code will still work if you have one single line of code.
如果您只有一行代码，代码仍然可以正常运行。
Why?
为什么？
Just saves people some keystrokes.
只是节省了一些人的按键次数。
If you have two lines, three lines, or more in there,
如果您有两行、三行或更多行代码，
you need the curly braces.
您需要使用花括号。
But I'll always draw it with the curly braces in class
但我会在课堂上始终用花括号绘制它
so it resembles Scratch as closely as possible.
以便尽可能地与 Scratch 类似。
As an aside to some of you who have programmed before,
顺便说一下，对于之前已经编程过的一些人来说，
you might be cringing now because like you really
您现在可能在皱眉，因为您真的
like your curly brace to be over here instead of here, that,
希望您的花括号在这里而不是在这里，这，
too, is a stylistic choice.
也是一种风格选择。
And we'll talk, too, about this in the class.
我们也会在课堂上讨论这个问题。
Aesthetically, stylistically there are certain decisions we can make.
从美观和风格的角度来说，我们可以做出一些决定。
But generally in a class, in a company, you as a student or an employee
但通常在课堂上，在公司里，您作为学生或员工
would simply standardize on one set of rules, so to speak.
只会简单地遵循一套规则，可以这么说。
So we'll use these rules for formatting our code in class consistently.
因此，在课堂上，我们将始终如一地使用这些规则来格式化代码。
All right, any questions on this snippet of C code?
好的，关于这部分 C 代码，有什么问题吗？
All right, a couple of others then.
好的，还有其他几个。
So here is how, in Scratch, we might have a two-way fork in the road.
所以，在 Scratch 中，我们可能会有一个双向的岔路口。
If x is less than y, say x is less than y, else say x is not less than y.
如果 x 小于 y，就说 x 小于 y，否则就说 x 不小于 y。
In C, It's going to look pretty much the same.
在 C 语言中，它看起来几乎是一样的。
But notice I'm adding an "else" keyword here with another set of curly braces.
但请注意，我在这里添加了一个 "else" 关键字，以及另一组花括号。
I'm going to have a couple of more printf's.
我将再添加几个 printf 语句。
But in C, even though it's clearly keyboard based,
但在 C 语言中，即使它显然是基于键盘的，
it's just text, no more puzzle pieces, it's kind of the same shape,
它只是文本，不再有拼图块，它的形状有点一样，
so to speak, and it's definitely the same idea.
可以这么说，它绝对是一样的想法。
So it's following a pattern.
所以它遵循着一定的模式。
What about a three-way fork in the road, if x is less than y,
如果x小于y，会怎样？
then say x is less than y, else if x is greater
那么就说x小于y，否则如果x大于
than y, say x is greater than y, else if x equals y, then say x is equal to y.
y，就说x大于y，否则如果x等于y，就说x等于y。
Well, you can probably see where this is going.
好吧，你可能已经猜到我们要做什么了。
On the right-hand side, it looks almost the same.
在右边，它看起来几乎一样。
In fact, if I add in the printf's, it's really almost the same,
事实上，如果我加上printf语句，它真的几乎一样，
at least logically.
至少在逻辑上是相同的。
But there is at least one curiosity, seemingly a typo
但是至少有一点奇怪，看起来像是一个打字错误
but it's not this time.
但这次不是。
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: The double equals.
学生：双等号。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, the double equal signs does not match Scratch,
戴维·马兰：是的，双等号与Scratch不匹配，
but it's not in fact a bug or a mistake in C. Anyone
但事实上它不是C语言中的错误。有人
have an intuition for why I did use two equal signs instead of one here?
对为什么我在这里使用两个等号而不是一个等号有直觉吗？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: Because otherwise it could be mistaken for a variable.
学生：因为否则它可能会被误认为是变量。
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
戴维·马兰：没错。
Well, otherwise it would be mistaken for a variable, specifically
好吧，否则它会被误认为是变量，特别是
assignment of a variable.
变量的赋值。
So recall that in previous code, when we used the get_string function,
所以回忆一下之前代码中，当我们使用get_string函数时，
we used an equals sign to assign, from right to left, the value of a variable.
我们使用了一个等号来赋值，从右到左，变量的值。
And that's a reasonable decision.
这是一个合理的决定。
"Equal" kind of means that the two should ultimately
“等于”某种程度上意味着两者最终
be equal even though you think about it from going right to left.
应该是相等的，即使你是从右到左考虑的。
Unfortunately, the authors of C kind of [? painted ?] themselves into a corner.
不幸的是，C语言的设计者把自己逼到一个角落里了。
And presumably, decades ago when they realized, oh, shoot,
我想，几十年前当他们意识到，糟糕，
we've already used a single equal sign, how
我们已经使用了一个等号，如何
do we represent equality of two values, the answer they came up with was,
表示两个值相等，他们想出的答案是，
all right, we'll just use two instead.
好吧，我们只用两个。
And thus was born this decision.
就这样，这个决定诞生了。
Is it the best one?
这是最好的吗？
Who knows?
谁知道呢？
Crazy enough, in other languages, like JavaScript,
有趣的是，在其他语言中，比如JavaScript，
you have not just one, but two, but also three equal signs
你不仅有1个，还有2个，甚至还有3个等号
in a row to solve yet another problem.
连续在一起，为了解决另一个问题。
So reasonable people will disagree as to how good or bad these decisions are.
所以，理智的人会对这些决定是好是坏持不同意见。
But in C, this is what you must do.
但在C语言中，你必须这样做。
But there's a bad design decision here, too.
但是这里也存在一个糟糕的设计决策。
It's still correct, the code, left and right.
代码仍然是正确的，左边和右边。
But I bet I could critique the quality of the design of both the Scratch code
但我敢肯定我能批评Scratch代码和C代码的设计质量，因为什么原因？
and the C code for reasons, what?
为什么？
STUDENT: Do we have to do else if x equals [INAUDIBLE]??
学生：我们必须这样做吗？else if x等于[无法识别]？？
DAVID MALAN: OK, no, really good intuition.
戴维·马兰：好的，不，直觉很好。
Do we have to ask this third question, "else if x equals y?"
我们必须问第三个问题吗，“else if x等于y”？
So short answer, no, logically, right?
简短的回答，不，从逻辑上讲，对吧？
Just based on arithmetic, either x is less than y or x is greater than y
仅仅从算术的角度来说，要么x小于y，要么x大于y
or, what's the only other possible answer?
或者，唯一可能的答案是什么？
They must be equal, logically.
它们必须相等，从逻辑上讲。
So technically, you're just kind of wasting the computer's time
所以从技术上讲，你只是在浪费计算机的时间
by asking this question because it already knows,
因为你问了这个问题，但它已经知道了，
at that point, the answer.
当时的答案。
And you're wasting your time as the programmer bothering
而你作为程序员，浪费时间去写
to type out more code or more puzzle pieces
更多代码或更多拼图块
than you need because logically one stems from the other.
比你需要的更多，因为在逻辑上，一个是从另一个得来的。
So I can tighten this up, get rid of the "else, if," just use an "else."
所以我可以简化它，去掉“else，if”，只用一个“else”。
And I can do the same thing over here in C, thereby avoiding
我可以在C语言中做同样的事情，从而避免
the double equal sign altogether, but not because it's wrong
双等号的出现，但不是因为它是错误的
but because you're wasting time, because now you're potentially asking only two
而是因为你在浪费时间，因为现在你可能只问了两个
questions, two Boolean expressions, instead of 50% more by asking
问题，两个布尔表达式，而不是通过问问题来增加50%
a total of three questions at most.
最多三个问题。
Other questions then on this kind of code, logically or otherwise?
关于这种代码，还有其他问题吗，无论是在逻辑上还是其他方面？
No?
没有？
All right, so if we have these puzzle pieces, so to speak, at our disposal,
好吧，如果我们有这些拼图块，可以这么说，我们可以使用它们，
how can we go about actually using these?
我们该如何实际使用它们呢？
Well, suppose that we actually want to do something with values.
假设我们实际上想用这些值做一些事情。
Let's introduce variables in C, as well.
让我们在C语言中也引入变量。
We saw an example using a string a moment ago.
我们刚才看到了一个使用字符串的例子。
But what about with something like integers?
但是对于像整数这样的东西呢？
Well, you might not have used this in Scratch.
好吧，你可能没有在Scratch中使用过它。
But here's the orange puzzle piece in Scratch
但在Scratch中，橙色拼图块是
via which you can create a variable called counter to count things.
你可以用它创建一个叫做计数器的变量来计数。
And you can set it equal to some value like 0.
你可以把它设置为一个值，比如0。
Now, you can perhaps guess where we're going with this.
现在，你可能已经猜到我们要去哪里了。
If I want in C a variable called counter and I want to set it equal to 0,
如果我在C语言中想要一个叫做计数器的变量，并且我想把它设置为0，
I use a single equal sign because logically you
我使用一个等号，因为从逻辑上讲，你
read it from right to left, or technically it's
从右到左读它，或者从技术上讲，它是
executed from right to left.
从右到左执行的。
But that's not enough in C. What's missing from the screen?
但这在C语言中还不够。屏幕上缺少了什么？
STUDENT: Data type.
学生：数据类型。
DAVID MALAN: I need a what?
戴维·马兰：我需要什么？
STUDENT: You need a data type.
学生：你需要一个数据类型。
DAVID MALAN: So we need a data type.
戴维·马兰：所以我们需要一个数据类型。
And if it's going to be an integer, indeed I'm going to use int.
如果它是一个整数，我确实要使用int。
And now the other mistake I keep making is--
现在我一直在犯的另一个错误是--
STUDENT: Semicolon.
学生：分号。
DAVID MALAN: So a semicolon at the end of the line.
戴维·马兰：所以在行尾添加一个分号。
So it's a little more verbose than some languages.
所以它比一些语言更冗长。
But if you read it left to right, this is
但是如果你从左到右读，这就是
how you tell C to give you a variable called counter of type int
你告诉C语言为你创建一个叫做计数器的int类型的变量的方式
and initialize it to a value of 0.
并初始化它为0。
That's all.
就是这样。
All right, how about, in Scratch, if you want to change that variable by 1,
好吧，在Scratch中，如果你想把那个变量改变1，
by adding 1 to it?
把它加1？
In Scratch, it's super simple.
在Scratch中，这非常简单。
You just change it by 1 or even negative 1
只需将其更改为 1 甚至 -1
if you want to go up or down respectively.
如果你想分别向上或向下移动。
In C, it turns out you have a few different ways to do this.
在 C 语言中，实际上你可以用几种不同的方法做到这一点。
And this looks like it's not mathematically possible,
这看起来在数学上是不可能的，
but that's because equals is assignment, recall.
但这是因为“等于”是赋值，还记得吗？
So this line of code is not saying that counter equals counter plus 1,
所以这一行代码并非在说计数器等于计数器加 1，
because that's just not possible using typical numbers.
因为对于一般的数字来说这是不可能的。
But this means take counter's value, add 1 to it,
但它的意思是取计数器的值，加上 1，
and assign it back to the counter variable.
然后将其重新赋值给计数器变量。
So it's like incrementing counter in this way.
所以这就像用这种方式递增计数器。
But this is such a common thing in C and in programming
但在 C 语言和编程中，
to increase or decrease the values of variables,
增加或减少变量的值是一件非常常见的事情，
there's a more succinct syntax.
因此存在一种更简洁的语法。
This is identical.
它们是一样的。
And it might take you a little practice to get used to it,
你可能需要一些练习才能习惯它，
but it just saves you some keystrokes.
但这可以节省一些按键操作。
But it similarly adds 1, or whatever number you use there.
但它同样地加 1，或者加你用在那里使用的任何数字。
And this is such a common operation in C especially
而这在 C 语言中尤其是一个非常常见的操作，
that there's an even tighter way of executing the same idea.
因此存在一种更紧凑的方法来执行相同的思想。
And you can literally just say counter++ and then semicolon in this case.
在这种情况下，你可以直接写计数器++，然后加上分号。
All three are exactly the same.
三种方法完全相同。
All three are perfectly correct.
三种方法都完全正确。
But you'll learn over time that typing less on the screen
但你会随着时间的推移而发现，在屏幕上输入越少，
is probably going to save you some time.
你就能节省更多的时间。
Meanwhile, if we wanted to do the opposite and do something like minus 1
同时，如果我们想要做相反的操作，比如减去 1，
in Scratch, we could similarly do minus minus in C. Or we could do--
在 Scratch 中，我们可以用类似的方法在 C 语言中写成减减。或者我们可以写成...
yeah, we could do minus minus in C here at right.
没错，我们可以在这里在 C 语言中写成减减。
All right, so just some additional building blocks, translating
好了，只是一些额外的构建模块，将
from scratch to C. Why don't we go ahead and try using this perhaps
从 Scratch 翻译到 C 语言。我们为什么不试着使用它呢？
in the following way?
以如下方式？
Let me go ahead and go back to VS Code.
让我回到 VS Code 中。
And let me propose that we do something like this.
让我提议我们做一些类似的事情。
In VS Code, I'm going to go ahead and clear my terminal window.
在 VS Code 中，我将清除我的终端窗口。
I'm going to close "hello.c" by just clicking
我将通过点击来关闭“hello.c”
the X. I'm going to go ahead and create a new file called "compare.c"
X。我将创建一个名为“compare.c”的新文件
because the purpose in life of this program
因为这个程序存在的意义
is going to be to compare integers on the screen.
就是要在屏幕上比较整数。
This time I'm not going to mess up.
这一次我不会搞砸了。
I'm going to preemptively include CS50.h.
我将预先包含 CS50.h。
I'm going to preemptively include stdio.h.
我将预先包含 stdio.h。
And here, too, is a very common mistake in learning C. It is not "studio.h."
在学习 C 语言时，这也是一个很常见的错误。它不是“studio.h”。
So when you email us asking why "studio.h" is not working,
所以当你发邮件给我们询问为什么“studio.h”不起作用时，
that's because that is not the word.
那是因为这个词是错误的。
It is "standard io.h," meaning standard input and output,
它是“standard io.h”，意思是标准输入和输出，
stuff involving the screen and the keyboard.
涉及屏幕和键盘的东西。
Then I'm going to go ahead and, just as before, int main(void),
然后我将继续，和以前一样，int main(void)，
but we'll come back to that eventually as to what it means.
但我们最终会回到它，来了解它的含义。
And now inside of "main," which is just where the main part of my program goes,
现在在“main”中，也就是我的程序的主体部分所在的地方，
again you can think of this as being analogous to "when green flag clicked."
你可以将其看作与“当绿旗被点击时”类似。
This just kicks everything off.
这仅仅是启动了一切。
I'm going to go ahead and do two things.
我将要做两件事。
I'm going to go ahead and get an integer called x,
我将获取一个名为 x 的整数，
and I'm going to prompt the user for that int
并提示用户输入该整数
and just say something like, "what's x?", space.
并提示用户输入类似“x 是多少？”这样的信息，后面带空格。
Then I'm going to do int y equals get_int, quote, unquote, "what's y?",
然后我将进行 int y 等于 get_int，双引号，“y 是多少？”
space.
后面带空格。
And then let's just do something simple like, if x is less than y,
然后让我们做一些简单的事情，比如，如果 x 小于 y，
then go ahead and print out, quote, unquote,
那么就打印出，双引号，
"x is less than y backslash n," semicolon.
“x 小于 y 换行符”，分号。
So it's not a very deep program.
所以它不是一个非常复杂的程序。
It's just going to do what most any human brain could do pretty quickly.
它只是会做任何一个人类大脑都能很快完成的事情。
But it's at least demonstrating how we might use now
但它至少展示了我们现在如何使用
something like a conditional in code.
类似条件语句这样的东西。
So let me go ahead and re--
所以让我继续重新...
let me compile this code for the first time, make compare, enter.
让我第一次编译这段代码，make compare，回车。
Nothing bad happens, which is good. "./compare" is how I run the program.
没有发生任何错误，这是好事。"./compare" 是我运行程序的方式。
And just to tease this apart, dot, as we'll soon see,
为了让它更清晰，点号，正如我们很快就会看到的，
essentially means that the file is in your current folder.
本质上意味着该文件位于你的当前文件夹中。
So dot means in your current folder.
所以点号意味着在你的当前文件夹中。
And we'll eventually see that dot dot means your parent
而我们最终会看到点点意味着你的父级
folder, like the one that contains wherever
文件夹，比如包含我所在位置的文件夹
I am on my computer's hard drive.
我的电脑硬盘上的文件夹。
All right. ./compare.
好的。 ./compare。
What's x?
x 是多少？
1.
1。
2 for y.
y 是 2。
And hopefully it should say that x is less than y.
我希望它会说 x 小于 y。
So pretty straightforward.
所以很简单。
Proof by example.
举例证明。
And hopefully this would work in other cases, too.
我希望它在其他情况下也能工作。
But if I flip that around and I rerun it, ./compare, and I do 2 and 1,
但如果我反过来，重新运行它，./compare，然后我输入 2 和 1，
nothing's going to happen.
什么也不会发生。
But you would expect that because there's
但你会发现，因为只有一个
only one Boolean expression deciding whether or not
布尔表达式来决定是否
I should actually type this out.
我应该实际输入它。
So what's going on?
所以发生了什么？
Well, if this helps you, you might find it
好吧，如果这对你有所帮助，你可能会发现它
useful to think about the logic of any program, be it in Scratch or C,
有助于思考任何程序的逻辑，无论是 Scratch 还是 C 语言，
as kind of a flowchart of sorts.
将其视为一种流程图。
And we'll put up a few of these over time just in case
而我们将会随着时间的推移，提供一些这样的流程图，以防万一
you're a particularly visual thinker.
你是个非常视觉化的思考者。
And this represents what it is I just did.
而这代表了我刚刚做的事情。
So here in this picture is where the program starts conceptually.
所以在这幅图中，就是程序概念上的起点。
And any time you see a diamond, think of that as a Boolean expression,
而当你在流程图中看到菱形时，就将其视为一个布尔表达式，
a question that's being asked.
一个正在被问的问题。
And the question being asked is, is x less than y?
而正在被问的问题是，x 是否小于 y？
That has two possible answers, true or false, yes or no respectively.
它有两个可能的答案，真或假，分别对应是或否。
So let me propose, per the arrow, that if the answer is true, then print out,
因此，我建议，根据箭头，如果答案为真，则打印出来，
per this rectangle, "x is less than y," just quote, unquote, and then stop.
根据这个矩形，“x 小于 y”，直接引号，引号，然后停止。
That's it for the program.
这就是整个程序了。
But logically, if x is not less than y, that
但从逻辑上讲，如果 x 不小于 y，那么
is that question's answer is false, we'll just skip right to the end
也就是该问题的答案为假，我们将直接跳到最后
and stop.
并停止。
So this is a control-flow diagram.
所以，这是一个控制流程图。
It's just a pictorial way that you could write
这只是一个你可以用图片的方式在
on a piece of paper that just represents what it is the program is doing.
纸上写下来，它只是表示程序正在做的事情。
And this gets a little more interesting if now we
如果现在我们做一些其他事情，这会变得更有趣。
do something else with the code.
对代码做一些其他的操作。
For instance, instead of just concluding that it's less than 1 or the other,
例如，与其只是得出结论它小于 1 还是小于另一个，
let's go back to the code here.
让我们回到这里的代码。
Let me clear my terminal window.
让我清除我的终端窗口。
And let me add an "else."
让我添加一个“else”。
So else, go ahead and print out "x"--
所以，else，继续打印出“x”--
I don't think I want to say this-- "greater than y."
我不认为我想说这个-- “大于 y”。
It's not quite right.
不太对。
What would be reasonable to say here?
这里应该说些什么比较合理？
STUDENT: "x is not less than y.
学生：“x 不小于 y。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, subtle, but "x is not less than y" because it could be equal.
大卫·马兰：是的，很微妙，但“x 不小于 y”，因为它可能相等。
We don't know if we're only checking two scenarios here.
我们不知道我们这里是否只检查了两种情况。
So if I recompile this, make compare, ./compare.
所以，如果我重新编译这个，make compare，./compare。
Now if I do 1, comma 2, I still get the same answer.
现在，如果我输入 1，逗号 2，我仍然得到相同的答案。
If I rerun ./compare 2, comma 1, I now get the opposite answer.
如果我重新运行 ./compare 2，逗号 1，我现在得到相反的答案。
It's not as good as might be ideal.
这并不像理想的那样好。
It'd be nice to know if it's equal to or greater than.
如果能知道它等于还是大于就好了。
But at least that's all of the code that we have here.
但至少这就是我们在这里所有的代码。
And just to now paint a picture, if I go back
现在，为了画一幅图，如果我回到
to my control-flow diagram, my flow chart here,
我的控制流程图，我的流程图，
this is what it looked like before logically.
从逻辑上来说，它以前是这个样子。
Now that I've added in a second branch, so to speak,
现在，我已经添加了第二个分支，可以这么说，
now, if the answer is false, I first print out x is not less than y,
现在，如果答案为假，我首先打印出 x 不小于 y，
and then I stop the program.
然后我停止程序。
So same idea, but the decision tree, if you will,
所以，同样的想法，但决策树，如果你愿意的话，
if you've taken a 10 or the like, is getting a little bit bigger now
如果你已经学过 10 门课或者类似的，现在它会变得稍微大一些
conceptually.
在概念上。
All right, what if we do something more than this?
好吧，如果我们做一些比这更多的事情呢？
Let's actually have that third condition.
让我们实际拥有那个第三个条件。
Let me go back into my code here.
让我回到这里的代码。
I'm going to hide the terminal window just to make room for more code.
我要隐藏终端窗口，以便为更多代码腾出空间。
And I'm going to say, "else if x is greater
我将说，“else if x 大于
than y," then go ahead and say not "x is not less than y,"
y”，那么继续说，不是“x 不小于 y”，
but rather "x is greater than y."
而是“x 大于 y”。
And then down here, I'll do an "else if x equals equals y,"
然后，在这里，我将做一个“else if x 等于等于 y”，
then I can go ahead and say printf, "x is equal to y backslash n,"
然后，我可以继续说 printf，“x 等于 y 反斜杠 n”，
close quote.
关闭引号。
All right, so now if I run it-- let me open my terminal window again.
好了，现在如果我运行它--让我再次打开我的终端窗口。
Let me rerun make compare.
让我重新运行 make compare。
Let me rerun ./compare.
让我重新运行 ./compare。
1 and 2 are the same.
1 和 2 是相同的。
Let me rerun it.
让我重新运行它。
2 and 1 are the same.
2 和 1 是相同的。
Let me rerun it a third time.
让我第三次重新运行它。
1 and 1 are now in fact equal.
1 和 1 现在实际上是相等的。
So this works correctly.
所以，这工作正常。
But why did I make a point of using these "else if"s?
但为什么我要特别强调使用这些“else if”呢？
Put another way, couldn't I just make my life a little simpler
换句话说，我不能让我的生活更简单一些吗？
and just say, if this, then that?
只说，如果这样，那么那样？
If this, then that.
如果这样，那么那样。
Just ask all three questions.
只问三个问题。
Keep the code simple.
保持代码简单。
Don't bother with these else's.
不要理会这些 else。
Would this work for me?
这对我有用吗？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: It just seems like [INAUDIBLE] the program
学生：这看起来就像 [听不清] 程序
doesn't have to run the rest.
不必运行剩下的部分。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so it saves a little bit of time because in this case,
大卫·马兰：是的，所以它节省了一点时间，因为在这种情况下，
just like in English, this is like asking three separate questions.
就像在英语中，这就像问三个独立的问题。
And it's not harnessing any information from previous questions
并且它没有利用来自之前问题的任何信息
in order to decide whether you should bother asking that other question.
来决定你是否应该费心问另一个问题。
In other words, if x is less than y-- and you already
换句话说，如果 x 小于 y-- 而且你已经
figured that out because it's 1 and 2 respectively-- you're
弄清楚了，因为它分别是 1 和 2-- 你将
going to print this.
打印这个。
Why would you waste time asking this question when
为什么你会浪费时间问这个问题，当
it's not going to be true?
它不会是真值？
Why would you waste time asking this question when
为什么你会浪费时间问这个问题，当
it's not going to be true?
它不会是真值？
And so the point I wanted to make here, which
所以，我在这里想说的重点是，
is that if we visualize that particular design,
就是，如果我们可视化那个特定的设计，
what the flow chart looks like is actually this.
流程图实际上是这样。
And let me zoom in at the top.
让我放大顶部。
If you ask the question "is x less than y," well,
如果你问问题“x 是否小于 y”，那么
you're going to go ahead and say, x less than y.
你将继续说，x 小于 y。
Then if you go down to the next question,
然后，如果你继续往下问下一个问题，
you're still going to ask is x greater than y.
你仍然会问 x 是否大于 y。
And then below that, you're still going to ask is x equal equal to y?
然后，在下面，你仍然会问 x 是否等于等于 y？
So no matter what x and y are, you're asking one, two, three questions all
所以，无论 x 和 y 是什么，你总是要问一个、两个、三个问题
of the time.
所有时间。
But if we actually go in and do what we did the first time,
但如果我们实际上进入并做我们第一次做的事情，
where if I go back to my code and I undo this edit and add back the "else if"s--
在那里，如果我回到我的代码，撤销这个编辑并添加回“else if”--
and now let me go back to the flow chart,
现在，让我回到流程图，
which I claim is bad because it's one, two, three questions, one
我认为它不好，因为它是一个、两个、三个问题，一个
or two of which might not be necessary-- now if I visualize what I just did,
或者两个可能是不必要的--现在，如果我可视化我刚刚做的，
the flow chart gets a little more complicated looking,
流程图看起来会更复杂一些，
but it's going to be better designed, more efficient.
但它将被更好地设计，更高效。
Why?
为什么？
Well, because if I start at the top here, I ask one question,
嗯，因为如果我从这里开始，我会问一个问题，
is x less than y.
x 是否小于 y。
If the answer is true, OK.
如果答案是正确的，好的。
I say x less than y.
我会说 x 小于 y。
And then, boom, I sort of cheat and go all the way
然后，砰，我有点作弊，直接
to the end of the program and stop, having asked only one question.
到达程序的末尾并停止，只问了一个问题。
If, though, x is not less than y, OK, fine, I'll ask you a second question.
但是，如果 x 不小于 y，好的，我会问你第二个问题。
But if the answer is true, boom, I print out x is greater than y,
但如果答案是正确的，砰，我会打印出 x 大于 y，
and then I stop.
然后我停止。
And only in a perverse case where x actually
并且只有在一个奇怪的情况下，即 x 实际上
equals y, which I'm going to claim is very unlikely or infrequent,
等于 y，我将声称这种情况非常不可能或不常见，
only then am I going to ask one, two, three questions to figure out whether
只有在这种情况下，我才会问一个、两个、三个问题来弄清楚是否
or not to print something at all.
打印任何东西。
So this is what we mean by distinguishing between correctness
所以这就是我们所说的代码正确性之间的区别
of code-- because it's still correct--
因为代码仍然是正确的——
but this version is better designed because hopefully you're
但这个版本设计得更好，因为希望你会
going to go down this branch or this branch rather than the longest one
沿着这条分支或那条分支，而不是最长的分支
frequently.
频繁地。
Any questions now about this code or this visualization thereof?
现在有关这段代码或其可视化，还有问题吗？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: I don't know if [INAUDIBLE]
学生：我不知道是否 [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: A perfect segue.
戴维·马兰：这是一个完美的过渡。
Why did I bother, though, even asking this question?
不过，我为什么要费心问这个问题呢？
Don't need to because when I hit this button--
不需要，因为当我按下这个按钮——
hopefully I have the right slide in place--
希望我的幻灯片正确就位——
this would be even better than that design.
这个设计会比那个设计更好。
So thank you for teeing that up.
所以感谢你提出这个问题。
This is the same picture.
这幅图是一样的。
It sort of got bigger because there's fewer nodes,
它变得更大了一点，因为节点更少了，
fewer shapes in the picture.
图片中的形状也更少了。
Notice that if x less than y, boom, we say as much, and we stop.
注意，如果 x 小于 y，砰，我们这样说，然后停止。
If x is not less than y but it's greater than y, boom, we stop.
如果 x 不小于 y，但它大于 y，砰，我们停止。
Or if it's not greater than, we immediately
或者如果它不大于，我们立即
conclude x indeed is equal to y.
得出结论，x 确实等于 y。
And again, we stop.
然后我们再次停止。
So this picture is about as efficient and as
所以这幅图在效率和
well designed as we can make our logic.
设计方面，已经达到我们逻辑所能达到的最佳水平。
That's about as good as we can solve this problem.
这是我们所能解决这个问题的最佳方法。
So if I go back to my code now to make my C code
所以，如果我现在回到我的代码，来修改我的 C 代码，
match that, the only thing I need to do is stop wasting the computer's time.
使其与之匹配，我只需要做的事情是，停止浪费计算机的时间。
Don't ask that third question.
不要问第三个问题。
Just logically, mathematically conclude that of course it's
从逻辑上和数学上得出结论，当然它会
going to be equal at that point in the story.
在那一点上相等。
All right, any other questions on this?
好了，关于这个还有其他问题吗？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Sorry, a little louder?
戴维·马兰：抱歉，能大点声吗？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
戴维·马兰：非常好的问题。
What if I put in something that's not a number?
如果我输入了不是数字的东西，会怎么样？
So here, too, is where the CS50 library and the implementation of get_int
所以这里也是 CS50 库和 get_int 实现发挥作用的地方
will be your friend.
将会是你的好帮手。
So for instance, if I run ./compare and I want to compare cats and dogs,
例如，如果我运行 ./compare，我想比较猫和狗，
I could type in "cats," Enter.
我可以输入 "cats"，回车。
It's just going to prompt me again and again.
它会不断地提示我。
It's not going to let me type in "dogs" either.
它也不会让我输入 "dogs"。
It's going to force me to give it an integer.
它会强制我给它一个整数。
C does not do that by default.
C 不会默认这样做。
And in fact, as we'll soon see over the course of CS50,
事实上，正如我们很快将在 CS50 课程中看到的那样，
C is actually a very dangerous language at the end of the day
C 实际上是一种非常危险的语言，因为
because it just trusts that the human is doing what it wants.
它只是相信人类会按照它的意愿做事。
And as such, a lot of today's software that is hacked in some ways,
因此，今天很多以某种方式被黑客攻击的软件，
if it's using C or another language called C++,
如果它使用了 C 或另一种名为 C++ 的语言，
are actually very vulnerable to certain types of hacking,
实际上非常容易受到某些类型的黑客攻击，
whereas other languages that we'll get to in the class are less so for reasons
而我们将在课堂上学习的其他语言，由于诸如
like this.
这样的原因，不太容易受到攻击。
All right, so besides this, let's consider just one other data type.
好了，除了这个之外，让我们考虑一下另一种数据类型。
how about.
比如
So besides strings, besides chars, there's some others on this list here.
除了字符串之外，除了字符之外，这里列表中还有其他的数据类型。
Sorry, besides strings, besides integers,
抱歉，除了字符串之外，除了整数之外，
there's this other data type here in C known as a char for a single character.
在 C 中还有另一种数据类型，称为 char，用于表示单个字符。
So here, let me just tease this apart.
所以，让我来解释一下。
A string is indeed a string of text.
字符串确实是一串文本。
It is zero or more characters together.
它是由零个或多个字符组成的。
A char is always precisely one character.
char 始终是一个字符。
Not all languages bother distinguishing between a single character
并非所有语言都区分单个字符
and a string of characters.
和一串字符。
But in C, a string is typically multiple characters,
但在 C 中，字符串通常包含多个字符，
but technically can be zero.
但从技术上讲也可以是零个。
Coincidentally, it could be one.
巧合的是，它也可以是一个。
But it's capable of being more.
但它也可以是更多。
But a char is literally, as the word implies, a single character.
但 char 正如字面意思，就是单个字符。
All right, given that, notice that in the CS50 library,
好了，鉴于此，请注意在 CS50 库中，
besides get_string, besides get_int, we also have get_char,
除了 get_string，除了 get_int，我们还有 get_char，
so another handy function for just getting a single character
因此，这是另一个方便的函数，用于从用户那里获取单个字符
from the user.
。
Now, why would it be useful to get a single character from the user?
现在，为什么要从用户那里获取单个字符呢？
Well, what if you're just doing something
嗯，如果你只是在做一些
that you and I do pretty frequently when you install new software
你和我经常做的事情，比如安装新软件
or fill out some form?
或者填写一些表格？
You agree to some form of terms and conditions.
你会同意某种形式的条款和条件。
So in fact, let me go back over to VS Code here.
所以，事实上，让我回到这里的 VS Code。
And let me propose that I create a new program called agree.c,
让我提议创建一个名为 agree.c 的新程序，
so something akin to asking for the user's agreement.
所以，类似于征求用户的同意。
So in VS Code, I'm going to type "code agree.c."
所以，在 VS Code 中，我将输入 "code agree.c"。
And I'm going to do some quick boilerplate.
我将快速完成一些基本内容。
So include CS50.h, include stdio.h, int main(void).
所以，包含 CS50.h，包含 stdio.h，int main(void)。
And then inside of main, which is like the "green flag clicked,"
然后在 main 内部，这就像 "绿色旗帜被点击"，
I'm going to do this.
我要这么做。
Go ahead and get a character from the user,
获取用户输入的一个字符，
and ask them something simple like, "Do you agree?,"
并问他们一个简单的问题，例如："你同意吗？"
expecting a yes/no response.
预期得到一个“是”或“否”的答案。
But at the beginning of this line, I need to put the return value somewhere.
但在这行的开头，我需要将返回值存储到某个地方。
So I'm going to put it in a variable called
所以我将把它放到一个名为
C. And in programming, if you're just getting a single value,
C 的变量中。在编程中，如果你只是获取一个单一值，
it's OK sometimes to use X and Y or C when you're using--
有时使用 X 和 Y 或 C 也是可以的，当你使用--
in larger programs, you'll benefit from using actual words like "answer,"
在大型程序中，使用诸如“answer”之类的实际单词会更有益，
like we did from the get go.
就像我们从一开始就做的那样。
But C has to be a specific type.
但 C 必须是一种特定类型。
So I'm going to literally say "char," and then
所以我会直接写“char”，然后
I'm going to finish my thought with a semicolon.
用分号结束我的语句。
And here's now how I could check if the user agrees or not.
现在我可以检查用户是否同意。
I could do something like this.
我可以这样写。
If the value of C equals equals, quote, unquote,
如果 C 的值等于等于，双引号，双引号，
lowercase 'y,' then go ahead and print out "Agreed backslash n."
小写的 'y'，那么就打印 "Agreed backslash n"。
Else if the variable C has a value equal to lowercase 'n', let's go ahead
否则，如果变量 C 的值为小写的 'n'，我们继续
and print out, say, "Not agreed," as though I'm agreeing or not to some
打印 "Not agreed"，就好像我同意或不同意某些
terms and conditions.
条款和条件。
But notice these are not typos.
但注意，这些不是错误输入。
What did I do ever so subtly different from last time I used text?
我做了什么微妙的改变，和上次我使用文本时不同？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: Single quotes instead of double quotes.
学生：使用单引号而不是双引号。
DAVID MALAN: Single quotes instead of double quotes.
大卫·马兰：使用单引号而不是双引号。
So here's the heuristic.
所以这里有一个经验法则。
When using strings, which are generally multiple characters,
当你使用字符串，通常包含多个字符，
have to use double quotes.
必须使用双引号。
When using a single character, you should use single quotes
当你使用单个字符，应该使用单引号
around the single character.
将单个字符括起来。
So let me go ahead now and, make agree.
现在让我运行一下，让程序同意。
Nothing went wrong, which is good. ./agree, Enter,
没有任何错误，这很好。 ./agree，回车，
and let me go ahead and type in y for yes.
让我输入 y 代表 yes。
It seems to work.
它似乎工作正常。
Let me run it again. ./agree. n for no, and it seems to work.
我再运行一次。 ./agree。n 代表 no，它似乎工作正常。
And just if I type in something random like question mark, I don't know,
如果我输入一个随机的字符，比如问号，我不知道，
it doesn't crash.
它不会崩溃。
It just ignores me because I only had two Boolean expressions there.
它只是忽略了我，因为我只有两个布尔表达式。
But notice that it's actually a little buggy arguably.
但请注意，它实际上可能有点bug。
Let me run it again. ./agree, Enter.
我再运行一次。 ./agree，回车。
How about capital Y because, like, my Caps Lock is down.
大写的 Y 怎么样？因为我的 Caps Lock 键坏了。
OK, it just ignores me.
好的，它只是忽略了我。
Let me do it again. ./agree, capital N because my-- oops--
我再试一次。 ./agree，大写的 N，因为我的-- Oops--
because my Caps Lock is down.
因为我的 Caps Lock 键坏了。
OK, it just ignores me.
好的，它只是忽略了我。
But this should make sense because I'm literally checking for lowercase.
但这应该是有道理的，因为我实际上只检查了小写字母。
So how could I fix this?
那么我该如何解决这个问题？
How could I fix this without just changing lowercase to uppercase,
我该如何解决这个问题，而不只是将小写字母改为大写字母，
because that would then break it in the other direction?
因为那样就会在另一个方向上产生错误？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, let's just add another branch here, so to speak.
大卫·马兰：好的，我们在这里添加另一个分支。
So if variable C equals equals capital Y, then I can go ahead here
所以，如果变量 C 等于等于大写的 Y，那么我就可以在这里
and say printf agreed.
写上 printf agreed。
And then let me close my terminal to make more room.
然后，我关闭我的终端，腾出更多空间。
Otherwise, down here, else if C equals equals capital N,
否则，在这里，else if C 等于等于大写的 N，
let's go ahead and again say printf not agreed.
我们继续写上 printf not agreed。
And I claim that this would actually now work.
我认为这样应该可以正常工作了。
It's a four-way fork in the road, but I'm at least
这是一个四叉路口，但我至少
checking for lowercase, uppercase, lowercase, uppercase for y and n
检查了 y 和 n 的小写字母、大写字母、小写字母、大写字母
respectively.
分别。
I claim that this is correct, but this too,
我认为这样是正确的，但这样也
even if you've never programmed before, should start today
即使你之前从未编程过，也应该从今天开始
to rub you the wrong way.
让你感到不舒服。
Like, we can do better.
就像，我们可以做得更好。
This isn't the best design.
这不是最好的设计。
Why might that be?
为什么这么说？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: Could you change the character c to be uppercase, like before you even
学生： 你可以将字符 c 更改为大写字母，就像你在输入之前
[INAUDIBLE]?
[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Ah, clever.
大卫·马兰：哦，很聪明。
So could we change the variable c to just be forced to uppercase
所以我们可以将变量 c 强制转换为大写字母
or maybe forced to lowercase?
或者强制转换为小写字母？
No matter what the human types, we just do that ourselves so that way
无论人类输入什么，我们自己做就可以了，这样
we can just simplify this again to two possible scenarios.
我们可以将它简化为两种可能的情况。
I love that, but we haven't seen any functions yet
我喜欢这个想法，但我们还没有看到任何函数
in C that would let me change things to uppercase or lowercase.
在 C 中可以将字符转换为大写或小写字母。
So we'll get there, but a good instinct and correct.
我们会学到的，但这是一个很好的直觉，也是正确的。
Other thoughts?
还有其他的想法吗？
STUDENT: Use "or."
学生：使用“或”。
DAVID MALAN: So we could use "or" in some sense, like a logical "or."
大卫·马兰：所以我们可以使用某种意义上的“或”，就像逻辑上的“或”。
What I don't like about this, to be clear, is that it's repeating itself.
我要说清楚，我不喜欢这一点，因为它重复了自己。
And there's this principle in programming, and in life in general,
在编程中，以及生活中，有一个原则，
like, don't repeat yourself unnecessarily.
就是不要无谓地重复。
And by that I mean I literally have the same line 10 as 14.
我的意思是，第 10 行和第 14 行完全相同。
I have the same line 18 as 22.
第 18 行和第 22 行也完全相同。
And if anything, one, I literally wasted twice as much time as I needed to.
而且，我浪费了两倍于必要的时间。
Put another way, per our discussion of Scratch,
换句话说，根据我们之前对 Scratch 的讨论，
what if I go in and just change something like,
如果我进入程序并更改某些内容，例如，
I want to be more excited, like "Agreed!"?
我想更兴奋一些，例如 "Agreed!"？
Well, I might forget to change it in the other place.
那么，我可能会忘记在另一个地方进行修改。
And let's just claim for today's purposes that that looks stupid,
而且，今天就假设那看起来很愚蠢，
it's a bug, because I want them to be consistent.
这是一个错误，因为我希望它们保持一致。
So don't invite situations where you might change something
所以，不要让代码出现你可能在一个地方修改，
in one place but not another.
而在另一个地方却没有修改的情况。
Just only write it in one place total.
只在一个地方写就行了。
So I like this idea of "or"-ing things together.
我喜欢将它们用“或”连接起来的想法。
So let me go ahead and delete what I just did.
所以我删除掉我刚写的代码。
And just to be clear, too, while this is on the screen, when you highlight code
为了更清楚起见，当你在屏幕上高亮代码时，
in VS Code based on how we've configured it, these dots just show you
在 VS Code 中，根据我们的配置，这些点只是显示
how much I've indented because in C, stylistically, the convention
我缩进了多少，因为在 C 语言中，从风格上来说，约定俗成的是
is generally to indent four spaces and maybe four more spaces.
通常缩进四个空格，可能还要再缩进四个空格。
So those dots just help you count without having
所以，这些点可以帮助你计数，而无需
to manually eyeball things yourself.
手动去估算。
But let me delete those lines.
但让我删除这些行。
Let me delete these lines.
让我删除这些行。
And this is going to look a little weird,
这看起来会有点奇怪，
but the way you can "or" two thoughts together, so to
但是，你可以将两个想法“或”在一起，也就是说，
speak, like "or" them together, is you don't say "or,"
将它们“或”在一起，你不会说“或”，
but you use two vertical bars, which syntactically
而是使用两个竖线，在语法上，
means the English word "or."
就代表英语单词“或”。
And you can just ask the other question, if C equals,
你也可以问另一个问题，如果 C 等于
quote, unquote, capital 'Y.'
引号引号，大写的‘Y’。
And then down here, I can say or C equals equals capital 'N.'
然后在下面，我可以说或者 C 等于等于大写的‘N’。
So it adds a little more code to each of those lines,
所以它给每一行都增加了一点代码，
but it doesn't add redundancy, because I've not duplicated my printf.
但它并没有增加冗余，因为我没有重复我的 printf。
I've not added more curly braces unnecessarily.
我没有无端地添加更多花括号。
Now as an aside, there's the opposite of "or", logically is the word "and."
顺便说一句，与“或”相反，在逻辑上就是“与”。
Just so you've seen it, I could do this.
为了让你看到它，我可以这样做。
"&&" in C is how you express that the thing on the left must be true
在 C 语言中，"&&" 表示左边的表达式必须为真
and the thing on the right must be true.
而右边的表达式也必须为真。
But why would this make no sense in this context of line 8?
但是，为什么在第 8 行的上下文中，这毫无意义呢？
STUDENT: It can't be uppercase and lowercase.
学生：它不可能既是大写又是小写。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, at least to my knowledge,
大卫·马兰：是的，至少据我所知，
a character can't be both lowercase and uppercase.
一个字符不可能既是小写又是大写。
That just makes no logical sense.
这在逻辑上说不通。
So indeed "or" is what we want in this case.
所以，在这种情况下，我们确实需要“或”。
Other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
STUDENT: In CS50.h, is there a way to directly compare strings [INAUDIBLE]??
学生：在 CS50.h 中，有没有办法直接比较字符串 [听不清]？
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
大卫·马兰：好问题。
Via CS50.h, is there a way to compare strings.
通过 CS50.h，有没有办法比较字符串。
Short answer, no.
简短的回答，没有。
But C is going to give us that capability.
但是，C 语言会给我们提供这种能力。
And in fact, next week, among the things we'll do is actually compare strings.
事实上，下周，我们将会做的事情之一就是比较字符串。
And if you've programmed before, you'll see in C
如果你之前做过编程，你会在 C 语言中看到
that it actually doesn't work the way that you might expect.
它实际上并没有按照你预期的方式工作。
But that's a problem, too, that we will solve.
但这也是一个问题，我们会解决的。
But that transcends CS50.
但这超出了 CS50 的范畴。
That's a question for C. Other questions on this kind of logic?
这是关于 C 语言的问题。关于这种逻辑还有其他问题吗？
Just to make this real then, anytime you click one of those EULAs
为了使这一点变得真实，每当你点击那些 EULA
or terms and conditions on a form in a piece of software,
或软件中表格上的条款和条件时，
odds are there is code as simple as this underneath the hood.
很可能，在幕后会有像这样的简单代码。
Maybe it's graphical.
也许它是图形化的。
Maybe it's checking for you clicking this button
也许它在检查你是否点击了这个按钮
or maybe hitting the Enter key.
或者是否按下了回车键。
But underneath the hood is presumably some kind
但在幕后，很可能有一些
of conditional checking for those kinds of outputs.
条件检查来处理这些输出。
All right, how about another building block
好了，再来看看上一次的另一个构建块，
from last time, which we'll now translate to C,
现在我们将把它翻译成 C 语言，
namely loops, things that happen again and again?
也就是循环，反复发生的事情？
And these, too, are everywhere in code.
这些东西在代码中随处可见。
So in Scratch, here's how we might meow three times, super simple.
所以在 Scratch 中，我们可以用以下方法发出三声喵叫，非常简单。
In C, it's going to look a little weird.
在 C 语言中，它看起来会有点奇怪。
But you will get used to this over time if you've never programmed before.
但如果你以前从未做过编程，你会随着时间的推移逐渐习惯的。
It looks like a mouthful, OK.
它看起来很繁琐，好吧。
But let's tease it apart line by line.
但让我们逐行分析一下。
And you'll see that you won't have that reaction frequently because it's all
你会发现，你不会经常有这种反应，因为所有这些
going to start to look very similar to itself.
都会开始看起来非常相似。
But what are we doing here?
但我们在做什么呢？
In C, you don't have the luxury of these cute and fun puzzle pieces
在 C 语言中，你没有这些可爱有趣拼图块的便利，
that just do the work for you, repeat three times.
它们为你完成工作，重复三次。
In fact, in C and programming in general, sometimes
事实上，在 C 语言和一般的编程中，有时
the work is on us to actually figure out, OK,
我们要自己想办法解决，好吧，
how can I use functions, variables, conditionals, and loops
我怎样才能使用函数、变量、条件语句和循环
and implement some idea like repetition, like looping?
来实现重复这样的概念，比如循环？
And in C, here's how this might work.
而在 C 语言中，它可能是这样工作的。
How can I go about doing something like printing "meow" three times?
我如何才能做到像打印“喵”三次这样的事情呢？
Well, I know about variables now.
好吧，我现在知道变量了。
We're about to see loops.
我们马上就要看到循环了。
And I've seen how I can update variables by plussing or minusing
我已经看到了如何通过加减来更新变量
some value to them.
某个值。
Let's combine those ideas.
让我们把这些想法结合起来。
So first, I'm doing what with this highlighted line in English?
那么首先，用英语来说，我用这行高亮的代码在做什么呢？
If a friend cared to ask you, like, 'what is this line of code doing'
如果一个朋友想知道，比如，‘这行代码在做什么’
later today, what would you say?
今天晚些时候，你会怎么说？
STUDENT: It's creating a variable called "counter" and setting it equal to 3.
学生：它创建了一个名为“counter”的变量，并将其设置为 3。
DAVID MALAN: Good, it's creating a variable called "counter"
大卫·马兰：很好，它创建了一个名为“counter”的变量
and setting it equal to 3.
并将其设置为 3。
I'll use slightly new jargon.
我将使用一些新的术语。
I'm defining a variable, would be the term of our "called counter"
我正在定义一个变量，我们把它叫做“counter”
and setting it equal to 3.
并将其设置为 3。
So I'll use my hand to represent the counter.
所以我将用我的手来代表计数器。
And that's all a variable is.
而这就是变量的全部。
It's like storage in some case that I'm representing information, using
它就像一个存储器，我用它来表示信息，使用
my hand in this case or the computer's memory here.
我的手在这个例子中，或者计算机的内存在这里。
Now what happens when using a loop in C?
现在，在 C 语言中使用循环会发生什么？
There's different types of loops, one of which is called a for loop-- oop--
有很多不同类型的循环，其中之一叫做 for 循环——oop——
one of which is called a while loop-- spoiler.
其中之一叫做 while 循环——剧透一下。
A while loop works like this.
while 循环是这样的。
Inside of parentheses is a Boolean expression just like inside
在括号里面是一个布尔表达式，就像在
of a conditional that asks a question.
条件语句中询问问题一样。
But this time the question is going to determine,
但这一次，问题将决定，
do you keep going through the loop again and again and again?
你是否一遍又一遍地循环下去？
So it's not a one-time thing potentially.
所以这可能不是一次性的事情。
It is checked again and again and again to decide
它一遍又一遍地检查，以决定
when it is time to stop looping, to stop cycling.
何时停止循环，停止循环。
All right, so it's asking this question first.
好的，所以它首先问这个问题。
Is counter greater than 0?
计数器是否大于 0？
OK, obviously the answer is true because I'm still holding up three fingers.
好吧，答案显然是正确的，因为我仍然举着三根手指。
So what happens?
那么会发生什么？
C goes inside of the curly braces per the indentation
C 按照缩进进入花括号内
and executes printf of "meow," which prints out a "meow" on the screen.
并执行 "meow" 的 printf，它在屏幕上打印出 "meow"。
The next line of code executes, which, recall,
下一行代码被执行，回想一下，
is the same as just subtracting 1 from counter.
它和从计数器中减去 1 是相同的。
So I think I take down one finger, so I'm left with two.
所以我想我放下了一根手指，现在剩下两根了。
And what happens next?
接下来会发生什么？
Well, this you just kind of have to memorize.
好吧，这个你就必须记住。
Once you get to the end of the inside of a loop,
当你到达循环内部的末尾时，
you go back to the beginning of a loop here
你回到这里循环的开头
and ask the same question, the same Boolean expression.
并问相同的问题，相同的布尔表达式。
So is 2 greater than 0?
所以 2 大于 0 吗？
OK, obviously so.
好吧，显然是。
So you go into it, you print a "meow."
所以你进入它，你打印一个 "meow"。
You go into it and decrement counter further by one.
你进入它并将计数器再减 1。
So now my hand is holding up one.
所以现在我的手举起一根手指。
Now we wrap back around to the Boolean expression.
现在我们回到布尔表达式。
Is 1 greater than 0?
1 大于 0 吗？
Obviously.
显然是。
We print out a third "meow."
我们打印出第三个 "meow"。
We then decrement counter again, and my hand goes to zero.
然后我们再次减小计数器，我的手变为零。
We go back around once more.
我们再绕一圈。
Is 0 greater than 0?
0 大于 0 吗？
No.
不。
And now the program just terminates.
现在程序就结束了。
Or if there were more code here, it would just
或者如果这里有更多代码，它就会
jump outside of the curly braces and keep going lower on the screen.
跳出花括号，继续向下移动到屏幕上。
So that's all that's happening.
这就是发生的所有事情。
And so this is what MIT has the luxury of doing with pictures.
所以，这就是麻省理工学院可以用图片做到的。
But at MIT, someone probably essentially wrote
但在麻省理工学院，有人可能基本上写了
code that looks like this to give us the illusion, the abstraction of this.
看起来像这样的代码来给我们这种错觉，这种抽象。
So what we're learning today is how they invented these puzzle pieces
所以我们今天学习的是他们如何利用这些低级管道，如果你愿意的话，就像这样，
by just using lower-level plumbing, if you will, like this here.
发明了这些拼图块。
Yeah?
对吧？
STUDENT: What would happen if you created the variable "counter"
学生：如果你在花括号内创建变量 "counter" 会怎么样？
inside of the curly braces?
在花括号内？
DAVID MALAN: A really good question.
大卫·马兰：这是一个很好的问题。
What would happen if you created the variable inside of the curly braces?
如果你在花括号内创建变量会怎么样？
Short answer, it just wouldn't work in C,
简短的答案，它在 C 中不起作用，
because if I were to try with my slide here,
因为如果我要用我的幻灯片来试一下，
for instance, to move this line of code here down inside of this, for instance,
例如，将这行代码移到这里，例如，
now the very top line is trying to use counter before it even exists.
现在最上面的那行代码试图在它存在之前使用计数器。
So C is very literal it.
所以 C 非常严格。
Reads top to bottom, left to right.
从上到下，从左到右读取。
And if it hasn't seen you define or create a variable yet,
如果它还没有看到你定义或创建变量，
you're going to get some scary error message on the screen instead.
你将在屏幕上看到一些可怕的错误信息。
All right, other questions on this here code?
好的，关于这段代码还有其他问题吗？
No?
没有？
All right, so if we want to then maybe tighten this up a bit,
好的，如果我们想要紧凑一些，
let me propose that we could do this instead.
我建议我们可以这样做。
So besides this version of the code, let me just
除了这段代码之外，让我只
do something more canonical, more conventional.
做一些更规范、更传统的事情。
So you're totally fine with using a variable like counter .
所以你完全可以接受使用像 counter 这样的变量。
It's what Scratch uses by default. It's very verbose.
这是 Scratch 默认使用的，它非常冗长。
It does what it says.
它做它说的事。
Frankly, once you get comfy with programming,
坦白地说，一旦你对编程感到舒适，
like most typical programmers, whenever they
就像大多数典型的程序员一样，每当他们
have a single integer in a program whose sole purpose in life is to count,
在一个程序中有一个唯一的整数，它的唯一目的是计数，
they'll just use "i" for integer just like I used "c" for character.
他们会像我使用 "c" 来表示字符一样，使用 "i" 来表示整数。
When you have larger programs, you don't want
当你拥有更大的程序时，你不会想要
to start using A and B and C and D and E and F and so forth for your variables
使用 A、B、C、D、E、F 等等作为你的变量，
because nothing's going to make any sense.
因为什么都说不通。
But when you're doing something super simple like counting with an integer,
但当你做一些非常简单的事情，比如用整数计数时，
using a short-named variable is totally stylistically reasonable.
使用短命名的变量在风格上是完全合理的。
But I can tighten this up further, not just renaming counter to i.
但我可以进一步压缩它，不仅仅是将计数器重命名为 i。
What else can I do, if you recall?
你还记得我还能做什么吗？
Over here?
在这里？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Sure.
大卫·马兰：当然。
STUDENT: A for loop?
学生：一个 for 循环？
DAVID MALAN: Oh, OK, for loop.
大卫·马兰：哦，好的，for 循环。
Yes, that was my spoiler.
是的，那是我剧透的。
But while in a while loop, I can tighten this up slightly more.
但在 while 循环中，我可以进一步压缩它。
Over here?
在这里？
STUDENT: Instead of i equals i minus 1.
学生：而不是 i 等于 i 减 1。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, instead of i equals i minus 1,
大卫·马兰：是的，而不是 i 等于 i 减 1，
I can actually tighten this up this way.
我实际上可以这样压缩它。
And we didn't see the minus before, but it's
我们之前没有看到减号，但它是
the same idea-- i minus equals 1, or even more succinctly, i minus minus.
同一个想法——i 减等于 1，或者更简洁地说，i 减减。
So when you get comfortable with programming, any of these approaches
所以当你对编程感到舒适时，这些方法中的任何一种
are correct.
都是正确的。
This would be more conventional at this point.
现在，这将更常规。
So if you want to write code like most other people
所以如果你想像大多数其他人一样写代码，
write code, adopt ultimately these kinds of conventions.
写代码，最终采用这些约定。
All right, so that just does the exact same thing, though.
好的，虽然这只是做了完全相同的事情。
But let's now put this into practice.
但现在让我们把它付诸实践。
Let me go back to VS Code here.
让我回到这里的 VS Code。
Let me go ahead and clear my terminal and close agree.c from before.
让我清除我的终端，并关闭之前的 agree.c。
And let me go ahead and create a file called "meow."
让我创建一个名为 "meow" 的文件。
So code meow.c.
所以代码 meow.c。
And let me do this the sort of wrong way.
让我用错误的方式来做这件事。
Let me include stdio.h.
让我包含 stdio.h。
at the top, int main(void) thereafter.
在顶部，int main(void) 之后。
Inside of there, let me do printf "meow."
在里面，让我执行 printf "meow"。
And then you know what?
然后你知道吗？
I don't want to keep typing that.
我不想一直打字。
Let me just go ahead and copy/paste two more times.
让我直接复制粘贴两次。
So I claim this is correct, make meow.
所以，我认为这是正确的，运行 meow。
./meow, done.
./meow，完成。
I've got code that prints "meow" three times.
我写了三遍打印“meow”的代码。
But this, again, should already rub you the wrong way.
但是，这，再次强调，应该让你感到不舒服。
Why?
为什么？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: There's duplication.
学生：代码重复了。
DAVID MALAN: Because what?
大卫·马兰：因为什么？
STUDENT: There's duplication.
学生：代码重复了。
DAVID MALAN: Because I have duplication.
大卫·马兰：因为我的代码重复了。
I mean, I literally copied and pasted it.
我的意思是，我直接复制粘贴了。
And that's kind of a good rule of thumb.
这是一个经验法则。
If you, in the future, start finding yourself copying and pasting code
如果你在未来开始发现自己复制粘贴代码
within the same program, you're probably doing something wrong.
在同一个程序中，你可能做错了什么。
There's a better way to design it even if it's correct.
即使它是正确的，也有一种更好的设计方法。
So this is clearly a candidate for a loop.
所以这显然是一个循环的候选者。
So let me go ahead and actually do that.
所以，让我继续执行。
Let me just go ahead and remove all of this duplication.
让我直接删除所有重复代码。
Let me give myself a variable called i, set it equal to 3.
让我给自己一个名为 i 的变量，并将其设置为 3。
Let me go ahead and give myself a while loop
让我给自己一个 while 循环
and check that i is greater than 0.
并检查 i 是否大于 0。
Inside of this loop, let me print out just "meow" once.
在这个循环中，让我打印一次“meow”。
But I'll reuse that code again and again because here I'm
但是，我会反复使用这段代码，因为在这里我
going to do i minus minus.
将执行 i 减减。
So that's the exact same code, the tight version of it that we saw a moment ago.
所以，这是完全相同的代码，是我们刚才看到的紧凑版本。
Let me go ahead and "make meow" again, ./meow, and it still works.
让我继续运行“make meow”，./meow，它仍然有效。
Why is this version better?
为什么这个版本更好？
Because if you want the cat to meow five times, you change it in one place.
因为如果你想让猫叫五声，你只需要在一个地方进行修改。
If you want to make the cat a dog, you change the meow to a woof in one place,
如果你想把猫变成狗，你只需要在一个地方将 meow 改为 woof，
albeit changing the file name eventually, but changing it
虽然最终要更改文件名，但修改
in one place, not worrying about changing it again and again and again.
只需要在一个地方，而不用担心反复修改。
But there are other ways to do this.
但是还有其他方法可以做到。
For instance, let me propose that.
例如，我建议这样做。
And actually, let's see, let me propose that instead of just doing it this way,
实际上，让我们看看，我建议不要用这种方式，
just to be clear--
为了清楚起见，
yeah, let's go ahead and propose that instead of doing this,
是的，让我们继续建议不要这样做，
we can actually count in different directions.
我们可以用不同的方向计数。
I'm kind of forcing this idea of starting at 3, going down to 0.
我有点强迫大家接受从 3 开始，然后降到 0 的想法。
But when normal humans in this room, if you ever count something,
但是，当房间里正常的人类，如果你曾经数过东西，
you probably do 1, 2, 3, and done.
你可能就会 1，2，3，然后就完了。
Like, that's how we would count in the real world.
就像，这是我们在现实世界中计数的方式。
Well, we can do that, too, here code-wise.
好吧，我们也可以在代码中做到这一点。
We could initialize i to 1.
我们可以将 i 初始化为 1。
We could check that i is less than or equal to 3.
我们可以检查 i 是否小于或等于 3。
And we've not seen this syntax before, but there's
我们以前没有见过这种语法，但这里有
no easy way on a typical keyboard to type a less than or equal sign
在普通键盘上没有简单的方法来输入小于或等于符号
like in a math book.
就像数学书那样。
So we use two characters, a less-than sign and then an equal sign
所以我们使用两个字符，一个小于符号，然后是一个等于符号
back to back.
紧挨着。
And that means less than or equal to.
这意味着小于或等于。
And this is the same idea so long as I plus plus i inside of it
只要我在里面加上 i 的值
because that'll start at 1, then 2, but it won't stop then.
因为这将从 1 开始，然后是 2，但不会在那时停止。
It will go up to until i is equal to 3.
它将一直持续到 i 等于 3。
Once i becomes 4, then that Boolean expression isn't going to be true.
一旦 i 变成 4，那么这个布尔表达式将不再为真。
So it stops after three "meow"s total.
所以，它总共在三次“meow”之后停止。
But there's another way, too, and this is probably
但是，还有另一种方法，这可能是
the most conventional and the way you should do it
最传统的方法，也是你应该采用的方法
even though it's just as correct.
虽然它也是正确的。
In CS, if you've seen already last week, we almost always start counting from 0.
在 CS 中，如果你上周已经了解过，我们几乎总是从 0 开始计数。
Why?
为什么？
Just because, so we're not wasting a pattern of bits.
仅仅是因为，这样我们就不会浪费一串比特。
So generally when you start writing code that counts,
所以，通常当你开始编写计数的代码时，
you should, quote, unquote, "almost always" start at 0,
你应该，引号，引号，"几乎总是"从 0 开始，
count up to but not through the total you
计数到，但不要超过你
care about so you don't get one extra by accident.
关心的总数，这样你不会意外多出一个。
And so this would be the most conventional way
所以，这将是我们刚才描述的最传统的方法
of doing what we just described.
来完成我们刚才描述的事情。
But they're all correct.
但它们都是正确的。
You can make an argument that all of them are equally good.
你可以争辩说它们都同样好。
This is what most people, quote, unquote, "would do."
这是大多数人，引号，引号，"会做的事情"。
OK, other questions on this here syntax or logic?
好的，关于这种语法或逻辑，还有其他问题吗？
No?
没有？
All right, how about--
好的，怎么样 -
we got some cookies on the horizon.
我们快有饼干了。
But before we get there, let's meow a few more times, if we may.
但在我们到达那里之前，让我们再叫几声“meow”，如果可以的话。
So how about doing a little bit differently versus the while loop.
那么，与 while 循环相比，我们如何进行一些不同的操作呢？
And I think we heard it over here.
我认为我们在这里听到了。
Turns out there's another type of loop altogether.
事实证明，还存在另一种类型的循环。
So this one here.
所以，这个循环。
And this one, if you can believe it, is probably even more conventional
而且这个循环，如果你相信的话，可能比另一种方法更传统
than the other way.
更传统。
And this is going to be thematic in programming.
这在编程中将是主题性的。
There's rarely one way, one right way to do things.
很少有一种方法，一种正确的方法来做事情。
You're going to have bunches of different tools in your toolkit.
你的工具箱里会有很多不同的工具。
And your code might look different from someone else's because each of you
你的代码可能与别人的代码看起来不同，因为你们每个人
tends to reach for a different tool in that toolkit.
倾向于从工具箱中选择不同的工具。
And here's another tool--
这是另一个工具 -
and as you proposed earlier--
正如你之前所建议的那样 -
a for loop.
一个 for 循环。
A for loop is just another way of achieving the exact same idea
一个 for 循环只是实现完全相同想法的另一种方式
using slightly different syntax.
使用略微不同的语法。
And it's appealing, frankly in general, because it's a little more succinct.
坦率地说，它一般来说比较吸引人，因为它更简洁。
It just saves some keystrokes even though you have to memorize
它可以节省一些按键，即使你必须记住
the order in which it works.
它工作的顺序。
This code is identical to this code here functionally.
从功能上来说，这段代码和这里这段代码是一样的。
But aesthetically, of course, it looks different.
但从美学上来说，它看起来当然不同。
How does it work?
它是如何工作的？
In a for loop, notice that in the parentheses
在for循环中，请注意在括号中
is not a single simple Boolean expression.
不是一个简单的布尔表达式。
There are three things.
有三个东西。
One, before a semicolon, is a place to initialize a variable
第一个，在分号之前，是初始化变量的地方
to do your counting typically.
通常用于计数。
Second is the Boolean expression.
第二个是布尔表达式。
So it's still there.
所以它还在那里。
It's just surrounded on the left and the right by two other things.
它只是被另外两个东西包围着。
Lastly is the update.
最后一个是更新。
What do you want to do at the end of every loop through this block of code?
在循环通过这段代码的末尾，你想做什么？
So you can probably imagine where we're going with this.
所以你可能已经猜到我们要做什么了。
How does this work?
它是如何工作的？
The first thing that happens is that a variable
首先发生的是一个变量
called i is defined and initialized to the value of 0.
叫做i被定义并初始化为0。
That happens once and only once.
这只会发生一次。
Then we check the condition.
然后我们检查条件。
Is 0 less than 3?
0小于3吗？
Obviously yes.
很明显是的。
So now we don't do the plus plus yet.
所以现在我们还没有做加加操作。
We go into the loop.
我们进入循环。
And this is where the for loop's a little confusing at first.
刚开始的时候，for循环有点让人困惑。
We print out "meow."
我们打印出“喵”。
Then what happens?
然后发生了什么？
There's no more lines.
没有更多的行。
So we go back to the for loop, and we increment i at that point.
所以我们回到for循环，然后在那个时候增加i的值。
So now i is 1.
所以现在i是1。
Then we check the condition. i is less than 3?
然后我们检查条件。i小于3吗？
Yes, because 1 is less than 3.
是的，因为1小于3。
We go back into the loop and print "meow."
我们回到循环中，并打印出“喵”。
Now we go back to the plus plus, so i is now 2.
现在我们回到加加操作，所以i现在是2。
We check the condition.
我们检查条件。
2 is less than 3 obviously.
2显然小于3。
So we go back into the loop and print "meow."
所以我们回到循环中，并打印出“喵”。
Then we do the increment. i is now 3.
然后我们进行增量操作。i现在是3。
Is 3 less than 3?
3小于3吗？
No, so we exit the loop, and we're done, or we keep
不是，所以我们退出循环，然后就完成了，或者我们继续
going down here if there's more code.
如果还有更多的代码，则继续向下执行。
But how many times did I say "meow?"
但我说了多少次“喵”？
1, 2, 3 total, when my hand was 0, 1, and 2.
一共说了1、2、3次，当我的手是0、1、2的时候。
Questions on this alternative syntax?
关于这种替代语法，有什么问题吗？
It takes some getting used to, but most people
它需要一些时间来适应，但大多数人
would write loops using a for loop, I would say.
会使用for循环来写循环，我会说。
STUDENT: Could you now in the curly braces, use just one line of code?
学生：你现在可以在花括号中只使用一行代码吗？
DAVID MALAN: Yes.
大卫·马兰：是的。
If you really want to be cool and save syntax,
如果你真的想酷一点，节省语法，
yes, it is correct and common to eliminate the curly braces if you only
是的，如果你只有一行代码，那么省略花括号是正确且常见的。
have one line of code therein.
只有一行代码。
We in class will always put the curly braces there
我们在课堂上会一直放上花括号
because this is the kind of thing where, if you get forgetful, you go in later
因为这是那种，如果你健忘，你以后再去
and add a second line.
添加第二行。
Like, darn it, like you forgot the curly braces,
就像，该死，你忘了花括号，
things will not work as expected.
事情将不会按预期进行。
So in general, use the curly braces, but you do not have to strictly.
所以一般来说，使用花括号，但你没有必要严格要求。
Other questions on 6?
关于第6题还有其他问题吗？
Yes?
有吗？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Can be used without, what?
大卫·马兰：可以不用什么？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Oh, could you do it without the condition?
大卫·马兰：哦，你能不用条件吗？
Yes, there are very fancy things you can do that we won't focus on today.
是的，你可以做很多非常花哨的事情，我们今天不会关注它们。
But yes, if you want to get rid of the condition, you could get rid of this
但是是的，如果你想摆脱条件，你可以摆脱这个
here.
这里。
And that would actually make the loop go forever,
这实际上会使循环永远运行，
which may be a good thing if it's like a clock
如果它像一个钟表，这可能是一件好事
that you want to tick forever, but often not a good thing in code.
你想要它永远走动，但在代码中这通常不是一件好事。
Good question, though.
不过，这是一个好问题。
All right, so beyond that, let's just go ahead and put this into context.
好的，除此之外，让我们继续把它放到上下文中。
Just in case it helps you to think about this,
以防万一这能帮助你思考这个问题，
this is just another flow chart, if you're
这是一个流程图，如果你是一个
more of a visual thinker, that represents
视觉型思考者，它代表着
what it is this loop is now doing.
这个循环现在正在做什么。
Previously, all of our arrows went from top to bottom and stopped.
之前，我们所有的箭头都从上到下，然后停止。
But now there's an arrow going back, up, and around
但现在有一个箭头向后、向上和环绕
because of this loop, this cycle.
因为这个循环，这个循环。
So when we start this program, we set i equal to 0.
所以当我们启动这个程序时，我们将i设置为0。
We then check, is i less than 3?
然后我们检查，i小于3吗？
Obviously it is, so we print "meow."
很明显是的，所以我们打印出“喵”。
We increment i, and then we go back to that same condition.
我们增加i的值，然后返回到相同的条件。
We check the condition.
我们检查条件。
We print "meow."
我们打印出“喵”。
i plus plus, go back, go back.
i加加，返回，返回。
Now, if i equals 3, 3 is not less than 3, so the answer is false.
现在，如果i等于3，3不小于3，所以答案是假的。
And we stop.
然后我们停止。
So again, it's just another way of thinking
所以，这又是一种思考方式
about how the code in Scratch, how the code in C
关于Scratch中的代码，C中的代码
might alternatively work in each of these contexts.
如何在这些上下文中交替工作。
But there's this one other puzzle piece in Scratch,
但在Scratch中还有一个拼图块，
recall, that's not the repeat block, which
回想一下，那不是“重复”块，而是
is for finite numbers of repetitions, but forever.
用于有限次数的重复，而是永远。
And in C, there is a way to do this, but it's a little weird looking.
在C语言中，有一种方法可以做到这一点，但看起来有点奇怪。
There's no forever keyword.
没有“永远”关键字。
But you can use the while loop or, as you inferred,
但你可以使用while循环，或者，正如你推断的那样，
you can actually use the for loop without a condition in the middle.
你实际上可以使用for循环，中间没有条件。
So here, I can actually say this.
所以在这里，我实际上可以这么说。
If I want to do something forever, I want
如果我想永远做某事，我想
to make sure that the answer to my question, the Boolean expression,
确保我问题的答案，布尔表达式，
is always true, always true, always true,
永远为真，永远为真，永远为真
the easiest way to achieve that goal is just literally write "true" there
实现这个目标最简单的方法就是直接写"true"
because true is true no matter what.
因为无论如何，真就是真。
And it's a trick for making the loop forever
这是一个让循环永无止境的技巧
go around and around, as you might if you
一遍遍地循环，就像你可能想
want the cat to live forever and meow incessantly
让猫永远活着，不断地喵喵叫
or if it is a clock that you want to tick forever or the like.
或者如果你想要一个永远滴答作响的钟表等等。
So here, for instance, is how we might have a cat meow endlessly,
例如，这里是如何让一只猫无限地喵喵叫的
using this so-called for loop instead.
使用这个所谓的for循环。
But recall that in Scratch, we also had this ability
但请记住，在Scratch中，我们也有这种能力
to create some of our own puzzle pieces.
创建我们自己的积木。
And this, too, is something that we're going to be able to do here in C.
在C语言中，我们也能做到这一点。
And let me propose that we do exactly that
我建议我们这样做
by introducing the C analog of this.
通过引入C语言的等效代码。
So here, for instance, is, in Scratch, our definition
例如，在Scratch中，这是我们对
of a function called meow whose sole purpose in life
名为"meow"的函数的定义，它的唯一目的
was to just play the sound "meow" until it's done.
只是播放“喵”的声音，直到播放完毕。
This is going to look a little weird at first.
乍一看，这会有点奇怪。
But you'll notice some similarities with main.
但你会注意到它与main有一些相似之处。
So recall this thing I keep typing with main, int main(void), int main(void).
请记住，我一直在用main键入的东西，int main(void)，int main(void)。
That's just the "when green flag clicked" equivalent for today.
这只是今天“当绿色旗帜被点击时”的等效代码。
But if you want to create your own puzzle piece or your own function in C,
但如果你想在C语言中创建你自己的积木或函数
you, for now, literally do this.
你现在要做的就是。
You say, void, the name of the function you want to create, and then
你要说，void，你想创建的函数的名称，然后
void in parentheses.
括号里的void。
And technically what this means is that this function has no return value.
从技术上讲，这意味着这个函数没有返回值。
It doesn't hand you anything back like get_string or get_int.
它不会像get_string或get_int那样返回任何东西。
And the "void" in parentheses means it takes no inputs.
括号里的“void”意味着它不接受任何输入。
It only meows.
它只会喵喵叫。
You don't have to tell it how to meow.
你不必告诉它如何喵喵叫。
It's just going to meow.
它只会喵喵叫。
So no arguments, so to speak.
所以，可以说，没有参数。
This literally just prints out "meow."
它只是打印出“喵”。
But what this does for me is it abstracts away the idea of meowing.
但对我来说，这抽象了喵喵叫的概念。
I don't need to know how to use printf or that you're
我不需要知道如何使用printf，或者说你正在
using printf to make the cat meow.
使用printf让猫喵喵叫。
I now have a function in life called meow because in Scratch, recall,
我现在有一个名为“meow”的函数，因为在Scratch中，请记住，
I used it like this.
我这样使用它。
When the green flag is clicked, I could repeat three times this new custom
当绿色旗帜被点击时，我可以重复三次这个新的自定义
puzzle piece.
积木。
But in C, I could now do this.
但在C语言中，我现在可以这样做。
In my main program, I can use a for loop just like we saw a moment ago,
在我的主程序中，我可以使用一个for循环，就像我们刚才看到的那样
copy/pasted from earlier.
复制粘贴自之前。
But now I can call my own C function called meow.
但现在我可以调用我自己的C语言函数，名为“meow”。
And let me go ahead now and do this.
现在让我继续做这件事。
If I go over to my C code here, back in VS Code, let me go ahead
如果我在VS Code中转到我的C语言代码，让我继续
and delete everything inside main.
删除main里面的所有内容。
Let me go ahead and do for int i equals 0, i is less than 3, i++.
让我继续做for int i等于0，i小于3，i++。
Inside of my curly braces, let me go ahead and say "meow."
在我的花括号内，让我继续说“喵”。
But I now need this meow function to exist because if I
但我现在需要这个“meow”函数存在，因为如果我
do "make meow" again, notice error.
再次执行“make meow”，注意错误。
"Implicit declaration of function meow is invalid in C99"--
“在C99中，对函数“meow”的隐式声明是无效的”——
the 1999 version of C. What does that mean?
C语言的1999版本。这意味着什么？
Well, it doesn't know what the meow function is.
好吧，它不知道“meow”函数是什么。
And the meow function is not in CS50.h.
而“meow”函数不在CS50.h中。
It's not in stdio.h.
它不在stdio.h中。
I have to create it.
我必须创建它。
So let me type out or really copy/paste what I had on the screen a moment ago--
所以让我键入，或者更确切地说，复制粘贴我刚才屏幕上的内容——
"void meow meow"--
"void meow meow"——
[CHUCKLES] "void meow(void)" printf, quote, unquote, "meow," close quote,
[CHUCKLES]"void meow(void)" printf，引号，反引号，“喵”，闭合引号，
semicolon.
分号。
But here, too, let me scooch this down a bit
但在这里，让我把它稍微往下移一点
so you can see all the code at once.
这样你就可以一次性看到所有代码。
Let me now do make meow.
现在让我执行make meow。
And unfortunately, I still have an error.
不幸的是，我仍然有错误。
If I scroll up, still on line 7 of meow.c,
如果我向上滚动，仍然在meow.c的第7行
my compiler thinks that meow is invalid, that it does not exist.
我的编译器认为“meow”是无效的，它不存在。
This too is a common mistake.
这也是一个常见的错误。
And as simple as this code might be in spirit, where did I screw up?
虽然这段代码从精神上来说很简单，但我究竟错在哪里？
Yeah, in the middle.
是的，在中间。
STUDENT: You need to define the function like above where you use it.
学生：你需要像在使用它的地方那样定义这个函数。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I need to define the function before I use it.
大卫·马兰：是的，我需要在使用函数之前定义它。
So again, C is going to take you literally.
所以，C语言会严格按照你的意思来执行。
If you try to call meow on line 7, you better not define it on line 11.
如果你尝试在第7行调用“meow”，你最好不要在第11行定义它。
You better define it higher up.
你最好在上面定义它。
So the simplest fix is going to be just to do this.
所以，最简单的解决方法就是这样做。
Let me clear my terminal.
让我清除我的终端。
Let me highlight and just delete the meow function.
让我选中并删除“meow”函数。
And let me just paste it up here.
然后让我把它粘贴到上面。
And this will actually solve the problem.
这实际上会解决问题。
Make meow now works.
现在make meow可以工作了。
And if I do ./meow, that, too, works.
如果我执行./meow，它也工作。
But this isn't really the best solution because if your solution is constantly,
但这并不是最好的解决方案，因为如果你的解决方案总是
oh, well, just put it up there, put it up there, put it up there,
哦，好吧，把它放到那里，把它放到那里，把它放到那里
I bet we could contrive a situation where
我敢打赌，我们可以设计出一种情况
one function needs to be above the other,
一个函数需要在另一个函数之上，
but it needs to be above the other.
但它必须在另一个函数之上。
And that's just not going to work in general.
而这在一般情况下是行不通的。
And more importantly, it just pushes main lower and lower and lower
更重要的是，它只是将main向下推，向下推，向下推
in your file.
在你的文件中。
But the whole point of your main function
但你的main函数的重点是
is like, that's the entry point.
就像，它是入口点。
That is what happens when the green flag is clicked.
这就是绿色旗帜被点击时发生的事情。
And so just in terms of user conventions, it's just useful for main
因此，就用户惯例而言，将main放在文件的顶部是有用的，因为这样你就可以快速找到它。
to always be at the top of a file because then you can find it fast.
如果main在文件的顶部，你的朋友、你的助教可以快速找到它。
Your friends can, your TFs can find it quickly if it's at the top.
如果main在顶部，你的朋友、你的助教可以快速找到它。
So the other solution here would be to leave meow at the bottom
所以这里另一个解决方案是将meow放在底部
and leave main at the top.
并将main留在顶部。
But this is the only time, if I may, that copy/paste is OK.
但恕我直言，这可能是唯一一次可以复制粘贴的地方。
What I've highlighted here in line 11 is what's called the function's prototype.
我在第11行中突出显示的部分被称为函数原型。
It is enough information to give you the return type, the name of the function,
它提供了足够的信息来告诉你函数的返回类型和函数名称，
and the return value--
以及返回值——
and any arguments.
以及任何参数。
And so if you just copy/paste that one line and end it with a semicolon
所以如果你只复制粘贴那一行并在末尾加上分号
up there, that's enough of a hint to the compiler
放在上面，这已经足以提示编译器了
that, OK, it doesn't exist yet, but it will.
好的，它现在还不存在，但它会存在。
And it will look like that.
而且它会像那样。
That's the only time it's OK to copy/paste
这可能是唯一一次可以复制粘贴的地方
the very first line of a function you've written
你编写的函数的第一行
to the top of the file with a semicolon so
到文件顶部并加上分号，这样
that you can make the compiler happy.
你就可以让编译器开心了。
So if I do make meow now, still no errors. ./meow, and it now works.
所以现在如果我创建meow，仍然没有错误。 ./meow，现在它可以正常工作了。
But let me add one final feature, coming back to Scratch here.
但是让我添加一个最后的特性，回到Scratch这里。
And then it's time for a snack.
然后该吃点心了。
So here, recall, was sort of the last fancy thing we did in Scratch, where
所以在这里，回忆一下，这是我们在Scratch中做的最后一个花哨的东西，在那里
we created not only our own custom puzzle piece,
我们不仅创建了自己的自定义拼图块，
but it took an input so that we didn't need to keep using the loop ourself.
而且它接受一个输入，这样我们就不用一直自己使用循环了。
We could just let the meow function be told how many times
我们可以让meow函数告诉我们多少次
do you want the cat to meow.
你想让猫叫。
So in C, we don't have to make that many changes except this.
所以在C语言中，我们不需要进行太多更改，除了这个。
We change the prototype to take an argument inside of parentheses.
我们将原型修改为在括号内接受一个参数。
And this is the syntax for that.
这是这样做的语法。
If you want your own function in C to take one or more arguments,
如果你想让C语言中的函数接受一个或多个参数，
you give the arguments a name, n, or whatever you want to call it.
你需要给参数一个名字，n，或者你想要叫它什么都行。
But you have to tell C what the type of that input is.
但是你必须告诉C语言输入的类型是什么。
So it's an int n.
所以它是一个int类型的n。
So it knows it's a number.
所以它知道这是一个数字。
And then you can just use n in your program.
然后你就可以在程序中使用n了。
So instead of hard coding, typing manually the number 3,
所以与其硬编码，手动输入数字3，
I'm just using n here.
我在这里使用n。
So this is equivalent to what I did with Scratch, by just dragging and dropping
所以这相当于我在Scratch中所做的，通过拖放
the n variable there.
那里的n变量。
And then "meow" will get printed that many times.
然后“喵”会被打印那么多次。
If I want to then use this-- notice, this is the last version of the cat
如果我想使用它——注意，这是我们上周做的猫的最后一个版本
that we did last week-- you just say "meow" this many times.
——你只需要说“喵”那么多次。
So in C, this is where now the code gets very succinct
所以在C语言中，现在代码变得非常简洁
because all the main part of the program does is meow three times.
因为程序的主要部分就是让猫叫三次。
So this, again, is an abstraction.
所以这再次是一个抽象。
I don't need to know, care, or remember how meow is implemented.
我不用知道，关心或记住meow是如何实现的。
I just need to know what its return value, its name, and any arguments
我只需要知道它的返回值，它的名字，以及任何参数
thereto are.
而已。
So if I make this change, I think we can get the cat
所以如果我进行这个改变，我认为我们可以让猫
to meow any number of times.
叫任何次数。
Let me go back over to my C code here.
让我回到C代码这里。
Let me go back into the file and change "void" here to be int n,
让我回到文件中，将这里的“void”改为int n，
where n just means number.
其中n只表示数字。
I could use i, but n tends to be a quantity instead of a counter.
我可以使用i，但n通常是一个数量而不是一个计数器。
I then, inside of this function, am going to do a for loop--
然后，在这个函数内部，我将执行一个for循环——
for int i get 0; i less than n--
for int i等于0；i小于n——
instead of 3-- i++.
而不是3——i++。
And then inside of here, I'll paste that "meow" again.
然后在这里面，我会再粘贴那个“meow”。
I need to change my prototype to be identical, so another copy/paste,
我需要将原型改成一样的，所以再复制粘贴一次，
or just manually edit it.
或者直接手动编辑它。
But now notice what's cool about main, is
但现在注意main的妙处在于
that now I can meow maybe three times.
现在我可以让猫叫三次。
Make meow, Enter, ./meow.
创建meow，回车，./meow。
OK, or if I really want to be cool, I can change this to 30,000 times.
好的，或者如果我真的想酷炫一点，我可以把它改成30000次。
Go back here, make meow.
回到这里，创建meow。
Increase the size of my terminal window for a dramatic pre-break flourish.
为了戏剧性的断点，扩大我的终端窗口。
And there are 30-- that was a fast cat.
有30个——那是一只很快的猫。
There are 30,000 meows.
有30000个喵。
I think now let's go ahead and take-- that's a lot-- a 10-minute break.
我认为现在让我们去——太多了——休息10分钟。
We'll see you in 10.
10分钟后见。
Cookies are now served outside.
现在外面供应饼干。
All right, so we are back.
好的，我们回来了。
And I realize this has been a lot so far, right?
我意识到到目前为止已经学了很多，对吧？
So there's a lot of new syntax.
所以有很多新的语法。
There's a lot of translation of Scratch over to C.
有很多将Scratch翻译成C语言的内容。
But among the goals of having spent last week in Scratch
但是，在上周花了时间学习Scratch之后，我们的目标之一
and having spent problems at 0 in Scratch is that none of today's ideas
以及在Scratch中花了时间解决问题，就是今天讨论的这些想法
are really all that new.
其实都不是全新的。
It's just a lot of syntax that will get more comfortable and more
只是一些语法，随着时间的推移，你会越来越熟悉，越来越
in your muscle memory as time passes.
进入你的肌肉记忆中。
Up until now, though, we've focused largely on these side effects,
然而，到目前为止，我们主要关注的是这些副作用，
like things happening on the screen.
比如屏幕上发生的事情。
And that was akin to the speech bubble appearing in the world of Scratch.
这就像Scratch世界中出现的气泡。
But let's focus for just a bit-- before we then explore things
但让我们稍微关注一下——在我们探索一些东西之前
we can't do very well in code-- on return
我们无法在代码中很好地做到——关于返回
values instead in C. We've seen them already.
值，而不是在C语言中。我们已经见过它们了。
Like, get_string returns a value.
比如，get_string返回一个值。
Get_int returns a value, a string and an int respectively.
Get_int分别返回一个值，一个字符串和一个整数。
But what if we want to make our own functions that don't just
但是，如果我们想创建自己的函数，而这些函数不仅仅是
meow and visually have this side effect of meowing on the screen
叫“喵”并在视觉上产生在屏幕上叫“喵”的副作用
but actually hand us back some value?
而是真正地将一些值返回给我们呢？
Well, I bet we can do this in C, as well.
好吧，我敢打赌我们也可以在C语言中做到。
Well, let me propose that to go that route--
好吧，我建议我们沿着这条路走下去——
let me go back to VS Code here.
让我回到VS Code这里。
And let's make our very simple calculator
让我们创建一个非常简单的计算器
that just adds some numbers together.
它只把一些数字加在一起。
But the same calculator, we'll soon see, is
但是很快我们会发现，同一个计算器
going to get us into trouble if you don't understand what the computer is
如果我们不理解计算机是什么，就会陷入困境。
doing underneath the hood.
代码的内部运作。
Let me go ahead and run code of, say, calculator.c.
让我运行一下代码，比如 calculator.c。
And in here, let me go ahead and give myself
在这里，让我添加一些代码，
access to the CS50 library with CS50.h, the stdio.h library with stdio.h,
访问 CS50 库，使用 CS50.h 头文件，访问 stdio.h 库，使用 stdio.h 头文件，
int main(void), which, again, we'll just take for granted today that we have
int main(void)，再次强调，今天我们将假定我们拥有
to include atop any of these programs.
这些程序顶部的包含语句。
And let's just add two numbers together-- super simple calculator.
让我们把两个数字加起来，一个超级简单的计算器。
So it gives me a variable called x.
因此，我定义了一个名为 x 的变量。
Assign it the return value of get_int.
将 get_int 函数的返回值赋值给它。
And I'll ask the user to give us x.
然后我会让用户输入 x 的值。
Give me another variable called y.
再给我一个名为 y 的变量。
Assign it the return value of get_int again.
同样，将 get_int 函数的返回值赋值给它。
But this time, ask the user for y.
这次，让用户输入 y 的值。
And then, lastly, let's just go ahead and print out the value of x plus y.
最后，让我们打印出 x 加 y 的值。
But I don't think I can get away with something
但是我认为我不能直接使用
like this, x plus y semicolon, because if I
这样的代码，x 加 y 加分号，因为如果我
do this, based on what we've seen before,
这么做，基于我们之前所学，
what's actually going to get printed out?
实际打印出来的是什么？
STUDENT: x plus y.
学生：x 加 y。
DAVID MALAN: Right, literally like x plus y.
大卫·马兰：没错，就是 x 加 y。
So I think this is where I need the F in "printf" for formatting.
所以我认为这里需要用到 printf 中的 F，用于格式化。
What I think I really want to do is print out the value of some placeholder
我认为我真正想要做的是打印出一个占位符的值，
because, what do I want to substitute for percent i
因为，我想用什么来替换百分号 i
maybe as a second argument to printf intuitively?
可能作为 printf 的第二个参数？
Maybe just x plus y.
也许就是 x 加 y。
So indeed, I can get away with this because it turns out in C,
因此，我可以用这种方式，因为在 C 语言中，
there's a bunch of arithmetic operators, all of the ones that you might expect,
有很多算术运算符，包括你可能想到的所有运算符，
including addition, subtraction, multiplication, division,
包括加法、减法、乘法、除法，
and even this one, the so-called modulo operator,
甚至还有这个，所谓的模运算符，
which generally gives us the ability to calculate a remainder when
它通常可以用来计算除法运算的余数，
you divide one number by another.
你用一个数字除以另一个数字时。
But I'll keep it simple with addition.
但我将只使用简单的加法。
And indeed, with printf, if I want to print out the value of x plus y,
事实上，使用 printf，如果我想打印出 x 加 y 的值，
I can do that.
我可以做到。
But I have to tell printf what kind of value to expect, an integer,
但我必须告诉 printf 它应该期待什么样的值，一个整数，
thus the percent i instead of %s for string.
因此使用百分号 i 而不是百分号 s 用于字符串。
And I think this should do the job.
我认为这应该可以实现。
So let me go back to my terminal.
现在让我回到终端。
Make calculator, Enter.
输入 make calculator 并回车。
All is well so far. ./calculator, and let's keep it simple--
目前一切正常，输入 ./calculator，让我们保持简单，
1 for x, 2 for y.
x 输入 1，y 输入 2。
And indeed, I get 3 as the output.
结果确实是 3。
It's not very dynamic.
它不太灵活。
It can't do a subtraction or multiplication or much more.
它不能进行减法、乘法或更复杂的运算。
But it does at least do those kinds of calculations.
但至少它可以进行这些计算。
But let me propose now that we maybe make a reusable addition
但现在我建议我们创建一个可重复使用的加法
function, right, because addition is something I'm going to do a lot.
函数，对吧，因为加法是我要经常使用的运算。
And maybe it should be abstracted away with a function
也许应该使用一个函数来抽象它
just like meowing was abstracted away a moment ago.
就像刚才我们抽象了喵叫声一样。
So let me go ahead and instead of doing this,
所以让我们尝试一下，而不是像这样写，
let me go ahead and give myself a function called add,
让我们定义一个名为 add 的函数，
but instead of last time where I had a meow function,
但这次不像之前我们定义的 meow 函数，
I'm obviously going to call this "add" instead.
我显然要把它命名为 “add”。
And instead of last time, taking in no arguments,
而且和之前不同，它不需要接受任何参数，
I think I want add to work a little differently.
我认为 add 函数应该以不同的方式工作。
I don't want add necessarily to take an argument yet,
我暂时不想让 add 函数接收参数，
but I do want add to return some type of value.
但我想让 add 函数返回某种类型的值。
And just intuitively, what type of value should an addition function return?
直观地来说，加法函数应该返回什么类型的值？
STUDENT: An integer.
学生：整数。
DAVID MALAN: An integer, so an int.
大卫·马兰：整数，所以是 int。
So I'm going to change void, which means the absence of a return value--
所以我要将 void 改为 int，void 表示没有返回值，
nothing's coming back-- to literally "int."
什么都没有返回。
But I'm not going to change the thing inside parentheses yet.
但我暂时不会改变括号里的内容。
I'm going to go ahead and copy my prototype up here.
我将复制这个函数原型到上面。
And I'm going to make this change, return x plus y.
然后，我将做这样的修改，返回 x 加 y 的值。
And then here, instead of printing out x plus y, let's go ahead and do this.
然后这里，我们不再打印 x 加 y 的值，而是这样写。
Let me give myself a third variable just for now.
现在让我先定义一个第三个变量。
z equals the return value of this brand-new
z 等于这个新定义的
add function that's going to add x plus y for me.
add 函数的返回值，它将为我计算 x 加 y 的值。
And then let me print out the value of z.
然后我打印 z 的值。
Instead of x plus y, I'm outsourcing now to this add function
现在，我不再使用 x 加 y，而是将计算工作外包给了 add 函数，
so it will do the addition of x plus y.
它将计算 x 加 y 的值。
So similar in spirit to meowing, but the return values, I claim,
所以，它和喵叫声函数很像，但是返回值，我猜，
are about to create an issue.
将要引发一个问题。
So let me make calculator again.
所以，让我重新编译 calculator。
And there's definitely some errors.
显然出现了一些错误。
So here we have, "use of undeclared identifier x."
这里有错误提示，"未声明的标识符 x"。
And that's on line 17.
错误发生在第 17 行。
So that's pretty far down in the file.
所以是在文件比较后面的地方。
So specifically, my compiler does not like my use of x on line 17.
具体来说，我的编译器不接受我在第 17 行使用 x。
But wait a minute, x is clearly defined on line 8.
等等，x 明明在第 8 行被定义了。
What intuitively might explain this issue
直观地来说，是什么导致了这个问题
even if you've never programmed before?
即使你之前没有编程经验？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: Well, because x and y are defined in the main function, not
学生：嗯，因为 x 和 y 是在 main 函数中定义的，而不是
the add function.
在 add 函数中。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, because x and y are defined in the main function,
大卫·马兰：没错，因为 x 和 y 是在 main 函数中定义的，
not in the add function.
而不是在 add 函数中。
So the term of art here that we're about to introduce
所以，我们即将引入一个专业术语
is something called "scope."
叫做 "作用域"。
So "scope" just refers to the context in which variables exist--
作用域指的是变量存在的上下文，
the context in which variables exist.
变量存在的上下文。
So by that, I mean this.
也就是说，
On line 8, I've declared x.
在第 8 行，我声明了 x。
On line y, I've declared--
在 y 行，我声明了，
[CHUCKLES] on line 9, I've declared y.
哈哈，在第 9 行，我声明了 y。
But the catch is-- and here's where the curly braces are helpful--
但是，关键在于，也是大括号发挥作用的地方，
those variables only exist in the context of the outer curly braces
这些变量只存在于最外层的括号中
that are nearest to them, like this.
最靠近它们的那一对，就像这样。
So I can use x and y on lines 10, 11, 12, and even up to 13,
所以，我可以在第 10 行、11 行、12 行，甚至一直到第 13 行使用 x 和 y。
but not thereafter.
但不能再往后用了。
So I certainly can't use x down here on line 7.
所以我当然不能在第 7 行使用 x。
But this is a problem, because if add's purpose in life is to add x and y
但这是一个问题，因为如果 add 的作用是将 x 和 y 相加
but add can't access x plus y, well, we have an issue of scope.
但 add 无法访问 x 加 y，那么，我们就遇到了一个范围问题。
Like, x and y are not in scope for this add function.
比如，x 和 y 在这个 add 函数的范围内不可用。
But that's OK because remember that every function we've seen thus far
但这没关系，因为请记住，到目前为止，我们看到的每个函数
can have maybe a return value or a side effect,
可能有一个返回值或副作用。
but it can also take 0 or one or two or more inputs, known as arguments.
但它也可以接受 0 个、1 个、2 个或多个输入，称为参数。
So what if I instead do this?
那我试试这个怎么样？
Let me clear my terminal window.
让我清理一下终端窗口。
And let me update add to not take nothing
让我更新 add，让它不接受任何
as input but maybe two integers.
作为输入，而可能接受两个整数。
And I'll call them arbitrarily a and b.
我将它们随意命名为 a 和 b。
But I have to tell the compiler what type of arguments
但我必须告诉编译器参数的类型
they are-- two integers, one after the other.
是两个整数，一个接一个。
And now what I can do is this.
现在我可以这样做。
Let me change this up here, too-- int a, int b--
让我在这里也改变一下，int a，int b。
just so that the prototype is exactly the same.
这样原型就完全一样了。
And the only purpose of this prototype is just to avoid the previous error,
而这个原型的唯一作用就是避免之前的错误。
where the compiler didn't realize add was going to exist
因为编译器之前没有意识到 add 会存在
because it came later in the file.
因为它出现在文件中的后面。
So here on line 11 now, if I want to add two values, x and y,
所以现在在第 11 行，如果我想把两个值 x 和 y 相加，
this is now the syntax.
这就是语法。
We saw syntax in Scratch for passing in inputs
我们在 Scratch 中看到了传递输入的语法
to tell it how many times to meow.
告诉它要叫多少次。
So this is just telling add what two numbers to add together.
所以这只是告诉 add 要将哪两个数字加在一起。
So now I have to change this to a plus b, for reasons we'll soon see.
所以现在我必须将它改为 a 加 b，原因我们很快就会看到。
And let me see if this is right.
让我看看是不是这样。
Make calculator.
生成计算器。
So far so good. ./calculator.
目前为止看起来不错。./calculator。
Let's do 1 and 2 for x and y respectively.
我们分别将 x 和 y 设置为 1 和 2。
And hopefully we should, again, see 3.
希望我们仍然能看到 3。
Now, what's going on?
现在，发生了什么？
So here, again, if I zoom in on my add function, this "int" here on the left,
所以这里，如果我放大 add 函数，左侧的这个 "int"
on line 15, means what about add?
在第 15 行，关于 add 是什么意思？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: This means that it has a return value, that it's an int.
大卫·马兰：这意味着它有一个返回值，它是一个整数。
So it's going to hand me back, metaphorically, a slip of paper
所以，它将象征性地交还给我一张纸条
with an answer on it that is of type integer.
上面写着答案，答案类型是整数。
It's not a word, like my name.
它不是一个词，比如我的名字。
It's a number instead.
而是一个数字。
These mentions of int here and here are inside the parentheses, which means
这里和这里提到的 int 都在括号内，这意味着
this function, add, takes two inputs.
这个函数，add，接受两个输入。
The first is an int.
第一个是整数。
The second is an int.
第二个也是整数。
And just so we have something to call them, I call them a and b respectively.
为了方便称呼，我分别称它们为 a 和 b。
So what happens essentially when I call the add function now on line 11,
所以当我在第 11 行调用 add 函数时，实际上发生了什么，
I'm kind of passing in x.
我实际上是在传递 x。
I'm passing in y.
我实际上是在传递 y。
But the add function is going to think of them as a and b respectively.
但 add 函数会分别将它们理解为 a 和 b。
It could call them anything I want.
我可以随意命名它们。
I could change this to the word "first" and "second."
我可以将它们改为 "first" 和 "second"。
And then I could literally change this to "first + second."
然后我可以直接将这里改为 "first + second"。
Those are perfectly acceptable as argument or variable names.
这些作为参数或变量名都是完全可以接受的。
But who really cares?
但这有什么关系呢？
Like, a and b for such a simple function is perfectly reasonable, too.
比如，对于这样一个简单的函数来说，a 和 b 也完全合理。
Technically, if your mind is going there,
从技术上来说，如果你想这样，
I could even call them the exact same thing.
我甚至可以给它们起一样的名字。
But let me propose for today, certainly don't do that because it just
但让我建议一下，今天就不要这样做，因为这样做会
confuses things if you've got x's and y's here, x's and y's here,
让人困惑，因为这里有 x 和 y，这里也有 x 和 y，
but they're clearly different.
但它们显然是不同的。
Just don't do that.
就不要这样做。
Try to come up with different variables just to keep yourself sane.
尽量想出不同的变量名称，这样才能保持清醒。
But here, I have a function that takes now two integers, a and b respectively.
但是这里，我有一个函数，它现在接受两个整数，分别为 a 和 b。
It just returns the sum of them so that I can now store the return
它只是返回它们的和，这样我就可以将返回值
value of add in a variable called z.
存储在一个名为 z 的变量中。
And then, quite simply, print it out.
然后，简单地将它打印出来。
But there's one other thing I can do here.
但我还可以做另外一件事。
Now, if we think about design, even if you've never programmed before,
现在，如果我们考虑设计，即使你以前从未编程过，
do I really need the variable z?
我真的需要变量 z 吗？
Because I'm defining it on line 11, and then I'm quickly using it on line 12,
因为我在第 11 行定义了它，然后我在第 12 行很快地使用了它，
and that's it?
就这样？
Like, sometimes you don't need variables.
比如，有时候你不需要变量。
And they might make your code more readable.
它们可能会让你的代码更易读。
But strictly speaking-- and this is just kind of like substitution in math--
但严格来说，这就像数学中的代入。
if z is the same thing as "add (x, y)," well, let me go ahead
如果 z 等于 "add (x, y)"，那么，让我继续
and just delete line 11 altogether.
直接删除第 11 行。
Let me get rid of mention of z.
让我删除 z。
You can actually get away with doing this.
你实际上可以这样做。
And much like the Join block in Scratch, where I kind of overlaid it
就像 Scratch 中的 Join 块一样，我把它叠加在
on the Say block, kind of stacking them, you can stack functions in C,
Say 块上，将它们叠起来，你可以在 C 中将函数叠起来。
or nest them really, kind of mathematically.
或者将它们嵌套起来，就像数学中那样。
Honestly, it makes it a little harder to read
说实话，这会让它稍微难以阅读一些
because your mind has to dive in conceptually deeper and deeper
因为你的思维必须在概念上不断深入
into this second argument.
到这个第二个参数。
But it's perfectly acceptable, too.
但这同样完全可以接受。
And just to connect the dots to maybe something from high school,
为了将这些点与高中的一些东西联系起来，
this is kind of analogous to a function in math class
这类似于数学课上的函数
being like f of x, where f is some function name,
就像 f(x)，其中 f 是一个函数名，
x is some arbitrary input to that function.
x 是该函数的任意输入。
And when you start to put functions inside of functions
当你开始将函数嵌套在函数中
so that the output of one becomes the input to the next,
使得一个函数的输出成为另一个函数的输入，
it's like using this syntax, f of g of x and so forth.
就像使用这种语法，f(g(x)) 等等。
If you've never seen that before, don't worry.
如果你以前从未见过，别担心。
But if you have, it's a way to connect some of these dots.
但如果你有，它是一种连接这些点的方法。
Any questions, though, on just this idea of now
不过，关于现在这个概念还有任何问题吗？
having a function that doesn't just have a side effect
有一个函数，它不仅仅有一个副作用
but instead has a return value?
而是有一个返回值？
Yeah, in back?
是的，后面那位同学？
STUDENT: In our declaration of main, why did we
学生：在我们的 main 函数声明中，为什么我们
show it as returning an integer instead of void?
把它显示为返回一个整数而不是 void？
DAVID MALAN: In our definition of main, why did I do, what?
大卫·马兰：在我们的 main 函数定义中，我做了什么？
STUDENT: Why do we show it as returning an integer
学生：为什么我们把它显示为返回一个整数
instead of returning as void?
而不是返回 void？
DAVID MALAN: Oh, a really good question that I was trying
大卫·马兰：哦，这是一个很好的问题，我今天正试图
to sweep under the rug for today.
把它掩盖起来。
But in every one of our programs thus far,
但在我们迄今为止的所有程序中，
I have indeed said "int main(void)."
我确实说过了“int main(void)”。
Technically speaking, whenever you write a program and it finishes running,
从技术上讲，每当你编写一个程序并运行完毕时，
it actually returns a value somewhat secretly.
它实际上会秘密地返回一个值。
It returns the number 0 by convention, which means all is well.
根据惯例，它返回数字 0，这意味着一切正常。
And it can return any other integer if something goes wrong.
如果出现问题，它可以返回任何其他整数。
In fact, on your Mac, PC, or even phone, if you've ever
事实上，在你的 Mac、PC 甚至手机上，如果你曾经
gotten like a weird message on the screen, like something went wrong
收到过屏幕上奇怪的消息，比如出现了错误
and it's like a weird numeric code, like error negative 129, or something
并且它像一个奇怪的数字代码，比如错误 -129，或者类似的东西
arbitrary like that, that tends to mean that some program running
像这样随意，这往往意味着你的 Mac、PC 或者手机上正在运行的某个程序
on your Mac, PC, or phone had something go wrong with the main function.
出现了 main 函数错误。
And that is the number that was returned.
那就是返回的数字。
But that's more than we want to talk about today.
但我们今天不想谈论太多。
But we'll come back to this.
但我们以后会再谈到这个。
But main always returns a number.
但 main 函数总是返回一个数字。
By default, it is 0.
默认情况下，它是 0。
More on that soon.
很快就会详细讲解。
All right, so with that said, let's actually tease
好了，现在让我们深入了解一下
apart what it is we've been using underneath the hood
我们一直在使用的一些幕后内容
here a little bit by returning to VS Code's interface itself.
通过回到 VS Code 的界面本身。
It turns out that all this time, even though I
事实证明，一直以来，尽管我
keep alluding to macOS and Windows, which like 99% of us
一直在暗示 macOS 和 Windows，就像我们 99% 的人
are probably running on our laptops or desktops,
可能都运行在我们的笔记本电脑或台式机上，
there's actually other very popular operating systems in the world,
实际上，世界上还有其他非常流行的操作系统，
among which is Linux.
其中之一就是 Linux。
So Linux is a very popular operating system,
所以 Linux 是一个非常流行的操作系统，
the thing that turns on-- the thing that boots up
是打开东西的东西——在你第一次开机时启动的东西。
when you first turn on a computer.
当你第一次开机时。
And it's very commonly used for servers nowadays.
现在，它非常普遍地用于服务器。
All of CS50's own servers run some version of Linux.
CS50 的所有服务器都运行着某个版本的 Linux。
Those students more comfortable sometimes
那些有时更习惯用 Linux 的学生
run Linux on their own Macs or PCs even.
甚至会在自己的 Mac 或 PC 上运行 Linux。
So Linux is a very popular operating system.
所以 Linux 是一个非常流行的操作系统。
And it's particularly characterized by its textual interface,
它的特点是文本界面，
its command-line interface, even though it also comes with graphical ones,
它的命令行界面，即使它也带有一个图形界面，
as well.
也是。
So again, this term we started today with, a graphical user interface
所以再次强调，我们今天开始讨论的术语，图形用户界面
is a thing with menus and buttons.
是指带有菜单和按钮的东西。
It's literally what you and I use every day on our devices,
它就是我们每天在设备上使用的，
otherwise known as a GUI.
也被称为 GUI。
But today onward, you'll get more comfortable
但从今天开始，你会对
with and more practice with this terminal window
这个终端窗口越来越熟悉，并且练习得越来越多
down here, which represents a command-line interface, or CLI.
这里，它代表的是命令行界面，即 CLI。
And just so you have a mental model of what's going on in the cloud here,
为了让你对这里云端发生的事情有一个心理模型，
when you access cs50.dev, you are accessing this version of VS Code
当你访问 cs50.dev 时，你正在访问这个版本的 VS Code
in the cloud, a piece of software just running in a browser.
在云端，这是一个在浏览器中运行的软件。
But that piece of software is automatically
但该软件会自动地
connected to your very own personal server in the cloud, so to speak.
连接到你自己的云服务器，可以这么说。
Technically speaking, it's a "docker container."
从技术上讲，它是一个“docker 容器”。
But it means that you have essentially your own mini server in the cloud
但这意味着你本质上拥有自己的云端迷你服务器
that only you have access to.
只有你才能访问它。
And that server or container is running an operating system called Linux.
该服务器或容器运行的操作系统叫做 Linux。
And in fact, every time I've been running a command down here,
事实上，每次我在下面运行命令时，
whether it's code or make or ./hello or anything else,
无论是 code 还是 make 还是 ./hello 或者其他任何东西，
I've been running commands from here in Sanders Theatre on a server somewhere
我都在桑德斯剧院的某台服务器上运行命令
in the cloud, my own Linux container or server.
在云端，我的 Linux 容器或服务器。
And you'll have the same yourself.
你也会拥有自己的。
This is the thing that we have pre-configured
这是我们预先配置好的
for you by installing the compiler in so many other pieces of software
为你们安装了编译器，以及其他许多软件
you'll soon see in the class.
你们很快就会在课程中看到。
But underneath the hood, then, of Linux is a soon-to-be familiar environment
但是，在 Linux 的幕后，有一个很快就会熟悉的环境
that allows you to run different types of commands.
它允许你运行不同类型的命令。
And those commands include things like this.
这些命令包括这些东西。
And this is something you'll develop muscle memory for over time.
随着时间的推移，你将会对它形成肌肉记忆。
But I wanted to give you a sense of some of the most popular textual commands
但我希望你们对一些最流行的文本命令有所了解
because we're essentially about to take away
因为我们基本上要拿走
muscle memory you have from a GUI world and have you type out words that
你们在 GUI 世界中形成的肌肉记忆，让你们打出代表着
represent double-clicking on things, dragging on other things,
双击某些东西、拖动其他东西的单词，
and other such commands that you and I take for granted.
以及其他我们习以为常的命令。
It'll be a little painful at first in the first days or weeks,
最初的几天或几周内会有点痛苦，
but it will make you far more productive long term so that even after CS50,
但从长远来看，这会让你效率更高，即使在 CS50 之后，
if you start using your programming skills in some other domain, class,
如果你开始在其他领域、课程中使用你的编程技能，
or real-world job, you'll just be a lot faster at the keyboard
或者现实工作中，你就会在键盘上快很多
and able to do more work more quickly.
而且能够更快地完成更多工作。
So with that said, let me go back to VS Code over here.
所以，现在让我们回到这里的 VS Code。
I'm going to go ahead and open up my File Explorer over here.
我要打开这里的文件资源管理器。
And you'll see at left all of the files that I've
你会在左边看到所有我已经有的文件
created thus far in class and all of the programs
目前在课堂上创建的所有程序
that I've compiled thus far in class.
以及我在课堂上编译的所有程序。
I also have this source 1 directory, which
我还有这个 source 1 目录，它
you can download from the course's website, which has all of today's code
可以从课程网站下载，其中包含今天的所有代码
pre-written in advance, so you don't have to type everything
事先编写好了，所以你不必输入所有内容
that I literally type.
我逐字输入的内容。
But all of these files are things that I've created.
但所有这些文件都是我创建的。
And you'll see that in white are the C files.
你会看到用白色显示的是 C 文件。
And grayed out are actually the binary files, the machine code
用灰色显示的是二进制文件，也就是机器码
that I created that I was running.
我创建并运行的机器码。
So you can click on any of these files in VS Code to open them.
因此，你可以在 VS Code 中点击任何这些文件来打开它们。
For instance, here is hello.c.
例如，这里就是 hello.c。
And voila, it opens in the text editor.
瞧，它在文本编辑器中打开了。
But if I try to open "hello," that's not going to work,
但如果我尝试打开“hello”，那就不行，
because that's zeros and ones.
因为那都是 0 和 1。
And frankly, the computer could show me all those zeros and ones,
坦白说，计算机可以向我展示所有这些 0 和 1，
but it's just not going to be useful.
但它并没有什么用。
And honestly, it's too easy to make one mistake and break the whole thing.
老实说，犯一个错误就很容易破坏整个程序。
So instead, VS Code says that it can't display the text, because it's binary
所以，VS Code 会提示它无法显示文本，因为它是二进制的
or maybe unsupported more generally.
或者更一般地说，它不受支持。
So know that you want to only click on the .c files when writing C code.
所以，记住，在编写 C 代码时，你只需要点击 .c 文件。
But let me go ahead and do something else.
但让我继续做点别的事情。
Suppose that I decide that, wait a minute, we're nearing the end of class.
假设我决定，等等，我们快下课了。
And we're not done yet, but what if I want to change hello.c to goodbye.c
我们还没结束，但如果我想把 hello.c 改成 goodbye.c
or if I want to change meow.c to woof.c and turn it into a dog?
或者如果我想把 meow.c 改成 woof.c 并把它变成一只狗？
Well, let's actually do that.
好吧，我们实际操作一下。
I could go over here and right click or Control click on the file,
我可以到这边，右键点击或 Control 点击文件，
just like on a Mac or PC.
就像在 Mac 或 PC 上一样。
I can find the Rename option.
我可以找到重命名选项。
And I can do it all via the GUI.
我也可以通过图形界面来完成所有操作。
But you should get more comfortable using commands like these here.
但你应该更习惯使用像这里这样的命令。
And among the commands on this list are "mv" for move, a.k.a.
在列表中的命令中，有“mv”，代表移动，也即
rename.
重命名。
So for instance, if I want to change meow.c to be woof.c instead,
例如，如果我想把 meow.c 改成 woof.c，
I literally type "mv" space, the original file name, space,
我会直接输入“mv”，空格，原始文件名，空格，
and the new file name.
以及新文件名。
So this is very similar to what I've already
所以这与我之前
been doing with the code program or the make program.
使用 code 程序或 make 程序的操作非常相似。
I not only type the name of the command but also the thing
我不仅输入命令的名称，还输入
that I want to code or the thing that I want to make.
我想编码的东西或我想制作的东西。
In this case, I type the thing that I want to move from old to new.
在这种情况下，我输入我想从旧位置移动到新位置的东西。
Now, if I hit Enter in a moment, watch on the left-hand side,
现在，如果我过一会儿按下回车，注意左侧，
meow.c in the GUI should automatically change
GUI 中的 meow.c 应该自动改变
even though I'm doing this all via the command-line keyboard interface.
即使我是在通过命令行键盘界面进行操作。
And now it becomes woof.c.
现在它变成了 woof.c。
I mean, it's not all that exciting.
我的意思是，它并不是那么令人兴奋。
But this is just to say that they are one and the same.
但这只是说它们是一回事。
One is a GUI, one is a CLI, but it's the same exact thing.
一个是 GUI，一个是 CLI，但它们本质上是一样的。
Moreover, let me go ahead and close now the GUI
此外，让我继续关闭左侧的 GUI
at left, the so-called explorer.
即所谓的资源管理器。
And in my terminal window alone, now I'm kind of out of my element,
现在，只有我的终端窗口，我有点不知所措，
like wait a minute, what was the file I created earlier?
比如，等等，我之前创建的文件是什么？
Well, there's other commands as well.
好吧，还有其他命令。
On this list is, coincidentally, "ls," which lists
巧合的是，列表中有“ls”，它列出了
the file in your current folder.
当前文件夹中的文件。
And as you might have gleaned here, "mv" for move, "ls" for list,
你可能已经注意到，“mv”代表移动，“ls”代表列出，
CS people like to be succinct, terse, and type
CS 人员喜欢简洁、简短，并且输入
the minimal number of keystrokes.
最少的按键。
That's why these are all abbreviated commands instead of full words.
这就是为什么这些都是缩写命令，而不是完整的单词。
But if I go back to my terminal window and type "ls," voila,
但如果我回到我的终端窗口并输入“ls”，瞧，
there is exactly the same contents of my server but displayed textually.
我的服务器的内容完全相同，但以文本形式显示。
And there's some heuristics here.
这里有一些启发式方法。
In green with an asterisk is all of the programs
用绿色和星号显示的是所有
that I made with make that are executable.
用 make 创建的可执行程序。
So the asterisks just means this is executable with dot-slash.
所以星号表示它可以用点斜杠执行。
Meanwhile, the source 1 directory, which only I have because I downloaded it
同时，source 1 目录，它只有我有，因为是我事先下载的
in advance, has a slash to indicate that it's a folder instead of a file.
它用斜杠表示它是一个文件夹，而不是文件。
But all of these white files ending in .c we created together here today.
但所有这些以 .c 结尾的白色文件都是我们今天在这里一起创建的。
Now, what if I really am embarrassed by my very first program, hello.c?
现在，如果我真的很害羞，不想保留我的第一个程序 hello.c 呢？
Well, I can very destructively go and use the rm command for remove.
好吧，我可以使用 rm 命令来删除它，它非常具有破坏性。
And rm hello.c is going to prompt me, a little cryptically,
而 rm hello.c 会提示我，有点神秘，
"remove regular file 'hello.c'?"
“删除普通文件‘hello.c’吗？”
And amazingly, this rm program has code just like we wrote earlier for agree.c,
令人惊奇的是，这个 rm 程序的代码和我们之前为 agree.c 编写的代码一样，
where I can type 'y' to delete it.
我可以在其中输入 'y' 来删除它。
I can type 'n' not to delete it.
我可以输入 'n' 来不删除它。
But let's delete it.
但我们还是删除它吧。
Let's go ahead and hit y, enter.
我们按下 y，回车。
Nothing seems to happen.
似乎什么也没发生。
But in general, that's a good thing.
但总的来说，这是一件好事。
But if I type "ls" again, notice what is now missing?
但如果我再次输入“ls”，你会发现现在缺少了什么？
And in fact, the list is a little shorter.
事实上，列表短了一点。
So it's one line instead of two.
所以只有一行，而不是两行。
"hello.c" is now gone.
“hello.c”现在不见了。
Now, if you do that, there are not easy ways to get the file back.
现在，如果你这样做了，就没有简单的方法来恢复文件。
So don't do that unless you really want to.
所以，除非你真的想这样做，否则不要这样做。
But there are backups maintained of these files, as well.
但这些文件的备份也得到了维护。
Well, what else is there, too?
还有别的什么吗？
Well, there's all of these other commands.
还有所有这些其他的命令。
And you'll experience them over time.
你会随着时间的推移而体验到它们。
Like, "cp" is copy.
比如，“cp”代表复制。
"mkdir" is make directory. "rmdir" is remove directory.
“mkdir”代表创建目录。“rmdir”代表删除目录。
And for instance, let me just show you one folder.
例如，让我展示给你一个文件夹。
If I type "ls," there's that source 1 folder
如果我输入“ls”，就会显示那个 source 1 文件夹
that I claimed I downloaded in advance.
我之前声称已经提前下载了。
If you want to see what's there, you can type "cd"
如果你想看看那里有什么，你可以输入 "cd"
for change directory, source 1, enter.
用于更改目录，源代码 1，回车。
And voila, notice that your prompt has now changed.
瞧，注意你的提示现在已经改变了。
And let me clear the screen.
让我清理一下屏幕。
Just as a visual reminder of where you are, you can see before the dollar sign
仅仅作为你所在位置的视觉提醒，你可以在美元符号之前看到
now the name of the folder that you're inside of.
你现在所在的文件夹的名称。
So in Mac or Windows, you'd see obviously a graphical folder.
所以在 Mac 或 Windows 上，你会很明显地看到一个图形化的文件夹。
Here, you just see a little textual reminder of where you now are.
在这里，你只是看到一个小小的文本提醒你你现在在哪里。
And if I type "ls," you'll see that I wrote a crazy number of files
如果我输入 "ls"，你会看到我在课前写了很多文件
before class.
。
And each of these represents different versions of the files
而这些文件中的每一个都代表着不同版本的
that we've been coding here in real time that I usually
我们一直在实时编码的文件，我通常
have printouts of just to go through things in series
会有打印版，只是为了按顺序浏览这些内容
so you have copies online, as well.
所以你也可以在网上获得副本。
So in short, all of these commands, if you've never used them before,
简而言之，所有这些命令，如果你以前从未使用过，
they will soon become like muscle memory.
它们很快就会成为你的肌肉记忆。
And they do the most basic of operations.
它们执行最基本的操作。
But there will be other commands that we'll see over
但我们会看到其他命令
time that do even much more than that.
随着时间的推移，这些命令的功能会比这些更加强大。
But let's go ahead now and solve some actual problems.
但现在让我们继续解决一些实际问题。
And it's no coincidence that we keep showing or alluding
我们不断展示或影射
to Super Mario Brothers in some form, an older game
超级马里奥兄弟并不偶然，这是一种比较古老的游戏
from the Nintendo Entertainment System, that allows you ultimately
来自任天堂娱乐系统，它最终允许你
to have this two-dimensional world, where Mario moves up and down
拥有这个二维世界，马里奥在其中上下移动
and side scrolls from left to right.
并从左到右水平滚动。
But you'll see we can distill even some aspects of "Mario"
但你会发现，我们甚至可以将 “马里奥” 的某些方面
into some fairly representative programming problems.
提炼成一些相当具有代表性的编程问题。
And in fact, let me propose that we consider this screen
实际上，我建议我们考虑一下这个屏幕
from the original Super Mario Brothers.
来自最初的超级马里奥兄弟。
So there's these four blocks in the sky, each with a question mark.
所以，天空中有四个方块，每个方块上都有一个问号。
And if you click on one of these-- or if Mario jumps up
如果你点击其中一个——或者马里奥跳到
underneath each of these question marks, he
这些问号的下面，他
gets like a coin or something else that pops out.
会得到一枚硬币或其他弹出的小东西。
Let's distill this, though, into its essence and consider in C, how can
让我们把它提炼到本质，并在 C 语言中考虑，我们如何
we make, not a blue sky yet, not a green grassy hill, and so forth,
制作，目前还没有蓝色的天空，也没有绿色的草地等等，
but how can we just make four question marks in a row,
但我们如何仅仅制作四个连续的问号，
because I dare say that we do have the building blocks via which to do this.
因为我敢说，我们确实拥有制作这些的必要组件。
Well, the simplest way might be to go over here and run code of mario.c.
好吧，最简单的方法可能是移到这里，运行 mario.c 的代码。
And then in mario.c, let's include some stdio.h so we have printf.
然后在 mario.c 中，让我们包含一些 stdio.h，这样我们就可以使用 printf。
Let's do int main(void), as we keep doing.
让我们像往常一样使用 int main(void)。
And inside of main, let's keep it super simple--
在 main 函数内部，让我们保持超级简单——
1, 2, 3, 4, backslash n.
1、2、3、4、反斜杠 n。
Doesn't get much simpler than that.
没有比这更简单了。
This is not going to be the prettiest of games.
这不会是最漂亮的游戏。
But if I make Mario now, ./mario, I get my four question marks in the sky.
但如果我现在制作马里奥，./mario，我就能得到天空中四个问号。
All right, so it's not all that interesting.
好吧，所以它并没有那么有趣。
But this is clearly a candidate for what type of programming feature.
但很明显，这适合哪种编程功能？
STUDENT: Scratch.
学生：Scratch。
DAVID MALAN: Not to Scratch, though Scratch would make it more interesting.
大卫·马兰：虽然 Scratch 会让它更有趣，但不是 Scratch。
yeah?
是吧？
STUDENT: A loop.
学生：循环。
DAVID MALAN: So some kind of loop, right?
大卫·马兰：所以是某种循环，对吧？
So print the thing out iteratively instead.
所以用迭代的方式打印出来。
So let me do that.
让我来做这件事。
Instead of just printing this out all at once,
而不是一次性地打印出来，
let me go ahead and remove this and do for int i gets zero; i less than 4;
让我继续删除这个，并使用 for int i gets zero; i less than 4;
i++.
i++。
And then in here, let me go ahead and print out just one question mark
然后在这里，让我继续打印出一个问号
instead.
。
And now let's run this.
现在让我们运行它。
So "make mario" to recompile it, ./mario.
所以用 "make mario" 来重新编译它，./mario。
And does anyone not want me to hit Enter yet?
还有谁不想让我按下回车键吗？
Why?
为什么？
STUDENT: Because it's gonna print a new line.
学生：因为它要打印一个新行。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it's going to print out a new line every time.
大卫·马兰：是的，它每次都会打印一个新行。
So notice it's four question marks, but there each on its own line.
所以注意它有四个问号，但它们都在自己的行上。
All right, well, let me fix this.
好吧，让我来修正一下。
It's obviously because of the backslash n.
很明显，这是因为反斜杠 n。
So let me remove that.
所以让我删除它。
Let me rerun make mario, ./mario.
让我重新运行 make mario，./mario。
And it's better in one way but worse in another.
这样一来，它在某些方面更好，但在另一些方面更差。
So wait, but now the dollar sign is doing
所以等等，但现在美元符号正在
that thing where it's on the same line, which
在同一行上做这样的事情，这
just looks stupid if nothing else.
至少看起来很愚蠢。
So how can I fix that?
那么我该怎么解决这个问题呢？
Yeah?
是吧？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so logically, we don't have that many building blocks
大卫·马兰：是的，所以从逻辑上讲，我们今天没有那么多的组件
today.
。
It's a lot of new syntax, but it's not that many new ideas.
虽然有很多新的语法，但没有那么多新的想法。
Let's just use printf to print out literally one and only
让我们只使用 printf 来打印一个
one of these backslash n's, but outside of the loop so
反斜杠 n，但放在循环之外，这样
it happens after all four of those have been printed.
它会在打印完所有四个问号之后发生。
All right, let me do make mario again, ./mario.
好吧，让我再次使用 make mario，./mario。
And OK, now we're back in business.
好的，现在我们又恢复正常了。
So sort of silly syntactical details, but if you
所以，这只是一些愚蠢的语法细节，但是如果你
reduce the problem to its essence, it should hopefully, logically,
将问题简化到本质，它应该有希望，从逻辑上讲，
become clear over time.
随着时间的推移变得清晰。
All right, well, how about not just something like that but vertical?
好吧，那么，除了这样，还有其他方法可以实现垂直排列吗？
Well, we've done something vertical already.
好吧，我们已经做过一些垂直排列的事情。
And so I can imagine we could change the program
所以我可以想象我们可以改变这个程序
to very simply print out three bricks instead of four question marks.
简单地打印三个砖块，而不是四个问号。
But what if we consider a two-dimensional world?
但是如果我们考虑一个二维世界呢？
And later on in this game if you go underground,
在这个游戏的后期，如果你进入地下，
everything looks like this with lots of bricks.
所有东西都像这样，有很多砖块。
And let me propose, for the sake of discussion,
为了讨论起见，我建议
that this big wall here is like a 3-by-3 grid of bricks.
这个大墙就像一个 3x3 的砖块网格。
So it's not just a single brick.
所以它不仅仅是一块砖。
It's like three by three, or nine total.
它就像三乘三，一共九块。
Now things get interesting.
现在事情变得有趣了。
And let me go back to mario.c.
让我回到 mario.c。
I could take the easy road out and just say, all right, well,
我可以走捷径，直接说，好吧，
let's printf, how about 1, 2, 3, backslash n, close quote.
让我们打印，如何用 1、2、3，反斜杠 n，关闭引号。
And then, OK, let me just copy/paste.
然后，好的，让我直接复制粘贴。
And I'm using hashes instead of the actual bricks.
我用井号来代替真正的砖块。
But aesthetically, it's pretty close.
但从美学上讲，它很接近。
Let me now go ahead and "make mario" again, ./mario.
现在让我继续执行 "make mario"，./mario。
And it doesn't quite look like a square.
它看起来不像一个正方形。
But that's just because the hashes are a little taller than they are wide.
但这仅仅是因为井号比它们宽要高一点。
But it is correct, but not well designed.
但它是正确的，但设计不好。
So here, too, what would be better designed than just hardcoding, typing
所以在这里，比直接硬编码、输入要好的是
literally all of these hashes?
所有这些井号？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: We could use maybe two loops.
学生：我们可以使用两个循环。
DAVID MALAN: Interesting, two loops.
大卫·马兰：有趣，两个循环。
And why two loops instead of one?
为什么用两个循环而不是一个？
STUDENT: Oh, wait, nevermind.
学生：哦，等等，不用了。
Well, I was going to say you could do it one for vertical and one
好吧，我要说你可以用一个循环做垂直，另一个循环做
for horizontal.
水平方向。
DAVID MALAN: OK, it's the right instinct.
大卫·马兰：好的，这是正确的直觉。
So one for vertical, one for horizontal.
所以一个循环做垂直，一个循环做水平。
And even though these predate most of us,
尽管这些东西早于我们大多数人，
old-school typewriters you might know or might
老式打字机，你可能知道或可能
recall that if you feed a piece of paper into it, you can print like line,
回想起，如果你把一张纸放进去，你可以像一行一样打印，
then it scrolls, line, then it scrolls, line, then it scrolls.
然后它滚动，一行，然后它滚动，一行，然后它滚动。
This is kind of how the terminal window works, too.
这有点像终端窗口的工作方式。
You can print rows and columns, but you have
你可以打印行和列，但是你必须
to print one row at a time, one row at a time, one row at a time.
一次打印一行，一次一行，一次一行。
It's not easy, but it is possible to go backwards and go up and down.
这并不容易，但可以向后移动，上下移动。
But just going row by row by row is more typical.
但一行一行地打印更常见。
So how can I do this?
那么我该如何做呢？
Well, I could use at least one and maybe even indeed two loops.
好吧，我可以用至少一个，甚至可能两个循环。
And this is where we're just now composing different ideas
这就是我们现在将不同的想法结合起来的地方
from today and even last week.
来自今天甚至上周。
So let me go ahead and say, for int i gets 0; i less than 3--
所以让我继续说，对于 int i 等于 0；i 小于 3--
for a 3-by-3 grid--
对于一个 3x3 网格--
i++.
i++。
And now let me cheat slightly.
现在让我稍微作弊一下。
Let me print out just three of these here, and that's it.
让我只打印出这三个，仅此而已。
So I'm kind of cheating.
所以我有点作弊。
I'm printing out rows dynamically, but I'm still printing three columns all
我正在动态打印行，但仍然在一次打印中打印三列。
in one breath.
一口气。
But let's see what happens.
但让我们看看会发生什么。
Make mario, ./mario, and it does work.
执行 mario，./mario，它确实有效。
But what if you said, no, I want 4 by 4 or 5 by 5 or 6 by 6?
但是如果你说，不，我想要 4x4 或 5x5 或 6x6 呢？
Now I have to change the 3 to a 6, and I have to add another three hashes here.
现在我必须把 3 变成 6，并且必须在这里再添加三个井号。
Things get messy if we don't do this mathematically.
如果我们不按数学方法来做，事情就会变得很混乱。
So let me now do this instead.
所以现在让我这样做。
Why don't I go ahead and print out every row at a time.
为什么我不一次打印一行。
But for each row, let me use another loop to decide, like, rat-a-tat-tat,
但对于每一行，让我用另一个循环来决定，比如，嗒嗒嗒，
from left to right, how many do I want to print.
从左到右，我想打印多少个。
So to do this, I could do another for loop.
为了做到这一点，我可以再用一个 for 循环。
I could call this variable something different. j is pretty common.
我可以给这个变量取一个不同的名字。j 很常见。
We start at i, we go to j.
我们从 i 开始，到 j 结束。
If you go past k, maybe l, you're probably doing something wrong.
如果你超过了 k，可能到 l，你可能做错了。
You don't want nested, nested, nested loops, but two is OK.
你不想要嵌套、嵌套、嵌套的循环，但两个是可以的。
j equals 0; j is less than 3; j++.
j 等于 0；j 小于 3；j++。
And then here, I can print out a single one of these and no new line.
然后在这里，我可以打印出一个，并且没有新行。
I don't want to screw up like I did before.
我不想像以前那样搞砸了。
So I'll just do one.
所以我只做一次。
Let me go ahead and do make mario now, ./mario.
现在让我继续执行 make mario，./mario。
But when I hit Enter, this is not correct yet.
但我按下回车键后，这还不正确。
What's it going to look like?
它会是什么样子？
STUDENT: A single line?
学生：一行？
DAVID MALAN: A single line of nine hashes, I think,
大卫·马兰：我认为是一行九个井号，
because I never used a single backslash n.
因为我从来没有用过一个反斜杠 n。
So that looks wrong.
所以看起来不对。
So between what line number should I insert a printf of backslash n?
那么我应该在哪些行号之间插入一个反斜杠 n 的 printf？
Let me look a little farther back if I can.
让我看看更远的地方。
How about over here?
怎么样？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: 10 and 11.
学生：10 和 11。
DAVID MALAN: Between 10 and 11.
大卫·马兰：在 10 和 11 之间。
So I'm going to go in here.
所以我将在这里
I'm going to add printf, quote, unquote, "backslash n" semicolon.
添加 printf，引号，引号，"反斜杠 n" 分号。
Let me go back and recompile mario--
让我返回并重新编译 mario--
./mario.
./mario。
And crossing fingers-- voila, perfect.
并且祈祷一切顺利--好了，完美。
I printed out now a 3-by-3.
我现在打印了一个 3x3。
Now, it's correct.
现在，它是正确的。
It's not, if we want to be really nitpicky, maybe still not
如果我们要吹毛求疵，可能仍然不是
the best design.
最好的设计。
Where am I perhaps repeating myself?
我可能在哪里重复了？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I mean, it's not a huge deal.
大卫·马兰：是的，我的意思是，这不是什么大问题。
But now I have two, people would call these magic numbers.
但我现在有两个，人们会称它们为神奇数字。
"Magic" in the sense of, where did that come from?
“神奇”是指，这些数字从哪里来的？
You just randomly put it in the middle of your code.
你只是把它随机地放在代码中间。
And you also put the same thing here.
你也在这里放了同样的东西。
Now I have to make sure I don't screw up and make one change but not the other.
现在我必须确保我没有搞错，只修改了一个地方，而没有修改另一个地方。
So it turns out we can factor these out.
事实证明，我们可以把这些提取出来。
I can actually do something like this, int n equals 3.
我实际上可以做这样的事情，int n 等于 3。
And then I can just change this to n and this
然后我只需要把这个改成 n，把这个
to n, which is marginally better because now
改成 n，这样稍微好一点，因为现在
I only have to change n in one place if I want
如果我想，我只需要在一个地方修改 n。
to make this thing bigger or smaller.
使这个东西变大或变小。
It's still going to work the same.
它仍然会以相同的方式工作。
So make mario, ./mario.
所以，编译mario，./mario。
There's our 3-by-3.
这是我们的3x3。
But if I want to make a 5-by-5, let me change the n to 5, rerun make mario,
但如果我想做5x5的，让我把n改成5，重新运行make mario，
./mario.
./mario。
And now it's a bigger grid, 5-by-5.
现在它是一个更大的网格，5x5。
But this is a little fragile.
但这有点脆弱。
And it turns out there's another trick we should introduce.
事实证明，我们应该引入另一个技巧。
It turns out that C supports what are called constants,
事实证明，C语言支持所谓的常量，
whereby if you have a variable that you want to exist because it's useful
也就是说，如果你有一个变量，你想让它存在因为它很有用
but you don't want to accidentally change it,
但你不想意外地改变它，
or if you're working with a partner in class or a colleague at work,
或者如果你在课堂上与搭档合作或在工作中与同事合作，
you don't want your partner or colleague to accidentally change
你不想你的搭档或同事意外地改变
that value with their own code, you can go into your code and tell C,
那个值使用他们自己的代码，你可以在代码中告诉C，
this is actually a constant integer, a const, so to speak.
这实际上是一个常量整数，一个const，可以这样说。
And this will just prevent you or someone else
这将阻止你或其他人
from doing something stupid by accidentally changing it elsewhere.
通过在其他地方意外地改变它来做一些愚蠢的事情。
The code is still going to work the same, ./mario,
代码仍然会以相同的方式工作，./mario，
but you won't be accidentally able to change it very easily to something
但你将无法轻易地意外地将其更改为其他内容
else.
其他。
And honestly, what we've now done, too, is set ourselves
老实说，我们现在也已经设置了自己
up to make this more dynamic.
为使之更具动态性。
Let me go up here, and let me add the CS50 library so that we have access
让我到上面来，让我添加CS50库，以便我们有权访问
to get_int because now we could do something
get_int，因为现在我们可以做一些
fancy like ask the get_int function for the size of this brick wall.
花哨的事情，比如向get_int函数询问这堵砖墙的大小。
And then we can use n dynamically.
然后我们可以动态地使用n。
So for instance, let me increase the size of my terminal, make mario,
例如，让我增加终端的大小，编译mario，
./mario, size 3.
./mario，大小为3。
Gives me a 3-by-3.
给我一个3x3的。
./mario size 5 gives me a 5-by-5.
./mario，大小为5，给我一个5x5的。
./mario, how about 50, gives me a crazy big one, but it's all dynamic.
./mario，50怎么样，给我一个超大的，但它是动态的。
And now I don't have to even change the code.
现在我甚至不需要更改代码。
It just now works.
它现在就起作用了。
As an aside, if you're wondering how I type so darn fast,
顺便说一句，如果你想知道我为什么打字这么快，
sometimes it's just because I'm hitting the up arrow.
有时只是因为我按了上箭头。
It turns out that Linux will remember, if you
事实证明，如果你配置Linux，它会记住
configure it this way, all of your previous commands.
以这种方式，你之前的所有命令。
So if you hit up, up, up, I can go through the past couple of hours
所以如果你向上，向上，向上，我可以浏览过去几个小时
of commands that I've typed, which is useful sometimes--
我键入的命令，有时这很有用--
not for hours of commands but the past few--
不是几个小时的命令，而是过去几个--
just to save yourself some keystrokes.
只是为了节省一些按键。
And another trick in a terminal window is to do this.
另一个在终端窗口中的技巧是这样做。
If I do ./ma and I get bored and I don't want to type out "rio,"
如果我输入./ma，我感到厌烦，不想打出“rio”，
I can also just hit Tab, and it will autocomplete based on the characters
我也可以直接按Tab键，它会根据匹配的字符自动补全
that do match.
匹配的字符。
So those kinds of tricks, too, will save you time over time.
所以这些技巧也会随着时间的推移为你节省时间。
But let's do this.
但让我们这样做。
It's kind of broken, arguably, if I do this.
可以说，如果我这样做，它有点坏了。
How about "cat?"
“cat”怎么样？
All right, well, that works.
好吧，这有效。
That prevents me from doing something stupid
这阻止我做一些愚蠢的事情
because get_int only accepts integers.
因为get_int只接受整数。
But it will accept 0, which does nothing.
但它会接受0，这什么也不做。
It will accept negative 1, which does nothing.
它会接受负1，这什么也不做。
And that's not bad.
这还不错。
It's not doing something weird.
它没有做奇怪的事情。
But it would be nice to catch that and force the user
但最好能捕捉到这一点，并强制用户
to give us a positive integer instead so we at least
给我们一个正整数，这样我们至少
see something on the screen.
在屏幕上看到一些东西。
So let me go back into my code, and let me propose that now
所以让我回到我的代码，现在我建议
that we have the CS50 library, why don't we do something like this?
我们有了CS50库，为什么我们不这样做呢？
I'm going to change this.
我要改变这个。
I'm going to get rid of the constant just in case
我要去掉这个常量，以防万一
the user needs to type it again.
用户需要重新输入它。
And what if I do this?
如果我这样做呢？
While n is less than 1--
当n小于1时--
so if it's 0, negative 1, negative 2, or whatever, let's go ahead
所以，如果它为0，负1，负2，或者其他任何值，让我们继续
and again ask the user for an int, and ask them for the size again.
再次询问用户一个整数，并再次询问他们大小。
And therefore, only once n is not less than 1 will
因此，只有当n不小于1时，
this loop break out and will proceed with the rest of the code.
这个循环才会退出，并继续执行代码的其余部分。
So now let me try this.
所以现在让我试试这个。
Make mario, ./mario 0--
编译mario，./mario 0 --
didn't like that.
不喜欢那个。
Negative 1-- didn't like that.
负1 -- 不喜欢那个。
Negative 2-- didn't like that.
负2 -- 不喜欢那个。
3-- it did like that.
3 -- 它喜欢那个。
So using a loop now, I can ensure that the human is providing me
所以现在使用循环，我可以确保人类正在为我提供
with input that I actually want.
我真正想要的输入。
So this is correct.
所以这是正确的。
But I dare say 6 through 10 could be done better.
但我想说6到10可以做得更好。
Why is this poorly designed instinctively?
为什么这在本能上设计得不好？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: There's repetition.
学生：有重复。
DAVID MALAN: What's the repetition, to be clear, what lines?
大卫·马兰：重复的是什么，说清楚点，是哪几行？
STUDENT: Lines 6 and 9.
学生：第6行和第9行。
DAVID MALAN: 6 and 9.
大卫·马兰：第6行和第9行。
OK, so they're literally the same, and that's generally not a good thing.
好的，所以它们实际上是一样的，这通常不是一件好事。
And maybe I could change this one to remind the user like, hey,
也许我可以改变这一行，提醒用户，嘿，
that's not a positive number.
这不是一个正数。
So you might want to customize the message.
所以你可能想自定义消息。
But just having copy/paste here for the most part is not a good thing.
但仅仅在这里进行复制粘贴，在大多数情况下不是一件好事。
So it turns out-- and there's just one feature of C we wanted to introduce you
所以事实证明 -- 而且C语言只有一个特性我们想让你了解
to today-- it turns out there's one other way that would actually help us
今天 -- 事实证明，还有另一种方法实际上可以帮助我们
eliminate this redundancy of using get_int twice and particularly asking
消除使用get_int两次的冗余，特别是询问
literally the same question-- size--
同一个问题 -- 大小 --
twice in duplicate.
两次重复。
So I'm actually going to go into my code here,
所以我要进入我的代码，
and I'm going to delete the loop as we've written it thus far.
我要删除我们迄今为止编写的循环。
And instead of using a while loop, I'm going
而不是使用 while 循环，我将
to introduce instead something that we typically
介绍我们通常所说的
call a do while loop, which is a little bit different.
do while 循环，它有一点不同。
Indeed, we begin with the keyword "do," and then
实际上，我们从关键字“do”开始，然后
inside of the curly braces, what I'm going to do here
在大括号内，我要在这里做的事情是
is that thing I might want to do once and more times thereafter.
我可能想做一次，然后多次重复的事情。
So for instance, I'm going to say n equals get_int quote, unquote, "size."
例如，我要说 n 等于 get_int，引号，引号，“size”。
And then at the bottom of this block of code, then
然后在这段代码的底部，
I'm going to use the keyword "while," as well as parentheses as always
我要使用关键字“while”，以及像往常一样使用括号
for a Boolean expression.
用于布尔表达式。
And here.
在这里。
I'm going to ask the question, do this while n is less than 1.
我要问这个问题，当 n 小于 1 时执行此操作。
But there's one fix I still need to do here because notice on the current line
但是这里还有一处需要修正，因为注意当前行
8, I actually haven't given n a type.
8，实际上我还没有给 n 指定类型。
I haven't declared n yet.
我还没有声明 n。
But it would not be correct to declare n here, inside of that do block.
但是在这里，在那个 do 代码块内声明 n 是不正确的。
But why might that be?
但这为什么呢？
Why would it not be a good thing to declare n inside of these curly braces?
为什么在这些大括号内声明 n 不是一件好事？
Yeah, so recall that this is an issue of scope.
是的，所以请记住，这是一个范围问题。
Recall that the scope of a variable is generally
请记住，变量的范围通常
confined to the most recently opened curly braces in which that variable is
局限于最最近打开的大括号，该变量在其中
declared.
被声明。
And so if I declare this variable on line 8,
因此，如果我在第 8 行声明此变量，
I'm not going to be able to use it on line 10.
我将无法在第 10 行使用它。
But there is a fix, even though it might look a little strange.
但是有一个解决方案，尽管它可能看起来有点奇怪。
I'm going to go above my do block here.
我将移至此处 do 代码块的上方。
And before I go into this loop, I'm actually
在进入此循环之前，我实际上
going to declare n to be an integer, but semicolon, end of thought.
要声明 n 为整数，但分号，结束思考。
I'm not going to bother giving it a value, because I
我不会费心给它一个值，因为我知道
know logically I'm going to end up giving it a value anyway now on line 9.
在逻辑上，我最终会给它一个值，现在在第 9 行。
And so what's different about this version of the code
所以，这个版本的代码与之前的版本有什么不同呢？
is that the do while loop ensures that we prompt the user for input at least
就是 do while 循环确保我们至少提示用户输入一次。
once.
一次。
And then while that input is not what we expect, for instance less than 1, then
然后，只要该输入不是我们预期的，例如小于 1，那么
it's going to execute again, again, again.
它将再次执行，再次执行，再次执行。
And indeed, the semantics are just that.
实际上，语义就是如此。
Do the following while this Boolean expression is true.
在该布尔表达式为真时，执行以下操作。
So if I go ahead now and rerun make mario, compiles OK-- ./mario.
因此，如果我现在继续重新运行 make mario，编译正常 - ./mario。
And now I'll go ahead and input something that's not correct, like 0.
现在，我将输入一些不正确的内容，比如 0。
But I'm prompted again.
但我被再次提示。
I'll input something like negative 1, and I'm prompted again.
我将输入类似负 1 的内容，然后我被再次提示。
But if I go ahead and input, for instance, 10,
但是如果我继续输入，例如 10，
now, because that's a positive integer, I indeed get a 10-by-10 grid of bricks.
现在，因为这是一个正整数，我确实得到了一个 10x10 的砖块网格。
And there's one other thing we should introduce here, too, in C, too.
在 C 中，我们还应该介绍另一件事。
C supports comments.
C 支持注释。
And a couple of you have asked about this
你们中的一些人已经问过这个问题了
if you come from other programming languages.
如果你来自其他编程语言。
Suppose I want to remember what it is I just did with this program.
假设我想记住我刚刚用这个程序做了什么。
Let me go in between lines 5 and 6 here and do "// prompt user for positive
让我在第 5 行和第 6 行之间做 "// 提示用户输入正
integer."
整数。"
This is what's known as a comment.
这就是所谓的注释。
And it's grayed out only in the sense that the compiler is not
它只是灰色的，因为编译器不会
going to care about this.
关心它。
The computer is not going to care about this.
计算机不会关心它。
This is a note to self, like a sticky note in the context of Scratch.
这是一个给自己看的笔记，就像 Scratch 中的便签一样。
And it starts with "//," which essentially tells the compiler ignore
它以“//”开头，本质上告诉编译器忽略
this, this is for the human, not for the computer.
它，这是给人类看的，不是给计算机看的。
But this comment, so to speak, is a way of just reminding yourself, reminding
但可以说，这个注释是一种提醒自己、提醒
your colleague, reminding your TF what it
你的同事，提醒你的助教几行代码应该做什么。
is a few lines of code are meant to do.
就是几行代码应该做什么。
And now this comment might be print, and how about n-by-n grid of bricks?
现在这个注释可能是打印，n x n 的砖块网格呢？
And what's nice about comments is that theoretically you can get away with,
注释的好处是理论上你可以逃脱，
or someone else can get away with, just reading this comment
或者其他人可以逃脱，只阅读这个注释
and then not even have to look at the rest of the code.
然后甚至不必查看其余的代码。
They can look at this comment and not have to look at the rest of the code
他们可以查看这个注释，而不必查看其余的代码
because you've described for them what it's meant to do.
因为你已经为他们描述了它应该做什么。
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: I just had a question about the hashtag [INAUDIBLE]
学生：我有一个关于井号的问题[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Sure.
大卫·马兰：当然。
STUDENT: That's for [INAUDIBLE]
学生：那是为了[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Correct, the hash sign in Python is a comment,
大卫·马兰：正确，Python 中的井号是注释，
is not the same thing in C. In C, hash include means to include the library's
在 C 中则不同。在 C 中，井号包含表示以这种方式包含库的
header files in that way.
头文件。
Other questions on these here tricks?
还有其他关于这些技巧的问题吗？
No?
没有？
All right, so as promised, what is maybe C not actually good at?
好的，正如承诺的那样，C 可能不太擅长什么？
Well, let me propose that we consider what's
嗯，让我提议我们考虑一下
actually inside of your computer.
你计算机内部到底是什么。
At the end of the day, whether it's a Mac, PC, iPhone, Android, phone,
归根结底，无论是 Mac、PC、iPhone、Android 手机，
or some other computer device, there's something that looks like this.
还是其他一些计算机设备，都有一个看起来像这样的东西。
And this is memory, otherwise known as RAM, or random access memory,
这就是内存，也称为 RAM，即随机存取存储器，
for reasons we'll get to in a few weeks.
原因我们将在几周后讲到。
But this is where data is stored.
但这里就是存储数据的地方。
This is where "hello, world" is stored.
这就是存储“hello, world”的地方。
This is where 1 and 2 and all of those numbers are stored.
这就是存储 1 和 2 以及所有这些数字的地方。
Any data in your program is stored ultimately in the computer's memory.
程序中的任何数据最终都存储在计算机的内存中。
And the most important takeaway for today is that all of us
而今天最重要的收获是，我们所有人
only have a finite amount of memory in our devices.
在我们的设备中都只有有限的内存。
You might have a high-end device which has a lot of memory,
你可能拥有一台高端设备，它拥有很多内存，
but it's still finite, which means you can only
但它仍然是有限的，这意味着你只能
count so high with that device.
用那个设备数到那么高。
You can only store so many files with that device.
你只能用那个设备存储那么多的文件。
There are fundamental physical limitations even though mathematically,
即使从数学角度来说，也存在着一些基本的物理限制，
theoretically, we should be able to count toward infinity.
理论上我们应该可以一直数到无穷大。
So what are the implications for this?
那么这对我们来说意味着什么呢？
Well, consider this.
让我们考虑一下这个。
In the world of numbers, as per week 0, if you're only using three digits--
在数字的世界里，就像上周我们讲的那样，如果你只用三个数字——
and I've grayed out the fourth one just to make the point-- if you're only
为了说明问题，我把第四个数字涂成了灰色——如果你只
using three digits, we can count from 0 to 1 in decimal, to 2, to3, to 4,
使用三个数字，我们就可以用十进制从 0 数到 1，到 2，到 3，到 4，
to 5, to 6, to 7.
到 5，到 6，到 7。
And as soon as you count to 8, you technically, per last week,
而当你数到 8 的时候，从技术角度来说，根据上周的内容，
need a fourth bit.
你需要一个第四位。
But if you don't have it, the number 7 might seem
但是如果你没有第四位，数字 7 之后看起来
to be followed by what number instead?
应该是多少呢？
STUDENT: 0.
学生：0。
DAVID MALAN: 0.
大卫·马兰：0。
The number overflows, so to speak, right?
这个数字就溢出了，可以这么说，对吧？
You carry the 1.
你进位 1。
But if there's no place to put the 1, because there's no fourth light bulb,
但是如果没有地方可以放这个 1，因为没有第四个灯泡，
if there's no fourth transistor, if there's no fourth bit,
没有第四个晶体管，没有第四位，
the lower bits, the zeros, are going to be mistaken for the number you
低位的 0 将会被误认为是你
and I know is 0.
和我都知道的 0。
So integer overflow is a thing in computers
所以，在计算机中，整数溢出是真实存在的
whereby if you don't have enough memory, if you count high enough,
如果你内存不足，如果你数到足够高的数字，
the number will wrap around back to 0.
这个数字就会回绕到 0。
Or sometimes it will wrap around to a negative number,
或者有时候它会回绕到一个负数，
depending on whether the code supports negative and positive numbers and 0
这取决于代码是否支持负数、正数和 0
alike.
这些值。
So that has some very real world implications
所以，这在现实世界中有一些非常重要的影响
in integer overflow that's sort of a fundamental limitation of how
整数溢出，这实际上是对数字存储方式的一种基本限制。
numbers are typically stored.
数字通常是如何存储的。
Now, thankfully, we typically don't store things
现在，值得庆幸的是，我们通常不会根据
based on number of digits but number of bits.
数字位数来存储数据，而是使用位数。
And a bit is just a 0 or 1.
而一个位就是一个 0 或 1。
And recall from last week that a common unit of measure
还记得上周我们讲过，一个常见的单位
is minimally eight bits, or a byte, but even more commonly is 32.
至少是八位，也就是一个字节，但更常见的是 32 位。
So for instance, here are 32 bits, all zeros.
例如，这里有 32 位，都是 0。
And if you do out the math, this is the number
如果你算一下，这个数字
you and I know in decimal is of course 0.
你和我都知道用十进制表示就是 0。
But if I change all 32 zeros to ones, this is a really big number now.
但如果我把这 32 个 0 全部变成 1，现在就是一个非常大的数字了。
If we're only using positive numbers, not negatives,
如果我们只使用正数，不使用负数，
what number roughly is this, 32 ones?
这个数字大约是多少呢，32 个 1？
It's roughly 4 billion in total-- roughly 4 billion in total.
大约是 40 亿——大约是 40 亿。
Why?
为什么？
Well, if you've got 32 bits, each can be two possible values, 0 or 1, that's
因为你有 32 位，每一位都有两种可能的值，0 或 1，那就是
2 to the 32nd power, which is roughly--
2 的 32 次方，大约是——
I'll stipulate-- roughly 4 billion total.
我承认——大约是 40 亿。
The problem is, what if you want to count to 4,000,000,001?
问题是，如果你想要数到 4,000,000,001 呢？
That's a bit of a white lie.
那有点说谎了。
It's not precisely that.
不是完全准确的。
But what if you want to count just higher than that?
但如果你想要数到比这更大的数字呢？
You'd need a 33rd bit because all of the others
你需要一个第 33 位，因为其他的所有位
are going to go to 0 at that point, and you might count from 1 to 2
此时都会变成 0，你可能会从 1 数到 2
to 3 to 4 billion back to 0, or worse if you're dealing with negative numbers,
到 3 到 40 亿再回到 0，或者更糟的是，如果你在处理负数，
too.
也是如此。
So the fact that there are finitely many bits used in computers is a problem.
所以，计算机中使用的是有限位数，这本身就是一个问题。
And negative numbers do add a complexity because this is specifically
而负数确实增加了复杂性，因为这是特指的
the 4 billion in question--
我们所谈论的 40 亿——
4,294,968,295.
4,294,968,295。
That is as high as you can count with 32 bits
这是你可以用 32 位数到的最大数字
if you don't bother with negatives.
如果你不考虑负数。
But if you want negative numbers, you've got to half
但如果你想要负数，你就必须把
that because you've got to save half of them for negative, half of them
这些位数分成两半，一半用于负数，一半用于
for positive, give or take.
正数，大致如此。
And so if you're supporting negative numbers, as you probably
所以，如果你需要支持负数，就像你可能
should for a calculator, for Microsoft Excel, Google Spreadsheets,
应该为计算器、Microsoft Excel、Google Sheets 做的那样，
you can only count as high up as 2 billion roughly,
你只能数到大约 20 亿，
or negative 2 billion roughly instead.
或者负 20 亿。
So it turns out that when you are using data types in C,
所以，当你使用 C 语言中的数据类型时，
you have some control over how many bits are actually used.
你可以控制实际使用的位数。
And this list is longer than we've covered today,
这个列表比我们今天讲的要长，
but we did talk about integers for a while.
但我们确实讨论了一段时间整数。
Those are, by convention nowadays, 32 bits.
现在，按照惯例，它们是 32 位。
If that's not enough, you can upgrade your variables to longs, which
如果不够，你可以将你的变量升级为 long 类型，这
tend to be 64 bits instead, which isn't just twice as big as an integer,
通常是 64 位，这不仅仅是整数的两倍，
it's actually 64 bits, which is exponentially more.
而是 64 位，这要大得多。
It's an unpronounceable number, at least for me.
至少对我来说，这是一个难以说出口的数字。
That's a crazy big number, but it's available to you.
这是一个非常大的数字，但你可以使用它。
Moreover, we can see this if we actually are a little reckless with how
此外，如果我们对代码的使用方式稍微不负责任一点，就能看到这一点。
we're using code.
我们使用代码的方式。
And just so you know too, though, there are
不过，你也要知道，还有
functions even in CS50's library that let
CS50 库中的函数，可以让你
you use these larger values, get long of course, will get you a long.
使用这些更大的值，当然，get long 函数可以获取一个 long 类型的值。
And this one's a little non-obvious, but "%li" is the format code for printf,
这个有点不太明显，但 "%li" 是 printf 函数的格式代码，
just so you know, for printing a long integer and not just an integer.
让你知道，用于打印长整型而不是仅仅打印整型。
So it's two characters instead of one.
所以，它有两个字符而不是一个字符。
Suppose, though, we actually want to use code involving some large numbers.
假设，我们确实想要使用一些包含较大数字的代码。
It turns out that certain bad things can happen.
结果表明，某些不好的事情可能会发生。
So let me go ahead and do this.
所以，我来做一下。
I'm going to go back over to VS Code here,
我将回到这里的 VS Code，
and I'm going to modify my calculator to do something that, at glance, should
并修改我的计算器，让它做一些看起来很合理的事情。
be perfectly reasonable.
看起来非常合理。
Let me go ahead and open up calculator.c, as before.
让我打开 calculator.c 文件，和之前一样。
And where we left off, we had this add function.
我们上次说到这里，我们有这个 add 函数。
And you know what?
你知道吗？
I'm going to simplify it back to its very original version.
我要把它简化回最初的版本。
I'm going to go ahead and get rid of the add function
我要删除 add 函数
and just distill it to its essence, which is not to add any more.
并且将其提炼到本质，即不要再添加任何东西。
But let's just do division.
但让我们只做除法。
I want to print out this time maybe x divided by y.
这一次我想打印出 x 除以 y 的结果。
So here we go. x divided by y is a nice simple program in my calculator.
所以我们开始吧。 x 除以 y 在我的计算器中是一个简单的程序。
Let me do make calculator again, ./calculator.
让我再次制作计算器，./calculator。
And let's divide something like 1 divided by 3, which should--
让我们除以类似 1 除以 3 的东西，结果应该——
hm, OK, weird.
嗯，好吧，奇怪。
It gave me 0 instead of probably 0.3333333,
它给了我 0 而不是 0.3333333，
as you might have expected for 1/3.
正如你对 1/3 所期望的那样。
So what might the takeaway there be?
所以那里有什么启示呢？
Why am I seeing zero perhaps?
为什么我看到了 0 呢？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: If 0's the integer [INAUDIBLE],, then if you want decimals [INAUDIBLE]..
学生：如果 0 是整数，那么如果你想要小数...
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so 0 is an integer.
大卫·马兰：是的，所以 0 是一个整数。
And indeed, that's what I'm telling the thing to print.
而且确实，这就是我告诉它要打印的。
And in fact, if we go over to my little cheat sheet here of format codes,
事实上，如果我们看一下我这里关于格式代码的小速查表，
I'm currently using %i.
我目前使用的是 %i。
I should actually, when I do division of numbers that might have floating point
实际上，当我进行可能包含浮点数的数字的除法时，
values, a decimal point that floats left to right,
值，一个从左到右浮动的的小数点，
otherwise known as a real number, I want to use %f for float instead.
也称为实数，我想用 %f 代替浮点数。
So I'm actually going to go back to my code here.
所以我实际上要回到我的代码这里。
And let's try this-- %f instead of %i.
让我们试试这个——%f 而不是 %i。
And let me go ahead and "make calculator."
让我继续执行“make calculator”。
Huh, all right.
嗯，好吧。
Well, this didn't work then.
好吧，这个不起作用。
"Format specifies type 'double,' but the argument has type 'int.'
“格式指定类型为“double”，但参数类型为“int”。
All right, so that, too, is not quite working.
好吧，这个也不起作用。
So I think I actually need to make a change here further.
所以我想我实际上需要在这里进一步更改。
Let me actually go ahead and do this.
让我继续做这个。
It turns out that besides integers, there
事实证明，除了整数之外，还有
are these things called floats, and also doubles.
叫做浮点数，还有双精度数。
A float uses 32 bits, and a double uses 64 bits.
一个浮点数使用 32 位，一个双精度数使用 64 位。
And that doesn't necessarily mean you can
这并不一定意味着你可以
count higher as much as it means you can have
计数更高，而是说你可以拥有
more numbers after the decimal point.
小数点后更多的数字。
So if you want a more precise value, you throw memory at it
所以如果你想要一个更精确的值，你用内存来解决
by using a double and 64 bits instead of a float.
使用一个双精度数和 64 位而不是一个浮点数。
But we'll keep it simple, and let me go ahead and do this.
但我们会保持简单，让我继续做这个。
Let me just do the math using the type of variable that I should be here.
让我使用这里应该使用的变量类型来进行计算。
Let me do not int, but float z equals x divided by y.
让我使用 float z 而不是 int，它等于 x 除以 y。
And now let me go ahead and print out the value of z.
现在让我继续打印出 z 的值。
Strictly speaking, I don't need the variable.
严格来说，我不需要这个变量。
But I'm trying to be pedantic and actually use a float explicitly
但我试图过于拘泥，并明确使用一个浮点数
this time so we see a real number.
这次，这样我们就能看到一个实数。
All right, let me go ahead and do make calculator, ./calculator.
好吧，让我继续执行 make calculator，./calculator。
1 divided by 3 equals--
1 除以 3 等于——
damn, now it's just showing me more zeros, which clearly isn't the case.
该死，现在它只显示我更多 0，这显然不是事实。
Well, this is because of an issue that we'll generally call truncation.
好吧，这是因为一个问题，我们通常称之为截断。
So truncation is just a term of art that means if you take an integer
所以截断只是一个术语，意思是如果你取一个整数
and you divide it by an integer, even if you get a fractional value,
并且你用一个整数除它，即使你得到一个分数值，
the fraction just gets thrown away because you're only
这个分数就被丢弃了，因为你只是
doing integer-based math.
在进行基于整数的数学运算。
So if there's anything after the decimal point,
所以如果小数点后有东西，
it just gets truncated, literally discarded.
它就被截断了，实际上被丢弃了。
So what should 1 divided by 3 be?
那么 1 除以 3 应该是什么呢？
Obviously, 0.33333333-- ad nauseum.
显然是 0.33333333——无限循环。
Fortunately, you throw away everything after the decimal point,
幸运的是，你丢弃了小数点后的所有东西，
which leaves you still with just 0.
这使得你仍然只有 0。
And even though I'm seeing more zeros, that's because we threw away all
即使我看到更多 0，那也是因为我们丢弃了所有
of the 3's.
3。
That is just what happens when you use integers and do
当你使用整数并进行
any kind of division like that.
任何类似的除法运算时，就会发生这种情况。
But there is a solution.
但有一个解决方法。
We can actually convert, or cast, integers to floating point values.
我们实际上可以转换或强制转换整数为浮点数。
So we can tell C, I know this is an integer now.
所以我们可以告诉 C，我知道现在这是一个整数。
But go ahead and treat it as though it has a decimal point, even
但继续把它当作有小数点，即使
if it's .0 At the end of the number.
它是数字末尾的 .0。
So I can go into this, and I can use parentheses and literally write
所以我可以在这个里面，我可以使用括号并直接写
"float" in parentheses.
括号中的“float”。
And over here for y, I can literally use parentheses and convert y to a float.
在 y 这里，我可以直接使用括号并将 y 转换为浮点数。
The term of art here is type casting.
这里的术语是类型转换。
You're converting one type to another effectively, or technically treating
你实际上将一种类型转换为另一种类型，或者在技术上将
one type as though it's another even if it doesn't necessarily
一种类型当作另一种类型，即使它不一定
have a mathematical impact.
产生数学影响。
But what it means now is that z will be defined
但现在这意味着 z 将被定义
by dividing one float by another.
为一个浮点数除以另一个浮点数。
So truncation will not now happen.
所以截断现在不会发生了。
So let me do make calculator, ./calculator.
所以让我执行 make calculator，./calculator。
And now 1 divided by 3, there it is.
现在 1 除以 3，结果出来了。
Now the math is actually correct.
现在数学计算是正确的。
But my God, we had to jump through hoops just to get this to work.
但我的天，我们不得不费尽周折才能让它工作。
So to be clear, the two issues we-- well, the issue we encountered
所以明确地说，我们遇到的两个问题——好吧，我们遇到的问题
was truncation.
是截断。
If you divide an int by an int, you will get an int no matter
如果你用一个 int 除以一个 int，无论它在数学上应该是什么，你都会得到一个 int。
what it should be mathematically.
是什么。
But if you instead type cast the values, the variables to a floating point
但如果你改为将值，变量强制转换为浮点数
value, or a double for that matter, then a float divided by a float will give
值，或者是一个双精度数，那么一个浮点数除以一个浮点数将得到
you a float and preserve all of those 3's.
一个浮点数，并保留所有 3。
But here's another catch, or at least a limitation potentially with computers.
但这里还有一个问题，或者至少是计算机可能存在的限制。
What if I go ahead here and do--
如果我在这里继续执行——
let me do this.
让我做这个。
Let me show you one trick here, even though the syntax is a bit weird.
让我在这里展示你一个技巧，即使语法有点奇怪。
Instead of printing out %f alone, let me print out % dot,
而不是单独打印 %f，让我打印 % 点，
maybe 5f So this is weird syntax.
也许是 5f。所以这是奇怪的语法。
And it's only specific to printf.
它只特定于 printf。
"%.5f" means 'show me five decimal places specifically.'
"%.5f"的意思是“准确地显示我五位小数”。
So if I do make calculator, ./calculator, 1, 3, voila,
所以如果我做计算器，./计算器，1，3，瞧，
I get five decimal places.
我得到了五位小数。
If I want six, let's do this.
如果我想要六位，让我们这样做。
I'll change the code to 6.
我将代码改为6。
Make calculator, ./calculator, 1, 3, and now I get six 3's instead.
制作计算器，./计算器，1，3，现在我得到了六个3，而不是五個。
All right, well, wouldn't it be nice to be even more precise?
好吧，如果能更精确一点，岂不是很好吗？
Let's give me 20 significant digits after the decimal point.
让我们在小数点后给出20位有效数字。
So make calculator, ./calculator, 1 divided by 3, and-- woo.
所以制作计算器，./计算器，1 除以 3，然后 - 哇。
So your middle school teacher seems to have lied to you at this point.
所以你的初中老师似乎在这个时候对你撒了谎。
1 divided by 3 is apparently not 0.33333 with a line over it,
1 除以 3 显然不是 0.33333 并在其上加一条线，
or just infinite number of 3's.
或者仅仅是无限个 3。
OK, that's not quite the right conclusion, though.
好吧，虽然这不是完全正确的结论。
Oops.
哎呀。
Why might I be seeing these weird numbers instead
为什么我可能会看到这些奇怪的数字，而不是
of just lots of 3's, intuitively?
仅仅是许多 3，直观地说？
Why this rounding error?
为什么会有这种舍入误差？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: The computer just has a [? limited ?] [? memory. ?] So
学生：计算机只有 [？有限的？] [？内存。？] 所以
there's [INAUDIBLE]
那里有 [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
大卫·马兰：没错。
The computer only has limited memory, finite memory.
计算机只有有限的内存，有限的内存。
So it just can't represent every possible number in the universe
所以它只是无法表示宇宙中所有可能的数字
because we know from grade school there are infinitely many of those numbers.
因为我们从小学就知道有无限多个这样的数字。
So what you're essentially seeing is the closest it can actually get.
所以你实际上看到的只是它能达到的最接近的数字。
It's rounding to the nearest floating point value, if you will.
如果可以的话，它将舍入到最接近的浮点值。
And it also relates to how the numbers themselves are represented
这也与数字本身在内存中的表示方式有关
in memory underneath the hood.
在幕后内存中。
I can do a little better, though.
不过，我可以做得更好一些。
Let me zoom out.
让我缩小范围。
And let me upgrade, so to speak, from 32 bits to 64 bits and use
我可以说是从 32 位升级到 64 位，并使用
doubles instead.
双精度浮点数。
I can still use %f.
我仍然可以使用 %f。
You don't use %d for double.
你不应该对双精度浮点数使用 %d。
Let me do make calculator again, ./calculator, 1, 3.
让我再次制作计算器，./计算器，1，3。
I get more 3's but still some rounding.
我得到更多 3，但仍然有一些舍入。
It's more precise, but it's not 100% accurate,
它更精确，但它并不完全准确，
because that's just not going to be possible in terms
因为就计算机内存而言，这是不可能的。
of the computer's memory.
计算机的内存。
So this is a whole other issue known as floating point imprecision, which
所以，这是另一个问题，被称为浮点精度问题，它
is another type of limitation.
是另一种限制。
We saw integer overflow, if integers can only
我们看到了整数溢出，如果整数只能
count so high before you run out of bits and things wrap around.
计数到一定程度，然后你就用完了位，然后就会发生溢出。
Floating point imprecision means that you can't possibly
浮点精度问题意味着你不可能
represent the infinite number of real numbers that exist in the universe
表示宇宙中存在的无限多个实数
if you only have a finite amount of memory.
如果你只有有限的内存。
You would need an infinite number of bits, it would seem.
看起来你需要无限多个位。
So these are two issues that actually fundamentally
所以，这些问题实际上从根本上
can influence the correctness not only of
会影响代码的正确性，不仅是
your code but code in the real world.
你的代码，也包括现实世界中的代码。
And case in point, back in my day--
举个例子，在我那个时代 -
I graduated in 1999-- and a lot of the world
我毕业于 1999 年 - 当时世界上的许多人
thought the world was going to end around then
都认为世界将在那时终结
because around the time the years rolled over from 1999 to 2000,
因为在年份从 1999 年跨越到 2000 年的时候，
there was a lot of old software still running in the world.
世界上还有很多旧软件在运行。
And in fact, that old software, reasonably so,
事实上，那些旧软件，也是合情合理的，
only used two digits to represent years.
只用两位数字来表示年份。
Why?
为什么？
Memory was very expensive early on.
早期内存非常昂贵。
And if you could use half as much memory to store a year, that was a win.
如果你能用一半的内存来存储一年，那就是胜利。
That saved you money.
这为你节省了钱。
That saved you memory.
这为你节省了内存。
The problem though, of course, is that a lot
但是问题是，当然，很多
of old software from the '70s and prior was still running in 1999.
来自 70 年代及之前的旧软件在 1999 年仍然在运行。
And unless companies or individuals updated that software,
而且除非公司或个人更新这些软件，
1999 might be mistaken for the year 1900 instead of 2000,
1999 可能会被误认为是 1900 年而不是 2000 年，
because all of the code just assumed that, of course,
因为所有代码都假设，当然，
we're talking about the 1900s.
我们说的是 1900 年代。
This code is not going to be running 50 years later,
这段代码不会在 50 年后运行，
but it was still in that case.
但它仍然是这种情况。
So people had to scramble, and they essentially
所以人们不得不争先恐后，他们基本上
had to solve this by using more digits, so upgrading from two to four.
不得不通过使用更多位数来解决这个问题，所以从两位数升级到四位数。
Nowadays, and really since the '70s too, we've
如今，实际上从 70 年代起，我们一直
used 32-bit integers to keep track of time,
使用 32 位整数来跟踪时间，
specifically keeping track of the number of seconds
具体来说，跟踪的是自 1970 年 1 月 1 日以来的秒数，
using an integer from January 1, 1970, the so-called epoch whereby
使用一个整数，自 1970 年 1 月 1 日起，也就是所谓的纪元，因此
that's just an arbitrary date early on where we just started counting time.
那只是一个早期的任意日期，我们从那时起就开始计算时间。
So all of the clocks in your Macs, PCs, and phones pretty much
所以你的 Mac、PC 和手机上的所有时钟基本上
just have a single integer that gets updated every second,
只有一个整数，每秒更新一次，
but it's just keeping track not of absolute time per se,
但它只是在跟踪时间本身，而不是绝对时间，
but how many seconds have passed since January 1, 1970,
而是自 1970 年 1 月 1 日以来，经过了多少秒，
just because that's the date humans chose.
仅仅是因为那是人类选择的日子。
The problem is you can only count as high as 4 billion,
问题是，你只能数到 40 亿，
give or take, with 32 bits and actually 2 billion, give or take,
左右，使用 32 位，实际上是 20 亿，左右，
if you support negative numbers, as well.
如果你也支持负数的话。
And the problem with that is that we're about to trip over the same issue
而问题是，我们很快就会再次遇到同样的问题
again in not too long from now.
不久之后。
This is the 2038 problem because in the year 2038, on that date, mark my words,
这就是 2038 年问题，因为在 2038 年，在那一天，记住我的话，
things could break again.
事情可能会再次崩溃。
Why?
为什么？
Because that 32-bit value is going to accidentally wrap
因为那个 32 位的值会意外地溢出
around back to a 0 or a negative value.
回到 0 或负值。
So we're going to go through the whole darn process again.
所以我们又要经历一遍整个过程。
Now, thankfully the solution, as you might expect, is kind of just
现在，谢天谢地，解决方案，正如你可能预期的那样，只是
to kick the can even further down the road
把问题推迟到更远的时间
and use 64 bits, which I think will get us another 290 million years of runway.
并使用 64 位，我认为这将为我们提供另外 2.9 亿年的运行时间。
It's more than twice.
它超过了两倍。
So it's not our problem anymore at that point.
所以到那时它就不再是我们问题了。
But that's fundamentally going to be the solution.
但从根本上来说，这将是解决方案。
But it will still be finite.
但它仍然是有限的。
So we're just deferring to our descendants
所以我们只是推迟到我们子孙
to actually deal with the issue some millions of years from now
来处理这个问题，可能是在数百万年后。
if these things are still running.
如果这些东西还在运行。
So if that does happen, here's the specific date
所以如果这种情况发生，这里有一个具体的日期
that, in 2038, all of a sudden our clocks will still
也就是在 2038 年，突然我们的时钟仍然会
think because a negative number will get subtracted to the current epoch time.
认为时间在进行，因为当前纪元时间会减去一个负数。
So it will think we're back in 1901.
所以它会认为我们回到了 1901 年。
So this has had some fun and very real world implications.
所以这带来了一些有趣的，非常现实的影响。
So for instance, this is the game Pac-Man, which you might have played.
例如，这是你可能玩过的游戏吃豆人。
It kind of came out around my day, back in time.
它是在我那个年代，也就是很久以前推出的。
And if you get to the 256th level, this unfortunately
如果你到达了第 256 关，不幸的是
is what happens because they didn't really
这就是会发生的事，因为他们并没有真正地
expect that players would spend all this much time playing Pac-Man apparently.
期望玩家会花这么多时间玩吃豆人。
And they didn't really have a condition saying,
他们并没有设定一个条件，
you win if you get to the 255th or 266th level.
如果你到达了第 255 关或第 266 关，你就赢了。
And so what happens here essentially is that the whole screen gets very
所以，这里实际上发生的是，整个屏幕变得非常
garbled because there's an integer in the original Pac-Man that
混乱，因为在最初的吃豆人游戏中，有一个整数
counts to 256, but that's too big, so it wraps back around to 0.
计数到 256，但这个数字太大了，所以它会回绕到 0。
And it doesn't know when to stop printing fruits on the screen,
它不知道何时停止在屏幕上打印水果，
as in this case, to collect.
就像在这种情况下，来收集。
Another example of this is actually from the original Donkey Kong
另一个例子实际上来自最初的 Donkey Kong
game, which looks something like this in my day, too, whereby in Donkey Kong,
游戏，在我那个年代看起来就像这样，在 Donkey Kong 中，
there was this mathematical formula, whereby
有一个数学公式，通过它
the number of seconds you have to solve the game was a function of 10 times
你用来通关游戏所需的时间是一个函数，是 10 乘以
your current level number plus the number 4.
你当前的关卡号再加上 4。
That dictated how many seconds you get.
这决定了你能得到多少秒。
So of course, the higher the level, you get more and more time
所以，当然，关卡越高，你获得的时间就越多
as the level climbs.
随着关卡的提升。
Unfortunately, once you hit level 22, the math ends up being 10 times
不幸的是，一旦你到达第 22 关，计算结果就变成了 10 乘以
22 plus 4, which gives you the number 260.
22 加上 4，结果是 260。
And they, too, were using 8-bit values, a single byte
他们也使用了 8 位的值，一个字节
to represent numbers, which means 260 is bigger than 256.
来表示数字，这意味着 260 比 256 大。
And the way that math worked out was, well,
而计算结果是，嗯，
260 minus 256, if it wraps back around, gave people four seconds to solve level
260 减去 256，如果它回绕，人们就有 4 秒钟来解决第
22, which is just impossible.
22 关，这几乎是不可能的。
Like, Mario can't even get up a couple of levels
就像，马里奥甚至不能从他所在的位置向上爬几关
or so from where he actually was.
或者更多。
So that, too, was sort of a well-known bug,
所以，这也是一个众所周知的错误，
as well, since that works out to be there.
因为结果就是那样。
Lastly, and this one is all the more real, in 2015,
最后，这是一个更为现实的例子，在 2015 年，
Boeing 787 was documented as having not a hardware bug but a software bug
波音 787 被记录为出现了一个软件错误，而不是硬件错误
in the following sense.
具体来说就是
"A model 787 airplane that has been powered continuously for 248 days
“一架 787 型飞机，如果连续运行 248 天
can lose all of its power due to the control unit simultaneously going
可能会因为控制单元同时进入
into failsafe mode.
安全模式而失去所有动力。
This condition was caused by a software counter that will overflow
这种情况是由软件计数器引起的，该计数器会在
after 248 days of continuous power.
连续供电 248 天后溢出。
Boeing at the time was in the process of developing a CPU software upgrade that
当时，波音正在开发一个 CPU 软件升级，
will remedy the unsafe condition."
将解决这个不安全状况。”
And people did the math.
人们做了计算。
It turns out that Boeing was probably using an integer that was 32 bits.
事实证明，波音可能使用了一个 32 位的整数。
And they were keeping track of time not in seconds but hundredths of seconds,
他们跟踪时间的单位不是秒，而是百分之一秒，
because if you do out the math, after a 32-bit value has reached 4 billion--
因为如果你算一下，当一个 32 位的值达到 40 亿--
or 2 billion one hundredths of a second, the number wraps around back to 0,
或者 20 亿个百分之一秒后，这个数字会回绕到 0，
or negative 2 billion.
或者负 20 亿。
And the implications was literally the plane's power would stop.
而结果就是飞机的动力会停止。
And if you can believe it, if you grew up with Windows, macOS, or whatnot,
如果你相信，如果你在 Windows、macOS 或其他操作系统下长大，
anyone want to conjecture what the solution was
有人想推测解决方案是什么
until Boeing updated their software?
直到波音更新了他们的软件？
STUDENT: Turn it off, turn it back on.
学生：关掉它，再打开它。
DAVID MALAN: Turn the plane off, and turn it
戴维·马兰：关掉飞机，然后打开它
back on because that has the effect of resetting its memory and therefore
因为它会重置它的内存，从而
all of its variables back to 0.
将它的所有变量重置为 0。
So this is ultimately to say as you dive into problem set 1, your first in C,
所以，总而言之，当你开始学习问题集 1，也就是你的第一个 C 语言问题集时，
you, too, will make quite a few mistakes when it comes to correctness.
你也会在正确性方面犯不少错误。
You, too, will encounter opportunities for better design and better style.
你也会遇到改进设计和风格的机会。
In the real world, there are very much these issues.
在现实世界中，这些问题非常普遍。
So even if you struggle, know that for better or for worse,
所以即使你遇到了困难，也要知道，无论好坏，
you're in very good company.
你并不孤单。
But some three months from now, you will be in much better shape
但三个月后，你会变得更好
because this was week 1, and this is CS50.
因为这是第一周，这里是 CS50。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
[INTRIGUING MUSIC]
[引人入胜的音乐]